<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2015 OpenLink Software
 -
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -
 -
-->
<refentry id="RD-V-1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>RDF Views</refentrytitle>
    <refmiscinfo>tutorial</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>RDF Views</refname>
    <refpurpose>Develop custom RDF views for NorthWind database.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1 id="RD-V-1a">
    <title>Concept</title>
    <para>
      RDF Views map relational data into RDF and allow customizing RDF representation of locally
      stored RDF data. To let SPARQL clients access relational data as well as physical RDF graphs
      in a single query, we introduce a declarative Meta Schema Language for mapping SQL Data to
      RDF Ontologies. As a result, all types of clients can efficiently access all data stored on
      the server. The mapping functionality dynamically generates RDF Data Sets for popular ontologies
      such as SIOC, SKOS, FOAF, and ATOM/OWL without disruption to the existing database infrastructure
      of Web 1.0 or Web 2.0 solutions. RDF views are also suitable for declaring custom representation
      for RDF triples, e.g. property tables, where one row holds many single-valued properties.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Virtuoso RDF Views meta schema is a built-in feature of Virtuoso's SPARQL to SQL
      translator. It recognizes triple patterns that refer to graphs for which an alternate
      representation is declared and translates these into SQL accordingly. The main purpose
      of this is evaluating SPARQL queries against existing relational databases. There exists
      previous work from many parties for rendering relational data as RDF and opening it to
      SPARQL access. We can mention D2RQ, SPASQL, Squirrel RDF, DBLP and others. The Virtuoso
      effort differs from these mainly in the following:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        Integration with a triple store. Virtuoso can process a query for which some
        triple patterns will go to local or remote relational data and some to local physical
        RDF triples.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        SPARQL query can be used in any place where SQL can. Database connectivity protocols
        are neutral to the syntax of queries they transmit, thus any SQL client, e.g. JDBC,
        ODBC or XMLA application, can send SPARQL queries and fetch result sets. Moreover,
        a SQL query may contain SPARQL subqueries and SPARQL expressions may use SQL built-in
        functions and stored procedures.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Integration with SQL. Since SPARQL and SQL share the same run time and query optimizer,
        the query compilation decisions are always made with the best knowledge of the data and
        its location. This is especially important when mixing triples and relational data or
        when dealing with relational data distributed across many outside databases.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        No limits on SPARQL. It remains possible to make queries with unspecified graph or
        predicate against mapped relational data, even though these may sometimes be inefficient.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Coverage of the whole relational model. Multi-part keys etc. are supported in all places.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="RD-V-1b">
    <title>Quad Map Patterns, Value and IRI Classes</title>
    <para>
      In the simplest sense, any relational schema can be rendered into RDF by converting all primary
      keys and foreign keys into IRI's, assigning a predicate IRI to each column, and an rdf:type predicate
      for each row linking it to a RDF class IRI corresponding to the table. Then a triple with the primary
      key IRI as subject, the column IRI as predicate and the column's value as object is considered to exist
      for each column that is neither part of a primary or foreign key.
    </para>
    <para>
      Strictly equating a subject value to a row and each column to a predicate is often good but is too
      restrictive for the general case.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        Multiple triples with the same subject and predicate can exist.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        A single subject can get single-valued properties from multiple tables or in some cases stored procedures.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        An IRI value of a subject or other field of a triple can be composed from more than one SQL value,
        these values may reside in different columns, maybe in different joined tables.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        Some table rows should be excluded from mapping.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Thus in the most common case the RDF meta schema should consist of independent transformations; the domain
      of each transformation is a result-set of some SQL SELECT statement and range is a set of triples. The
      SELECT that produce the domain is quite simple: it does not use aggregate functions, joins and sorting,
      only inner joins and WHERE conditions. There is no need to support outer joins in the RDF meta schema
      because NULLs are usually bad inputs for functions that produce IRIs. In the rare cases when NULLs are
      OK for functions, outer joins can be encapsulated in SQL views. The range of mapping can be described
      by a SPARQL triple pattern: a pattern field is a variable if it depends on table columns, otherwise it
      is a constant. Values of variables in the pattern may have additional restrictions on datatypes, when
      datatypes of columns are known.
    </para>
    <para>
      This common case of an RDF meta schema is implemented in Virtuoso, with one adjustment. Virtuoso stores
      quads, not triples, using the graph field (G) to indicate that a triple belongs to some particular
      application or resource. A SPARQL query may use quads from different graphs without large difference
      between G and the other three fields of a quad. E.g., variable ?g in expression GRAPH ?g {...} can be
      unbound. SPARQL has special syntax for "graph group patterns" that is convenient for sets of triple
      patterns with a common graph, but it also has shorthands for common subject and predicate, so the
      difference is no more than in syntax. There is only one feature that is specific for graphs but not
      for other fields: the SPARQL compiler can create restrictions on graphs according to FROM and FROM
      NAMED clauses.
    </para>
    <para>
      Virtuoso RDF Views should offer the same flexibility with the graphs as SPARQL addressing physical triples.
      A transformation cannot always be identified by the graph used for ranges because graph may be composed
      from SQL data. The key element of the meta schema is a "quad map pattern". A simple quad map pattern fully
      defines one particular transformation from one set of relational columns into triples that match one SPARQL
      graph pattern. The main part of quad map pattern is four declarations of "quad map values", each declaration
      specifies how to calculate the value of the corresponding triple field from the SQL data. The pattern also
      lists boolean SQL expressions that should be used to filter out unwanted rows of source data (and to join
      multiple tables if source columns belong to different tables). There are also quad map patterns that group
      together similar quad patterns but do not specify any real transformation or even prevent unwanted
      transformations from being used, they are described in "Grouping Map Patterns" below.
    </para>
    <para>
      Quad map values refer to schema elements of two further types: "IRI classes" and "literal classes".
    </para>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="RD-V-1c">
    <title>Implementation</title>
    <para>
      In the example script we implement RDF Views for Northwind tables (Customers, Orders, Order Details, Products,
      Product Categories, Employee, Region, Country, Province).
    </para>
    <para>
      To test the mapper we just use /sparql to execute:
    </para>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[
        sparql select ?o where { graph ?g {?s ?p ?o . filter(?p like '%Country%') }} limit 10;
    ]]></programlisting>
    <para>
      Or use <a href="/isparql" >iSparql</a> application.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
