<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes" ?>
<!--
 -
 -  $Id$
 -
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2014 OpenLink Software
 -
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -
-->
<wahelp>

  <help page="welcome">
    <title>Welcome to Virtuoso Web Applications</title>
    <para>This is the Virtuoso Web Applications home page.  If site-wide registration
  is enabled you may register yourself and begin using web applications hosted here.  After
  successful login you will be able to create your own application instances and join others.</para>
  <para>Some public application instances are shown for you to view and join if the service policy permits.
  If you are looking for a particular service or service containing particular information you can
  enter specific criteria in the search box to find any relevant instance.</para>

  <sect><title>Registration</title>
  <para>Before you can use this site you must have a suitable login.  If the policy of the site
  permits public registration then you may use the "Register" button to begin registration.
  For registration you will need an email address.  After providing some other details your
  email address may be used for verification or your details.</para>
  </sect>
  <sect><title>Login Problems</title>
  <para>Use of in-correct login details will reveal a button "Forgot your password" that will
  lead you through your security question to the recovery of your password.</para>
  </sect>

  </help>

  <help page="site">
    <title>Default Site Administration</title>
    <para></para>

  <sect><title>Mail Server Settings</title>
    <para>In order to send confirmation emails you must ensure that this server can
  send emails. The Virtuoso INI file may contain the setting for the
  <emphasis>"DefaultMailServer"</emphasis>, which can be used or overridden.
  This default mail setting is shown.  Use the checkbox to use the default or specify
  an alternative. </para>
    <para>Emails regarding the default WA site will be sent to the Administrator
  (DAV); you must ensure the administrators email address is valid.  Use the
  <emphasis>Test</emphasis> button to send the Administrator a test mail.
  You can change the Administrators email address from here.</para>
  </sect>

  <sect><title>System Mail Templates</title>
  <para>These are the mails that the WA will send to its users in response
  to particular actions.  You must enable "verify registration by email" above
  before any emails will be sent.</para>
  <para>The mails support some string-substitutions for personalized emails
  as follows:</para>

  <simplelist>
    <member><emphasis>%app%</emphasis>
      name of application type in question (weblog, wiki)</member>
    <member><emphasis>%wa_home%</emphasis>
      the home page of the wa</member>
    <member><emphasis>%app_owner%</emphasis>
      owner of the application instance</member>
    <member><emphasis>%app_name%</emphasis>
      the name of the application instance</member>
    <member><emphasis>%app_url%</emphasis>
      the preferred url to the application, usually a virtual directory?</member>
    <member><emphasis>%app_action_url%</emphasis>
      The url for continuing the action</member>
    <member><emphasis>%user%</emphasis>
      the users full name</member>
    <member><emphasis>%username%</emphasis>
      the user name</member>
    <member><emphasis>%password%</emphasis>
      the password</member>
    <member><emphasis>%timeout_join%</emphasis>
      the timeout for the join</member>
    <member><emphasis>%timeout_reg%</emphasis>
      the timeout for the registration</member>
    <member><emphasis>%apps_available%</emphasis>
      this will be a list of applications available in the format of name, line space, description </member>
    </simplelist>
  </sect>
  </help>

  <help page="index">
    <title></title>
    <para></para>
  </help>

  <fragment name="forgotpassword">
    <title></title>
    <para></para>
  </fragment>

  <help page="conf">
    <title></title>
    <para></para>
  </help>

  <help page="edit_inst">
    <title></title>
    <para></para>
  </help>

  <help page="inst">
    <title>Virtuoso Web Applications Management</title>
    <para>This page will show you what application you own or are a member of, and also
  other public application instances that you may view or join.  </para>
  <para>You may search for specific types of application instance or
  instances with particular information.  Depending on the policy of the service you
  may be able to join.</para>
  <sect><title>User Profile</title>
  <para>You may alter you personal or login details using the button
  provided.  You can also change your password.</para>
  </sect>
  <sect><title>Application Endpoint Administration</title>
  <para>You may alter the host/domain settings of your applications to provide more
  convenient URLs to remember them by.  You can choose from the site registered domain
  names or enter one based on your own Internet domain registration if you have one.</para>
  </sect>
  <sect><title>Applications</title>
  <para>This section shows details of applications that are hosted on this site.  Click on one
  to create your own application instance of such.  Then you can begin using it.</para>
  </sect>
  </help>

  <help page="join">
    <title></title>
    <para></para>
  </help>

  <help page="member_edit">
    <title></title>
    <para></para>
  </help>

  <help page="members">
    <title></title>
    <para></para>
  </help>

  <help page="new_inst">
    <title>Creating a New Application Instance</title>
    <para>This page lets you create an instance of the select application type.</para>
  <sect><title>Instance Name</title>
    <para>The new name of the instance you are creating.  This must be a
    site-wide unique name so your choice may have already been used.  By default your
    username is appended to the service type name as a suggestion since username are
    also site-unique.</para>
  </sect>
  <sect><title>Instance Description</title>
      <para>This can be any description that you wish to provide for your new instance.
    It should be as informative as possible especially if this instance is going to visible to the
    public.  This description may be used to provide the public with information about the
    nature of the instance.  It will also be used as search criteria.</para>
  </sect>
  <sect><title>Member Model</title>
      <para>This setting refers to the way the public can interact with your
    new application instance.  The options are:</para>
    <simplelist>
      <member><emphasis>Open</emphasis> - will allow any member to join your
    instance without requiring your consent or knowledge.  You will be able to see
    who is a member of instance at any time and revoke memberships but will not
    receive any join notifications.</member>
      <member><emphasis>Closed</emphasis> - No one will be able to join your instance.</member>
      <member><emphasis>Invitation Only</emphasis> - Only users specifically invited by
    you will be able to join the instance.  Invites are sent to a prospective users
    email address with a URL to proceed.</member>
      <member><emphasis>Approval Based</emphasis> - Any user may request to
    join your instance.  A notification will be sent to your email address asking you to
    accept of reject the request of the user.  They will not be permitted to complete the
    join without your approval.</member>
  </simplelist>
  </sect>
  <sect><title>Is Public</title>
      <para>This option defines whether the instance will be available for the public
    to view.  If this option is off then only logged-in members will be able to view the
    instance.  With this option disabled your application instance will not be listed on
    the Web Applications home page or be obtainable from a public initiated search.</para>
  </sect>
  <sect><title>Is Members Visible</title>
      <para>This option restricts access further to "Is Public" but preventing your instance
    be searchable by its members.</para>
  </sect>
  </help>

  <help page="pass_recovery">
    <title></title>
    <para></para>
  </help>

  <help page="register">
    <title></title>
    <para></para>
  </help>

  <help page="vhost">
    <title></title>
    <para></para>
  </help>

</wahelp>
