<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2012 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<refentry id="XA-S-1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>XMLA</refentrytitle>
    <refmiscinfo>tutorial</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>XML for Analysis</refname>
    <refpurpose>XML for Analysis</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

<refsect1 id="XA-S-1">
<title>Example</title>
<para>
The Virtuoso server can act as XML for Analysis (XMLA) tabular data provider.
XML for Analysis is a SOAP based XML API, 
designed specifically for data access interaction between a 
client application and a data provider working over the Web. 
The client application can do discovery of data provider information 
and execute of SQL statements. The result sets from server to client can be 
Multidimensonal and Tabular, at current state only Tabular is supported.
To setup an virtual directory to act as XMLA data provider, it needs to be 
defined as SOAP one and Discover and Execute procedures needs to be granted to the 
user account for SOAP execution.</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">

 <listitem>The example shows how SOAP enabled virtual directory can be exposed for XMLA.</listitem>
 <listitem>The SQL statements for setting up the virtual directory are shown in the .sql file</listitem>
 <listitem>In addition to the virtual directory setup, there is a grant to the Northwind Customers table 
 to be able to invoke select on that table via Execute method.
 </listitem>
 <listitem>The example XMLA client is a simplest browser of XMLA provider</listitem>
 <listitem>It allows to browse the data, do execute of SQL statements and such</listitem>
 <listitem>To try the example do load the script, start the VSP example and follow the steps</listitem>
</itemizedlist> 
</refsect1>
</refentry>
