<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2013 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<refentry id="SO-S-37">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>SOAP</refentrytitle>
    <refmiscinfo>tutorial</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>Northwind query via SOAP</refname>
    <refpurpose>Building a document style oriented Web services</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsect1 id="SO-S-37a">
      <title>Preliminaries</title>
      <para>The SOAP messages are XML documents which may follow 
	  encoding rules or an XML Schema. The ones that follow encoding rules 
	  are known as RPC encoded, so the 
	  XML Schema following messages are known as Document/literal encoded. 
	  Most of SOAP toolkits can work with both kind of messages, but for some purposes 
	  RPC encoded messages are not suitable. 
      </para>
      <para>The MS Office Infopath supports only document/literal encoded SOAP 
	  messages. So to inter operate with it, Web services have to be set to define 
	  document/literal SOAP messages and generate appropriate WSDL file.</para>
      <para>The Virtuoso can expose a services that using document/literal encoding by two ways:</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
	  <listitem>explicit declarations in stored procedure's definition</listitem>
	  <listitem>default SOAP encoding as an option of the SOAP enabled virtual directory</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
	  The first approach imply that procedure can be used only in the designated 
	  encoding style. So the second is more flexabile as it can switch very easy 
	  between encodings without procedure's re-definition.   
      </para>
      <para>
	  To allow a stored procedure to be exposed in a virtual directory 
	  that default SOAP encoding as a document/literal it should not use 
	  explicit declarations. This is because explicit declarations are not 
	  compatible in all cases. Instead of explicit declarations a user defined types 
	  must be used to describe the structures and array modifier have to be used to 
	  describe array parameters. 
      </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1 id="SO-S-37b">
      <title>Example</title>
      <para>The example script defines a service that do a query on Northwind Demo Database 
      and return an array of structures containing sales volume per product category.</para>
  <para>To run example, set the initial state and then click on the Run link or point
  	your browser to <ulink url="/NorthwindSvc/services.vsmx">http://[host]:[port]/NorthwindSvc/services.vsmx</ulink> 
  	to go to vsmx test pages.</para>
  <para>
      Note: the dateinput must follow ISO8601 format (for example: YYYY-MM-DD'T'HH:MM:SS) 
  </para>
  </refsect1>

</refentry>
