<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2015 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<refentry id="vspx_template">
<refmeta>
  <refentrytitle>vspx_template</refentrytitle>
  <refmiscinfo>vspx_control</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
  <refname>vspx_template</refname>
  <refpurpose>container for controls or HTML code</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv>
  <funcsynopsis id="syn_vspx_template">
    <funcprototype id="proto_vspx_template">
      <funcdef>
        <function>template</function>
      </funcdef>
      <attributes>
        <attribute>name (required) </attribute>
        <attribute>annotation (optional) </attribute>
        <attribute>initial-enable (optional) </attribute>
        <attribute>type (optional) </attribute>
        <attribute>redirect (optional) </attribute>
        <attribute>condition (optional) </attribute>
        <attribute>name-to-remove (optional) </attribute>
        <attribute>set-to-remove (optional) </attribute>
      </attributes>
      <childs>
        <child>after-data-bind</child>
        <child>after-data-bind-container</child>
        <child>before-data-bind</child>
        <child>before-data-bind-container</child>
        <child>on-post</child>
        <child>on-post-container</child>
        <child>before-render</child>
        <child>before-render-container</child>
        <child>radio-button</child>
        <child>button</child>
        <child>check-box</child>
        <child>select-list</child>
        <child>textarea</child>
        <child>text</child>
        <child>update-field</child>
        <child>key</child>
        <child>variable</child>
        <child>label</child>
        <child>url</child>
        <child>data-grid</child>
        <child>data-set</child>
        <child>data-list</child>
        <child>tab</child>
        <child>tree</child>
        <child>include</child>
        <child>error-summary</child>
        <child>radio-button</child>
        <child>button</child>
        <child>check-box</child>
        <child>select-list</child>
        <child>textarea</child>
        <child>text</child>
        <child>update-field</child>
        <child>key</child>
        <child>node</child>
        <child>form</child>
        <child>template</child>
        <child>login</child>
        <child>login-form</child>
      </childs>
      <class>
        <screen><![CDATA[
				
				create type vspx_template under vspx_control
                                temporary self as ref
                                constructor method vspx_template (name varchar, parent vspx_control)
                                ;
			    	-- repeatable version
				create type vspx_row_template under vspx_control
				as (
				    te_rowset any, 		-- the row data, vector in order as in columns selected
				    te_ctr int default 0,	-- index in result set
				    te_editable int default 0	-- edit is enabled
				   ) temporary self as ref
				constructor method vspx_row_template (name varchar,rowset any, parent vspx_control, ctr int)
				;
				
			    ]]>
        </screen>
      </class>
    </funcprototype>
  </funcsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1 id="desc_vspx_template">
  <title>Description</title>
  <para>
    <function>vspx_template</function>The container for any optional, repeatable or otherwise grouped controls or code. The type modifier is used to specify special kind of templates (i.e. repeatable content or tree node representation)</para>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="attrs_vspx_template">
  <title>Attributes</title>
  <refsect2>
    <title>name</title>
    <para>A unique name identifying the control.</para>
  </refsect2>
  <refsect2>
    <title>annotation</title>
    <para>A human readable comment.</para>
  </refsect2>
  <refsect2>
    <title>initial-enable</title>
    <para>Designates is control visible or not initially. Could be data-bound to an SQL expression.</para>
  </refsect2>
  <refsect2>
    <title>type</title>
    <para>The behaviour of the template.</para>
    <para>
         &#39;row&#39; : A repeating row of v:data-set. The template of this type will be repeated for each row in the window of the data-set. It will be instantiated, data bound, rendered.  If the template contains forms and submits, they get the post method called as one would expect.
On data binding, the parent of the template has its dg_current_row data member set to an array representing the selected row from left to right. 

The controls under this template (such as text, label, button etc.) can access data in current row in order as columns are given by referencing te_rowset member of row template.

(NOT IMPLEMENTED!!!: Also the method vc_get_field can be used on the data_grid to get a named column value for the current row for data binding a child of the template when instantiating the template.)
    
</para>
    <para>
         &#39;frame&#39; : 
OBSOLETE! A non-repeating static content of v:data-grid.
Content of this template represents view in page when rows are selected,
position of scroll buttons, rowset and form for adding a record.
</para>
    <para>
         &#39;if-exists&#39; : 
Template that is enabled only if the resultset is not empty in v:data-set.
</para>
    <para>
         &#39;if-not-exists&#39; : Template that is enabled only if the resultset is empty in v:data-set.</para>
    <para>
         &#39;add&#39; : Template that is enabled when user adds new record in the resultset in v:data-set (if the resultset is not read-only).
Similarly to templates of type &#39;edit&#39;, the &#39;add&#39; template contains a vspx:form of type &#39;update&#39; that is used to allow adding of rows in table as specified.
Usually this form is a update-form + update-fields constrained to columns and table selected in SQL expression of the parent vspx:data-set control with value of key attributes set to null. Please remember to set the &#39;if-not-exists&#39; attribute of the form to &#39;insert&#39;.</para>
    <para>
         &#39;edit&#39; : Template that is enabled when user edits an existing record in the resultset in v:data-set (if the resultset isnot read-only and if the &#39;edit&#39; attribute of v:data-set is set to &#39;true&#39;).
The template of this type usually contains a vspx:form of type &#39;update&#39;;
the &#39;table&#39; attribute of the form is the name of the table from &#39;sql&#39; attribute of the v:data-set where the &#39;edit&#39; template is located; controls of the form are usually constrained to columns of the SQL expression of that &#39;sql&#39; attribute.</para>
    <para>
         &#39;if-login&#39; : Template that is enabled when user is logged in (e.g. for use in v:login. If the login is valid, the contents of this child will be instantiated.  This can be for example a button with &#39;action&#39; attribute set to &#39;logout&#39;, a welcome message or such.  When using the vspx:login system, the user name is is obtained by connection_get (&#39;vspx_user&#39;).</para>
    <para>
         &#39;if-not-login&#39; : Template that is enabled when user is not yet logged in or is already logged out (e.g. for use in v:login.
The template specifies what to do if there are no credentials with the page.
If the &#39;redirect&#39; attribute is given, then the entire page containing
this is not processed at all but instead the page specified in the url
is processed instead, with the context being that of the invocation of
this page.  The redirect page can thus ask for the login and having
checked it return to this page, since it knows the url for this.  In
this way it is possible to bookmark places of which the uri&#39;s may
expire, and accessing an expired place will just prompt for the login
before going to the page.


If the redirect is not specified, the content of the template is instantiated and shown. The content can be arbitrary, e.g. the vspx:login-form control can appear here, providing a standard login form that prompts for a user name and password and has a submit button.</para>
    <para>
         &#39;tree-node&#39; : 
Template for internal nodes of the tree in v:tree (i.e. for nodes with children).
</para>
    <para>
         &#39;tree-leaf&#39; : 
Template for terminal nodes of the tree in v:tree (i.e. for nodes without children).
</para>
  </refsect2>
  <refsect2>
    <title>redirect</title>
    <para>The URL to be redirected user-agent if not authenticated, applicable only when type is &#39;if-no-login&#39;.</para>
  </refsect2>
  <refsect2>
    <title>condition</title>
    <para>This is a SQL expression to be tested for rendering the template</para>
  </refsect2>
  <refsect2>
    <title>name-to-remove</title>
    <para>This works together with set-to-remove, see next.</para>
  </refsect2>
  <refsect2>
    <title>set-to-remove</title>
    <para>This combined with name-to-remove gives possibility to remove a HTML elements from output.</para>
    <para>
         &#39;top&#39; : 
The rendered output of the enclosing template should not contain the first opening tag whose name is equal to the value of &#39;name-to-remove&#39; attribute of the template.
</para>
    <para>
         &#39;bottom&#39; : 
The rendered output of the enclosing template should not contain the last closing tag whose name is equal to the value of &#39;name-to-remove&#39; attribute of the template.
</para>
    <para>
         &#39;both&#39; : 
The rendered output of the enclosing template should not contain the both the first opening tag and the last closing tag whose name is equal to the value of &#39;name-to-remove&#39; attribute of the template.
</para>
  </refsect2>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="childs_vspx_template">
  <title>Children</title>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="examples_vspx_template">
  <title>Examples</title>
  <example id="ex_vspx_template">
    <title>Simple example</title>
    <para>Simple template, used in vspx:tab control
			    </para>
    <screen><![CDATA[
				
				<v:template name="template1" type="simple">
				This is a first template <br />
				</v:template>
				
			    ]]>
    </screen>
  </example>
</refsect1>
</refentry>