<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2019 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->

<sect2 id="webdavadmin">
  <title>WebDAV Administration</title>
  <para>DAV, or WebDAV, is a protocol for Web-based Distributed Authoring and Versioning. The location
where content items are placed is called the <emphasis>repository</emphasis>. Content elements are called
<emphasis>documents</emphasis>, corresponding to files, and <emphasis>folders/collections</emphasis>,
corresponding to directories. Collectively these documents and folders (collections) are known as
<emphasis>resources</emphasis>.
  </para>
  <para>Virtuoso implements the DAV protocol, allowing you to create and manage resources either directly
through repository manipulations or indirectly, through a variety of WebDAV services.
  </para>
  <sect3 id="resourcetypes">
			<title>DAV Resource Types</title>
    <para>To make sure that when Virtuoso serves files to client user agents the type of file is
conveyed properly so that the right application can be used with that file a list or file
types are maintained in the server. This list is used when sending any content via the HTTP
server which include content in DAV and under VSP.
    </para>
        <figure float="1"><title>DAV Resource Types</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/dav_resrctyp_01.png"/></figure>
		<para>
The Web Application Server/Content Management/Resource Types page shows the list of currently
defined resource types in the Virtuoso server. You can edit or remove these types by using the
action links on the right most column of the list next to the type applicable.
</para>
		<para>
Add new types by typing the details into the fields provided and pressing the <emphasis>Save</emphasis> button.
</para>
		</sect3>


    <sect3 id="contentmanagement"><title>Content Management</title>
  <para>The content management page gives you an interface to the WebDAV
  repository resources. From here you can navigate or create directories, 
  commonly referred to as collections or folders in DAV, alter properties,
  upload or remove files, or edit documents.</para>

  <para>The Repository tab lists the current location within the tree and
  the current login name.  The root of the repository is usually 
  <code>/DAV/</code>.</para>

        <figure float="1"><title>Content Management</title>
          <graphic fileref="webdav.png"/></figure>

  <sect4 id="davcontresnames"><title>Resource Names</title>
  <para>Resource names are given with collection (folder) names listed first, 
  then individual documents.  Permissions on resources are presented in a 
  style similar to Unix, with (r)ead, (w)rite, and e(x)ecute permissions 
  listed for the resource owner (the user), the resource's group, and 
  for the general public.  If a permission is present, the letter is 
  shown; if not, it is replaced with a dash.</para>
  </sect4>

  <sect4 id="davcontresperm"><title>Resource Permissions</title>
  <para>Unlike Unix, the Repository does not use the designation 'd' for 
  directories, which in DAV are more commonly referred to as collections.  
  Collections are distinguished by a different icon - a folder-like icon
  - and by having the type named &quot;collection&quot;.</para>

  <para>In addition, the permissions string has a trailing letter designating
  the indexing status of the resource.  This letter is 'n' to designate 
  that indexing is off, 'r' for recursive indexing, and 't' for direct indexing.</para>
  </sect4>

  <sect4 id="davcontresug"><title>Resource User and Group</title>
  <para>By default, the user and group of a DAV resource are those set by the 
  service that created the resource, or they are the ID and primary group of 
  the user who was logged in when the resource was created.</para>
  </sect4>

  <sect4 id="davconterssize"><title>Resource Size</title>
  <para>The size of a document resource is its size in disk bytes.  Note that 
  this does not necessarily correspond to characters displayed on the 
  screen because of encodings.  For example, the HTML token 
  &amp;-a-m-p-semicolon is five bytes on disk but displays as a single 
  screen character.</para>
  </sect4>

  <sect4 id="davcontrestype"><title>Resource Type</title>
  <para>The type of a resource is always &quot;collection&quot; for 
  collections (folder).  For documents it can be any of the known resource 
  types (see Resource Types below).  The resource type is usually based on the 
  resource's extension; for example, .xml files are usually assumed to 
  be <code>text/xml</code>.  If Virtuoso does not recognize the extension of a 
  resource, it assigns the default type of <code>application/octet-stream</code>.</para>
  </sect4>

  <sect4 id="davcontpropedt"><title>Editing Properties</title>
  <para>Within the Content Management screen, you can change any of the 
  properties of a resource, other than its name, by selecting the 
  resource via the checkbox to the left of the icon, and pressing the 
  &quot;Properties&quot; button.</para>
  <figure float="1" id="editres"><title>Edit Resource Properties</title>
    <graphic fileref="ui/editres.png"/>
  </figure>

  <para>XML documents also permit you to edit their XML properties 
  specifically.  This can be done on any document of type text/xml by 
  clicking on the icon for the document.</para>

    <sect5 id="davcontresprops"><title>Properties</title>
    <para>When clicked this button from the bottom of the page, you can edit the properties
for one or a group of resources which should be selected. The name of a resource cannot be changed.</para>

    <para>The owner, group, permissions, and indexing controls on this form 
    apply to the appropriate properties of resources, as documented 
    above.  Changes to the type of a collection (folder) are ignored.</para>
  <figure float="1" id="meditres"><title>Multiple Resources Edit Properties</title>
    <graphic fileref="ui/meditres.png"/>
  </figure>
    <para>The &quot;Property&quot; control permits you to change or add
    additional properties.  There is a pulldown of predefined XML-related 
    properties, or you may create your own property.</para>
  <figure float="1" id="meditres2"><title>Multiple Resources Edit Properties</title>
    <graphic fileref="ui/meditres2.png"/>
  </figure>    
    </sect5>

    <sect5 id="davcontdavprop"><title>WebDAV Properties</title>
    <para>This control permits you to manipulate the specific properties of XML
    documents.  Existing properties are shown with their values, and can 
    be removed.  New properties can be added.</para>

    <para>XML-related properties are generally set by specific XML-related 
    services and do not need to be edited directly by users; however, this 
    interface provides a quick means to correct a minor typo or other 
    change without re-running the entire service.  For example, you 
    can change the <parameter>xml-sql-root</parameter> property, which 
    controls the name of the root XML element for the document.</para>
    </sect5>
    </sect4>

  <sect4 id="davaddnewres"><title>Adding New Resources</title>
  <para>Resources may be added to the repository in two ways: by uploading 
  files or by creating new collections (folders).  Buttons for both these methods 
  are on the page.</para>

  <para>The &quot;Create Folder&quot; button brings up a form in which you can 
  specify the name of the collection (folder), its owner and group, and the initial 
  permissions.  You may also turn on indexing for the folder's contents at this point.</para>
    <figure float="1" id="cfolder"><title>Create Folder</title>
    <graphic fileref="ui/cfolder.png"/>
  </figure>

  <para>The &quot;Upload File&quot; button brings up a form in which you can 
  specify the name and location of a file on your local computer that is 
  to be copied into the DAV repository.  You need to specify the name of 
  the resource in the repository and give it a type.  You can also set 
  the basic repository properties here.</para>
      <figure float="1" id="ufile"><title>Upload File</title>
    <graphic fileref="ui/ufile.png"/>
  </figure>

  <!--sect5 id="davadsymlink"><title>WebDAV Symbolic Linking</title>

<para>WebDAV symbolic linking, also known as <emphasis>DAV
redirection</emphasis>, is another method for accessing content from
your DAV repository.  Instead of directly copying or creating
resources, as described above, symbolic linking permits you to create
a reference to a resource.  In this sense it is similar to the
&quot;Create Shortcut&quot; feature of Windows, &quot;Make Alias&quot;
on MacOS, and the &quot;ln -s&quot; command on Unix systems.</para>

<para>This capability enables Virtuoso users to import resources from
a plethora of sites such as webzine articles and keep references to
these imported resources in sensible locations for future
reference.</para>

<para>In the Virtuoso Conductor WebDAV Content Manager, links appear and are
accessed just as you would see a created resource.  Their Type is
<parameter>Link:&lt;Target&gt;</parameter> where the target is the URL
of the resource being linked.</para>

<para>To create a link, you first navigate to the DAV Repository
location where you want the alias to reside.  Then click the Create
Link button at the bottom-right of the screen.  This brings you to a
screen where you can specify the Link Name, as it will appear in your
DAV Repository.  The Link to field can be given a full URL, as in the
example below, or you can use the Browse button to target a resource
elsewhere in the DAV.</para>

<para>Linked resources do not permit direct Edit operations.  You can
change the Target by editing the <parameter>redirectref</parameter>
property of the link.  To view the resource, simply click its
Name.</para>

<example id="ex_davsymlincs"><title>Examples:</title>

<para>If one wishes to keep a link to the article found at &lt;URL:
http://www.xml.com/pub/a/2001/10/17/slippery-soap.html&gt;  he/she would
simply click the Add Link button, type a useful local name, such as
&quot;Slippery SOAP article&quot; and paste the URL into the Link to
field.</para>

<para>More interesting, he/she could set up a Web Data Import for the
target &lt;URL:
http://news.cnet.com/news/0-1277-210-7545619-1.html?tag=bt_bh&gt;</para>

<para>When this URL target is imported, Virtuoso will replicate the
traversal path within the DAV repository that results in multiple
access point locations for each import. Using the symbolic link
feature, we are able to map the actual documents imported to a common
location without encountering problems related to component
references, embedded links, etc.</para>
</example>
</sect5-->

</sect4>
</sect3>

    <sect3 id="freetext"><title>Free Text</title>

		<sect4 id="contentidxmode">
			<title>Indexing Mode</title>
		<para>
When files are inserted into Virtuoso's WebDAV repository, if their type is a type of text file such
as plain text TXT, XML, or HTML, then they may be automatically free text indexed.
</para>
		<para>
By default files are automatically free text indexed as they are inserted into Virtuoso. This is
very convenient but can be time consuming if you frequently insert or update text files. For
this reason Virtuoso can be set to index in batch mode at a particular interval in minutes.
</para>
        <figure float="1"><title>DAV Free Text Index Configuration</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/dav_idxprprty_01.png"/></figure>
		<para>
To change the free-text index mode to batch mode check the check-box and provide a non-zero time interval (in minutes).
Press the <emphasis>Accept</emphasis> button to save the changes into the server.
</para>
		</sect4>
		</sect3>
</sect2>
