<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2006 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->

<chapter id="adminui" label="adminui.xml">
<title>Visual Server Administration Interface</title>
<abstract>
    <para>This chapter describes how to administer the Virtuoso server from 
    the VSP based user interface, written completely in VSP (Virtuoso Server 
    Pages) and runs directly from the Virtuoso HTTP server.
    These pages primarily allow users to administer the server while giving access
    to many of the features that Virtuoso has to offer providing many conceptual
    demonstrations and introductions.</para>
		<para>Most of the pages from the administration interface are provided to 
    help administrators quickly and easily tune the Virtuoso server or navigate 
    the various interfaces and features that Virtuoso has to offer.</para>
</abstract>
	<sect1 id="leftmenu">
		<title>The Menu</title>
		<para>The menu provides links to pages that allow you to administrate
your Virtuoso server or use one of the provided samples.
The menu is organized into tree structures that are separated by domain of use or functionality.
</para>
	<figure id="adminui001" float="1">
		<title>The Menu</title>
		<graphic fileref="menu-cutout.jpg" width="300px" depth="230px"/>
	</figure>
<para>
Click on the plus and minus icons to expand and contract sections of the menu to find the desired item.
</para>
	<figure id="adminuidatabase" float="1">
		<title>Database Administration</title>
		<graphic fileref="database.jpg" width="300px" depth="46px"/>
	</figure>
		<para>Use this section to manage the Virtuoso Relational Database System.  
    This module enables the management of database users; view table, view, 
    stored procedure and trigger definitions. Virtuoso's virtual database 
    functionality (linking to 3rd Party Database Tables, Views, and Stored 
    Procedures) is also administered via this module.
</para>
	<figure id="adminuiwebdav" float="1">
		<title>WebDAV Administration</title>
		<graphic fileref="webdav.jpg" width="300px" depth="46px"/>
	</figure>
		<para>Configure Virtuoso's WebDAV, and HTTP Server functionality, 
    this includes the ability to expose Persistent Stored Modules as Web Services.</para>
	<figure id="adminuiquerytools" float="1">
		<title>Query Tools</title>
		<graphic fileref="querytools.jpg" width="300px" depth="46px"/>
	</figure>
		<para>Simple query tools for Querying Relational and XML Data using SQL, 
    XQUERY, XPATH, and FREE TEXT.</para>
	<figure id="adminuireplication" float="1">
		<title>Replication</title>
		<graphic fileref="replication.jpg" width="300px" depth="46px"/>
	</figure>
		<para>You can create Snapshot Replications to copy sections of the Database 
    to remote locations or use Transactional Replication to keep Virtuoso Servers 
    in sync over a definable interval.</para>
	<figure id="adminuimail" float="1">
		<title>Mail Administration</title>
		<graphic fileref="mail.jpg" width="300px" depth="46px"/>
	</figure>
		<para>Compose e-mail for delivery via your SMTP mail server, and retrieve mail 
    from your POP3 server.</para>
	<figure id="adminuinntp" float="1">
		<title>NNTP Administration</title>
		<graphic fileref="nntp.jpg" width="300px" depth="46px"/>
	</figure>
		<para>Configure Virtuoso's NNTP support which includes linking third-party 
    NNTP servers into Virtuoso and controlling access to these servers. This 
    interface also enables the creation of free-text searches on newsgroup 
    data.</para>
	</sect1>

&adminui.runtimehosting;
&adminui.webservices;
&adminui.webdavadmin;
&adminui.internetdomains;
&adminui.xmlservices;
&adminui.querytools;
&adminui.replicationandsynchronization;
&adminui.dbadmin;
&adminui.mailsrvadm;
&adminui.newssrvadm;

</chapter>



