<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2018 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->

<sect2 id="admui.internetdomains"><title>Internet Domains</title>

	<sect3 id="httpvirtualdirs">
		<title>HTTP Virtual Directories</title>
	<para>From Virtual Domains &amp; Directories you can define Virtual HTTP directories. Virtual Directories
  let you define multiple HTTP server listeners in Virtuoso for either the same 
  network interface or another one.  Virtual directories can respond logically 
  to a name or directly by IP address.  Both types as well as default responses 
  can be defined here.</para>
  <para>Each virtual directory can also have HTTP maps defined for it.  This 
  allow you to set logical paths on an HTTP directory to point to specific 
  directories available to Virtuoso through the file system or DAV.</para>
  <para>You can also publish stored procedures to a SOAP defined directory 
  during the virtual directory definition.</para>
    
      <figure float="1"><title>Virtual Directories</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir001.png"/></figure>

  <para>Click on the <emphasis>Add New Site</emphasis> button to start adding 
  a new Virtual Web Site and its directories.</para>

      <figure float="1"><title>Virtual Directories: Site Details</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir002.png"/></figure>

  <para>When adding or editing a web site you must supply a host.domain name, 
  which will be used to match again incoming requests to produce the correct 
  response, the IP address of the network interface, to set-up the listener on, 
  and the TCP port number that will be used to listen for incoming requests.  
  Although Virtuoso will be listening on the specified interface you can 
  set up multiple sites on this interface.  The site required by client web 
  browsers will be determined by the host name specified in the request.  
  This provides the virtual site.</para>

  <para>Click on "New Directory" to continue.</para>

      <figure float="1"><title>Virtual Directories Mappings</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir003.png"/></figure>

  <para>Before the directory settings are configured you can select from a 
  few types to help configure the details to follow quicker and easier.
  For SOAP virtual directories this step is particular useful.</para>

  <para>Select "Type" and then click "Next" to continue.</para>

      <figure float="1"><title>Virtual Directories</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir004.png"/></figure>

  <para>The "Virtual Directory Information" tab lets you configure most aspects of the virtual directory.</para>

  <para>The default directory checkbox can be checked if you want the site being 
  defined to act as the default site for the interface.  This means that if a 
  request is made to the interface that does not match a hostname defined for 
  the interface, the default will be returned.</para>

  <para>Logical Path will be the path that Virtuoso will respond to for this 
  virtual directory mapping.  This is what will be placed on the URL.
  Physical Path or URL is what Virtuoso will actually supply the content 
  from.  In either case you can use the Browse buttons to traverse the file systems 
  graphically.  Use the WebDAV Source Checkbox to instruct Virtuoso to use the 
  WebDAV store for the physical location.  "Default Page" will be returned if 
  no page is specified in the incoming URL.  </para>

  <note><title>Note:</title>
  <para>Virtual directories for SOAP must always use a physical path of /SOAP/.</para>
  <para>The physical path of /SOAP/ does not need to exist in the filesystem 
  under the VSP-root directory for normal SOAP operation.  If it does existing it 
  can be used to answer non-SOAP requests.  Thus, configuring the 
  virtual directory for SOAP with a "Default Page" can be used to 
  avoid SOAP clients receiving HTTP 404 errors when testing the SOAP endpoint 
  using standard HTTP only.  Some SOAP applications assume the SOAP endpoint 
  is down if they received HTTP 404 without checking the SOAP endpoint itself.</para></note>

  <para>The permissions panel lets you choose whether to enable various 
  abilities in the directory.</para>

  <para>In the SOAP Options section you can publish or unpublish procedures 
  and/or templates, both native and remote to the virtual directory using 
  the Publish/Unpublish buttons respectively. The SOAP Options text-area allows
  you to specify other SOAP options such as DIME encapsulations and WS-security 
  settings.  These options are supplied as name=value pairs terminated with a semi-colon and 
  a carriage-return.  Here is an example of the options used for the 
  default Interop test based demo virtual directory:</para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
Namespace=http://soapinterop.org/;
MethodInSoapAction=no;
ServiceName=InteropTests;
HeaderNS=http://soapinterop.org/echoheader/;
CR-escape=yes;
]]></programlisting>

  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para>For a list of available SOAP Options review the end section of the SOAP 
  chapter: <link linkend="soapoptions">Optional Parameters to the SOAP Endpoint</link>.</para></tip>

  <para>The Authentication Options panel lets you define the authentication 
  rules for the Virtual Directory.</para>

  <para>Once the form details have been completed press on the Add button to 
  save the them and proceed to configure mappings for the directory.</para>

      <figure float="1"><title>Virtual Directories Mappings</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir006.png"/></figure>

  <para>This screen lists mappings that have been defined for the virtual site.  
  If you have just created a fresh site then only one line will be displayed.  
  The "Add Virtual Directory" button will let you define more.  Back 
  returns you to the start page, Edit and Delete allow you to edit or remove 
  existing mappings as their link suggests.</para>

  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para><link linkend="virtdir">Virtual Directories</link></para></tip>

  <para>For example, here are the basic steps to be performed, in order to mount FS folder to DAV:</para>
  <orderedlist>
  <listitem>Suppose there is a folder with name "test" in your FS and it is under the root of the 
  	ServerRoot defined in your virtuoso ini file.</listitem>
  <listitem>Also suppose in the folder "test" there is a file index.html with simple content:
  <programlisting><![CDATA[
<!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//IETF//DTD HTML//EN">
<html>
  <head>
    <title>OpenLink Virtuoso Conductor Simple Test</title>
  </head>
  <body>
    <table cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" border="1" width="50%">
      <tr>
       <td><b>Name</b></td><td></b>State</b></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Simple test for mounting FS to DAV</td><td>Successful.</td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </body>
</html>
  ]]></programlisting>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>Install the Conductor package</listitem>
  <listitem>Go to http://host:port/conductor and login as dba user.</listitem>
  <listitem>Go to Web Application Server -> Virtual Domains &amp; Directories.
  <figure float="1"><title>Mount FS to DAV</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir011.png"/></figure>
  </listitem>    
  <listitem>For your {Default Web Site} click the link "New Directory".</listitem>
  <listitem>Check the check-box "Type" and select from the drop-down list "Filesystem".
  <figure float="1"><title>Mount FS to DAV</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir012.png"/></figure>
  </listitem>    
  <listitem>Click "Next"</listitem>
  <listitem>In the shown form: Enter for the field "Path": mytest; Enter for the field "Physical path": /test;
Enter for the field "Default page": index.html; Check the check-box "Allow Directory Browsing"; Leave the rest of the fields with their default values.</listitem>
  <listitem>Click "Save Changes"
  <figure float="1"><title>Mount FS to DAV</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir013.png"/></figure>
  </listitem>    
  <listitem>From your browser access the url: http://host:port/mytest/</listitem>
  <listitem>As result the content of the index.html file will be shown:
  <figure float="1"><title>Mount FS to DAV</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir014.png"/></figure>
  </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</sect3>
</sect2>
