<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2018 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->

<sect2 id="adminui.blogging">
	<title>Weblog</title>

  <sect3 id="adminui.blogging.admin"><title>Weblog Administration</title>

  <para>The Blog system administration page can be found from the main menu 
  of the Visual Server Administration Interface by expanding through: 
  <computeroutput>Web Services >> Weblog</computeroutput>.</para>

		<figure float="1"><title>Weblog UI - Blog Administration</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/blog002.jpg" width="356px" depth="157px"/></figure>

  <para>This page lists all users that have a blog account enabled.  Blog users 
  are created using the WebDAV Users Administration page and a few more 
  options, as shown below.</para>

  <para>Community blogging can be activated using the 
  <emphasis>Generate WebSite Pages</emphasis> button.  This will generate a 
  DAV owned blog site that will host other blogs within a community.  It can be 
  configured to allow anyone to register and begin blogging and/or existing 
  blogs can be added to the community by making sure they are part of the 
  same domain (see User Settings below).</para>

		<figure float="1"><title>Weblog UI - Adding a WebDAV User with Weblog Support</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/blog001.jpg" width="451px" depth="375px"/></figure>

  <para>You create or edit WebDAV users in the usual way, but to enable blog 
  support you must supply the following:</para>

  <simplelist>
    <member><emphasis>Create home directory</emphasis> - check box must be enabled</member>
    <member><emphasis>Home Directory</emphasis> - must be supplied to a 
	location in DAV, preferably <computeroutput>/DAV/&lt;blog-username&gt;/</computeroutput>.</member>
    <member><emphasis>Create Weblog</emphasis> - must also be checked.</member>
  </simplelist>

  <para>Having met this criteria the interface will save the details and create 
  the default blog site within the home directory.  Once details have been set or
  confirmed you should return the Blog Administration page to review the 
  Blog User Settings, below:</para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="adminui.blogging.userset"><title>Weblog User Settings</title>

		<figure float="1"><title>Weblog UI - Blog User Settings</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/blog003.jpg" width="588px" depth="445px"/></figure>

  <para>The user settings here are the same as those presented for the 
  community blog (see later), only the layout is different.  These settings 
  configure your blog site.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Title</title>
	  <para>The front page title for the blog home page.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Description</title>
	  <para>The description that will be accompanied with meta-data about the site, such as contained within RSS feeds.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Author's e-mail</title>
	  <para>The email address of the blog author.  This can be used for receiving notifications.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Owner</title>
	  <para>The WebDAV owner for the site.  This is supplied as read-only for reference only.</para></formalpara>
  </listitem>
  
    <!--listitem><formalpara><title></title>
	  <para></para></formalpara>
  </listitem-->
  
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Home page URL</title>
      <para>If the blog user has another home page it can be supplied here for 
	  blog readers to visit.  A valid URL should be supplied.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Copyrights; Disclaimers</title>
      <para>Should the blog user wish to supply such details they can do so
	  here, in plain-text.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Keywords</title>
      <para>These are HTML META TAG keyword values 
	  for the Blog Home Page; these are typically used by search engines 
	  amongst other "web spiders" to determine page and keyword associations.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Upload Photo Image; Photo</title>
      <para>You can supply a photo that will provide your site with a graphical 
	  identity.  Use the browse button to select an image to upload.  Uploaded
	  images are placed in the blog subdirectory of the users home.  You may 
	  have more than one image in this directory so you must enter the filename 
	  of photo you want displayed in the "Photo" field, relative to the blog subdirectory.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>XSL-T filter for Posts</title>
      <para>The <computeroutput>*default*</computeroutput> option can be 
	  replaced should a custom stylesheet be supplied for handling post output.  
	  The filename and path relative to the &lt;home-dir&gt;/blog directory should 
	  be supplied.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Domains</title>
      <para>This selects the domains (on the left) that will provide access to 
	  the blog site.  This option can be used to enable access to a single blog 
	  from a variety of personal, community, and corporate domains, which may be 
	  hosted on the same Virtuoso server instance using Virtuoso's Virtual 
	  Host/Domain functionality.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Weblog pings</title>
      <para>Enables automatic blog post notification to the central blog 
	  post server at <computeroutput>http://weblogs.com/</computeroutput>.  
	  This is one of the way of making the blogosphere aware of your blog posts.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Enable Contacts </title>
      <para>This is how you add records to the Virtuoso Weblog subsystem's 
	  FOAF (Friend of A Friend) database.  The FOAF database like other weblog 
	  gems is exposed to the web and blogosphere via a SQL-XML based RDF file. 
	  FOAF is an application of the XML based RDF vocabulary for persisting and 
	  sharing information about your contacts and associates.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>RSS file version</title>
      <para>To maximize compatibility with existing RSS aware technologies (e.g. 
	  RSS Headline Readers and RSS Content Aggregators) a choice of RSS 
	  formats provided for your blog posts (the system default is RSS 2.0).</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Enable Comments</title>
      <para>When enabled allows readers of your blog to provide comments on 
	  your site directly.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Enable Comment Post Notification via E-mail</title>
      <para>When checked you will receive an e-mail notification (using the 
	  blog e-mail account value provided above) every time a comment is posted 
	  to your blog.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Time-zone</title>
      <para>Allows you to set your time-zone.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Bridge Settings</title>
      <para>Allows you to define upstreaming destinations and rules.  
	  Upstreaming is how you enable Virtuoso to automatically route blog 
	  posts to other blogs that you may own, the only requirement is that 
	  these blog systems support any one of the following blog post APIs: 
	  Blogger, Meta-Weblog, or Moveable Type.  This also implies that you 
	  can use a single Blog Post Client (w.Bloggar, Newzcrawler, Zempt, 
	  and others) to post to several blogs.  See Community Blog Upstreaming 
	  below, the settings are identical.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Categories</title>
      <para>Provides a simple interface for creating blog post categories. 
	  It is important to note that the "enabled" and "disabled" attributes of 
	  these categories determines if they allow upstreaming of posts of not. 
	  Thus, when a category is set to "disabled" it means that any post that 
	  falls into this category will not be upstreamed to blogs outside the current 
	  server. When a category is set to "enabled" it means that although posts 
	  are not automatically restricted to the host server, they may still be 
	  excluded from upstreaming via an exception rule in an upstream 
	  routing table.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Channels</title>
      <para>Use this page to add RSS, OPML, OCS feeds to your blog home page. 
	  The OPML and OCS feeds contain collections of RSS feeds (these are Group 
	  Syndication Formats), and each RSS feed may or may not be a blog feed.  
	  In cases where the feed is deemed to be a blog (you indicate this by 
	  checking the "Is This a Blog" checkbox), it will be saved to Virtuoso's 
	  WebDAV repository and automatically added to the blog home's 
	  "Blogroll", otherwise they will be added to the "Channelroll" section of 
	  the blog home page - which enumerates a collection RSS based content 
	  sources.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Contacts</title>
      <para>Your electronic contact details are provided here.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="adminui.blogging.blogentry"><title>Weblog Posting</title>

		<figure float="1"><title>Weblog UI - Blog Entry Administration</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/blog004.jpg" width="527px" depth="460px"/></figure>

  <para>This interface allows you to post blog entries to selected categories 
  at a particular time.  You supply a title for the post and the main content 
  in the description field.  The preview option lets you see how it will look 
  without actually posting anything to the blog.</para>

		<figure float="1"><title>Weblog UI - Blog Home Page</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/blog005.jpg" width="567px" depth="391px"/></figure>

  <para>This is how the default generated blog home page will look.  This is 
  completely customizable via XSL's and VSPX code that is copied into your 
  blog directory in DAV without effecting other blogs.  You postings for the day 
  will be displayed in the centre column, you can select other days using the 
  calendar in the top right of the page.  Along the left column you have 
  syndication options to your site, a collection of XML based feeds, such as RSS 
  for other blog users to keep track of your blogging.</para>

  <para>As the blog site grows in complexity, your channels and RSS feeds will 
  be listed on the right-hand column of the page.</para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="adminui.blogging.comblog"><title>Community Blog Posting</title>

		<figure float="1"><title>Weblog UI - Community Blog Entry</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/blog006.jpg" width="674px" depth="469px"/></figure>

  <para>The community blog site providers a login section in the top-left of 
  the page.  Once a user is logged-in they can continue blogging as normal, but 
  using the same "skin" as the home page.  Hence, the Community Blog Entry 
  page that contains similar fields for authoring a blog post.</para>

  <note><title>Note:</title>
    <para>The left-hand column contains a configuration panel, used by bloggers 
	to maintain their part of the community.</para></note>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Channel Subscriptions</title>
      <para>For subscribing to news feeds and other RSS's.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Upstreaming</title>
      <para>So that your blogs on this community can be replicated to other blogs.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Categories</title>
      <para>For maintaining your blog categories.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Preferences</title>
      <para>For configuring you blog site details.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="adminui.blogging.comblogcats"><title>Community Blog - Categories</title>

		<figure float="1"><title>Weblog UI - Community Categories</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/blog011.jpg" width="521px" depth="259px"/></figure>

  <para>This page lets you define, remove and edit your blog categories.  You 
  provide a description and use the drop-down list to choose whether you want 
  the category to be included in any upstreaming configurations.  Click on the 
  save button to add the category. </para>

  <para>It is important to note that the "enabled" and "disabled" attributes of 
  these categories determines if they allow upstreaming of posts of not. 
  Thus, when a category is set to "disabled" it means that any post that 
  falls into this category will not be upstreamed to blogs outside the current 
  server. When a category is set to "enabled" it means that although posts 
  are not automatically restricted to the host server, they may still be 
  excluded from upstreaming via an exception rule in an upstream 
  routing table.</para>

  <para>Existing categories will be listed in a table on this page, the edit link
  lets you alter its details, whilst the delete link lets you drop a category.</para>

		<figure float="1"><title>Weblog UI - Community Category Posting</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/blog013.jpg" width="692px" depth="521px"/></figure>

  <para>You post to a category by selecting it from the list next to the 
  blog post description.</para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="adminui.blogging.commblogchnl"><title>Community Blog - Channel Subscription</title>

  <para>This page is used to add RSS, OPML, OCS feeds to your blog home page. 
	  The OPML and OCS feeds contain collections of RSS feeds (these are Group 
	  Syndication Formats), and each RSS feed may or may not be a blog feed.  
	  In cases where the feed is deemed to be a blog (you indicate this by 
	  checking the "Is This a Blog" checkbox), it will be saved to Virtuoso's 
	  WebDAV repository and automatically added to the blog home's 
	  "Blogroll", otherwise they will be added to the "Channelroll" section of 
	  the blog home page - which enumerates a collection RSS based content 
	  sources.</para>

		<figure float="1"><title>Weblog UI - Community Channel Subscription</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/blog007.jpg" width="546px" depth="231px"/></figure>

  <para>The channel subscription page lists in a table any RSS based feeds that 
  have been subscribed to, and lets you add entries to that list.</para>

		<figure float="1"><title>Weblog UI - Community Channel Subscription Settings</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/blog008.jpg" width="542px" depth="358px"/></figure>

  <para>To add a channel to the list simply supply the URL to the RSS feed 
  itself and click on retrieve.  After the RSS feed has been reviewed you will 
  be presented with its details to review and confirm using the Save button, 
  thus adding it to the list.</para>

		<figure float="1"><title>Weblog UI - Community Channel Subscription Confirmation</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/blog009.jpg" width="595px" depth="227px"/></figure>

<para>For each item in the list you can:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Edit</title>
      <para>Its details, such as its update interval.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Delete</title>
      <para>The entry altogether.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Fetch Posts</title>
      <para>To fetch the latest RSS version from the server on demand, now.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="adminui.blogging.commblogups"><title>Community Blog - Upstreaming</title>

		<figure float="1"><title>Weblog UI - Community Upstreaming</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/blog010.jpg" width="756px" depth="257px"/></figure>

  <para>Upstreaming keeps your blogs synchronized amongst your various blog 
  sites, should you have more than one.  This allows you to maintain all of your
  blogging centrally, and then upstream portions to appropriate servers 
  based on whether they are private, public or for your organization or of 
  various topics.</para>

  <para>Upstreaming is how you enable Virtuoso to automatically route blog 
	  posts to other blogs that you may own, the only requirement is that 
	  these blog systems support any one of the following blog post APIs: 
	  Blogger, Meta-Weblog, or Moveable Type.  This also implies that you 
	  can use a single Blog Post Client (w.Bloggar, Newzcrawler, Zempt, 
	  and others) to post to several blogs.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Endpoint</title>
      <para>Is the XML-RPC/SOAP endpoint that support SOAP based blogger API 
	  for your blog site.  For Virtuoso servers the endpoint typically ends with 
	  <computeroutput>/RPC2</computeroutput>, but this is configurable.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>User/Password</title>
      <para>The credentials required for accessing your blog site.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Type</title>
      <para>The Blog API system type.  One of: Blogger, MetaWebLog or 
	  Moveable Type</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>BlogID</title>
      <para>The system ID for your blog account on the server.  This is rarely 
	  known so the Fetch button can be used to obtain it once the above 
	  information has been provided.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Frequency</title>
      <para>The interval in minutes that Virtuoso will re-sync your blog with 
	  other sites.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Except</title>
      <para>Is an exception list to remove categories from this upstream entry.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Action</title>
      <para>The final step for adding your upstreaming entry is the Add 
	  button.  The checkbox next to it can be toggled to activate or de-activate 
	  an upstream entry as required.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="adminui.blogging.commblogusrprfs"><title>Community Blog - User Preferences</title>

		<figure float="1"><title>Weblog UI - Community User Preferences</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/blog012.jpg" width="637px" depth="499px"/></figure>

  <para>The user settings here are similar to those presented for the 
  single-user blog (see above), only the layout is different.  These settings 
  configure your part of blog community.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Title</title>
	  <para>The front page title for the blog home page.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Description</title>
	  <para>The description that will be accompanied with meta-data about the site, such as contained within RSS feeds.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Author's e-mail</title>
	  <para>The email address of the blog author.  This can be used for receiving notifications.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Home page URL</title>
      <para>If the blog user has another home page it can be supplied here for blog readers to visit.  A valid URL should be supplied.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Copyrights; Disclaimers</title>
      <para>Should the blog user wish to supply such details they can do so here, in plain-text.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Keywords</title>
      <para>These are HTML META TAG keyword values 
	  for the Blog Home Page; these are typically used by search engines 
	  amongst other "web spiders" to determine page and keyword associations.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Upload Photo Image; Photo</title>
      <para>You can supply a photo that will provide your site with a graphical 
	  identity.  Use the browse button to select an image to upload.  Uploaded
	  images are placed in the blog subdirectory of the users home.  You may 
	  have more than one image in this directory so you must enter the filename 
	  of photo you want displayed in the "Photo" field, relative to the blog subdirectory.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Ping Weblog.com using</title>
      <para>Enables automatic blog post notification to the central blog 
	  post server at <computeroutput>http://weblogs.com/</computeroutput>.  
	  This is one of the way of making the blogosphere aware of your blog posts.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Enable Contacts </title>
      <para>This is how you add records to the Virtuoso Weblog subsystem's 
	  FOAF (Friend of A Friend) database.  The FOAF database like other weblog 
	  gems is exposed to the web and blogosphere via a SQL-XML based RDF file. 
	  FOAF is an application of the XML based RDF vocabulary for persisting and 
	  sharing information about your contacts and associates.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>RSS file version</title>
      <para>To maximize compatibility with existing RSS aware technologies (e.g. 
	  RSS Headline Readers and RSS Content Aggregators) a choice of RSS 
	  formats provided for your blog posts (the system default is RSS 2.0).</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Enable Comments</title>
      <para>When enabled allows readers of your blog to provide comments on your site directly.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Enable Comment Post Notification via E-mail</title>
      <para>When checked you will receive an e-mail notification (using the 
	  blog e-mail account value provided above) every time a comment is posted 
	  to your blog.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Time-zone</title>
      <para>Allows you to set your time-zone.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Enable Trackback/Pingback</title>
      <para>TrackBack provides a method of notification between blog sites.  
	  it is a method of blog A saying to blog B, "This is something you may be interested in." - 
	  so that referrals and comments let the blog user know another blogger 
	  has used their blog.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Enable Referrals</title>
      <para>Toggle to specify whether you want to display referral URL's on your blog page.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Change password</title>
      <para>Lets you change your password.  You have your old password in order to do this for security purposes.</para></formalpara>
	  </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</sect3>
</sect2>
