<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2015 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->

	<sect2 id="dbadmin">
		<title>Database Administration</title>
      	<sect3 id="dbusersandgroups">
      		<title>Users &amp; Group Accounts</title>
		<para>
From System Admin / user Accounts you can alter the users that can access the Virtuoso database. You may
add a new user by clicking the "Create New Account" link, edit an existing user, or delete users.
You can associate users with groups or make new groups.
</para>
		<para>
Groups are created and function like normal user accounts.  To define a group you simply create a new user, and then to make
use of the group you assign users to that group from the drop down which will contain available groups.
</para>
		<para>
To create a new user or group you must enter a username, password and confirm the password by retyping it in the
fields provided.  You may optionally specify a group and default qualifier.  You can use groups to control access to a set of users
by maintaining the permissions granted to the group for which they are members.  Specifying a default qualifier
allows you to specify the catalog or database for which queries will be run against that do not explicitly
refer to a particular catalog or database.
</para>
		<para>
You can import users by adding LDAP Servers(s) from the "LDAP Servers" tab, and then from the "LDAP Import" to specify from
which LDAP server the import should be done:</para>

    <figure float="1"><title>Users Accounts</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admtables_01a.png"/></figure>

        <sect4 id="dbusersandgroupsldap"><title>Configuring and import from LDAP server</title>
<para>The following steps describe how to configure LDAP server and then import user(s) using the Conducor UI:</para>        
<orderedlist>
	 <listitem>Go to http://cname:port/conductor</listitem>
	 <listitem>Enter user dba credentials</listitem>
	 <listitem>Go to System Admin -&gt; User Accounts -&gt; LDAP Servers
     <figure id="ldap1" float="1">
       <title>LDAP Servers Configure and Import</title>
       <graphic fileref="ui/ldap1.png"/>
     </figure>
	 </listitem>
	 <listitem>Enter in the LDAP servers form respectively:
     <orderedlist>
     	 <listitem>Host Name: for ex.: ldap.example.com
         <para>Note: you can also use ldap:// or ldaps:// in front of Host name</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>Base: for ex.: o=MyCompany,c=DE</listitem>
       <listitem>Base DN: for ex: ou=Accounts,o=MyCompany,c=DE</listitem>
       <listitem>UID field: uid</listitem>
       <listitem>Account: for ex: joe</listitem>
       <listitem>Password: *******</listitem>
       <listitem>LDAP version: choose for ex. 3</listitem>
     </orderedlist>
	 </listitem>
	 <listitem>Check the connection by pressing "Test":
	   <figure id="ldap2" float="1">
       <title>LDAP Servers Configure and Import</title>
       <graphic fileref="ui/ldap2.png"/>
     </figure>	
	 </listitem>
   <listitem>If the test connection is successful, click "Add".
	   <figure id="ldap3" float="1">
       <title>LDAP Servers Configure and Import</title>
       <graphic fileref="ui/ldap3.png"/>
     </figure>	   	
   </listitem>
   <listitem>Next you can import various data from your LDAP server.</listitem>
   <listitem>Go to System Admin -&gt; User Accounts -&gt; LDAP Import
   	<figure id="ldap3a" float="1">
       <title>LDAP Servers Configure and Import</title>
       <graphic fileref="ui/ldap3a.png"/>
     </figure>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>Select the LDAP server added from above:  
   	 <figure id="ldap4" float="1">
       <title>LDAP Servers Configure and Import</title>
       <graphic fileref="ui/ldap4.png"/>
     </figure>   	
   </listitem> 
   <listitem>Click "Search".
   	 <figure id="ldap5" float="1">
       <title>LDAP Servers Configure and Import</title>
       <graphic fileref="ui/ldap5.png"/>
     </figure>   	
   </listitem>	  	
   <listitem>Click "Next".
   	 <figure id="ldap6" float="1">
       <title>LDAP Servers Configure and Import</title>
       <graphic fileref="ui/ldap6.png"/>
     </figure>   	
   </listitem>	  	
   <listitem>Select the desired profiles to be imported and set prefered "LDAP Authentication" for selected user:
     <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
       <listitem>If set to "enabled", then on an attempt to log in into Virtuoso, the system tries to 
       log in into the LDAP server with the given username and password. If this succeeds, then the user logs 
       in successfully in Virtuoso. </listitem>
       <listitem>If set to "account check",  then on an attempt to log in into Virtuoso, the system performs a 
       check if there is such an user on the LDAP server. If yes, then the user logs in successfully in 
       Virtuoso.</listitem>
     </itemizedlist>     
   	 <figure id="ldap7" float="1">
       <title>LDAP Servers Configure and Import</title>
       <graphic fileref="ui/ldap7.png"/>
     </figure>   	
   </listitem>	  	
     <listitem>Click "Import".
<para>Note: By default an importing LDAP user has "User type" set to "WebDAV". To log in into iSQL with 
     an imported LDAP user credentials you should:</para>
     <orderedlist>
       <listitem>Make sure you have set in Virtuoso ini the SQL_ENCRYPTION_ON_PASSWORD parameter to 1 in the [Client] section, i.e.:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
;virtuoso.ini
....
[Client]
SQL_ENCRYPTION_ON_PASSWORD  = 1
...
]]></programlisting>       
       </listitem>
       <listitem>Set the "User type" of the imported LDAP user to be "SQL/ODBC" by going to Virtuoso Conductor -&gt; 
       System Admin -&gt; User Accounts -&gt; user -&gt; Edit -&gt; field "User type".</listitem>
       <listitem>Log in into iSQL:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
isql host:port ldap-user-name ldap-user-password 
]]></programlisting>       
       </listitem>
     </orderedlist>     
     </listitem>	  	
   <listitem>Click "Finish".</listitem>	  	
   <listitem>The imported profile(s) should be displayed in the Users tab:
   	 <figure id="ldap8" float="1">
       <title>LDAP Servers Configure and Import</title>
       <graphic fileref="ui/ldap8.png"/>
     </figure>   	
   </listitem>	  	
  </orderedlist>
        </sect4>
      	</sect3>

      	<sect3 id="databases">
      		<title>Databases</title>
    <para>
Each catalog (database) within Virtuoso will be listed under the Databases /Schema Objects. For each
catalog you will be able to view and in some cases edit details about the tables, views, triggers,
and store procedures stored within that catalog.</para>

    <figure float="1"><title>Viewing Tables details for the Demo catalogue in the Demo Database</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admtables_01.png"/></figure>

    <figure float="1"><title>Viewing Views details for the Demo catalogue in the Demo Database</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admviews_01.png"/></figure>
    	<sect4 id="demodbinstallsteps">
	  <title>Demo Database Installation</title>
          <para>The Virtuoso Demonstration database can be installed with the Conductor by navigating to
the "System Admin" -> "Packages" tab where a list of available Virtuoso applications are
displayed, one of which is for the "Demo" database package as shown below:
          </para>
          <figure float="1"><title>Install Demo db using Conductor UI: "System Admin" -> "Packages"</title>
            <graphic fileref="ui/demodbinstall_01.png"/></figure>
          <para>Select the "Demo" package and click on the "Install" button to commence the
installation process:
          </para>
          <figure float="1"><title>Install Demo db: confirmation</title>
            <graphic fileref="ui/demodbinstall_02.png"/></figure>
          <para>Click on the "proceed" button to install the indicated "Demo Database"
application package:
          </para>
          <figure float="1"><title>Install Demo db: proceed</title>
            <graphic fileref="ui/demodbinstall_03.png"/></figure>
          <para>Once installed the demo database schema can be viewed from the
"Database" -> "Schema Objects" tab of the Conductor:
          </para>
          <figure float="1"><title>Install Demo db: view schema objects</title>
            <graphic fileref="ui/demodbinstall_04.png"/></figure>
    	</sect4>
     	<sect4 id="triggers">
	      		<title>Editing Triggers</title>
	<para>
	For each table, Virtuoso gives you the ability to edit the
	triggers linked to that table, as well as adding new triggers.
	The link text "Triggers" is followed by a number in parentheses
	that tells you how many triggers exist associated with that
	table.  If no number is shown, there are no triggers.  Clicking on
	the text takes you to the trigger edit page.
	</para>
<!--
need a screenshot  here
-->
  <para>
  The triggers page shows you the name of each trigger, an excerpt
  from the text of the trigger, and permits you to edit or drop the
  triggers. In the last column of the shown form there is a "New Trigger" link for creation of a new trigger.
  </para>
 </sect4>

	<sect4 id="storedprocedures">
	<title>Editing Stored Procedures</title>
	<para>
	The stored procedures link shows a page of information about
	existing stored procedures for the database you are viewing.  If
	there are stored procedures, you can see their names and text
	excerpts, and you may edit or drop them.  Adding new stored
	procedures can be done via the ISQL command-line interface or from the "Create Procedure" link shown
        above the list of objects for the relevant database.
	</para>
    <figure float="1"><title>Viewing Stored Procedures details for the DB catalogue</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admprocedures_01.png"/></figure>
        <para>
	Stored procedures may also refer to modules that contain a group
	of related stored procedures.  These are created and edited as a
	group, rather than individually.  An example of this is the module
	DB.DBA.AmazonSearchService, which contains procedures such as
	KeywordSearchRequest() and BrowseNodeSearchRequest().</para>
<!--
need a screenshot here of Edit Procedure DB.DBA.AmazonSearchService
-->
			</sect4>
			</sect3>
      	<sect3 id="externaldatabases">
      		<title>External Data Sources</title>
		<para>
		From Database / External Data Sources you will be able to manage the Virtual Database
                feature of Virtuoso. You are able to administer ODBC Data Sources, how to link remote
                tables and view, and already linked remote connections.</para>

   	<sect4 id="connecteddsns">
	      		<title>Data Sources</title>
			<para>
			This tab shows you the available Data Sources. For these one, to which there is no
connection, will be shown the link"Connect". For the datasource for which there is already established
connection, will be shown the links "Link objects", "Change Credentials" and "Disconnect".</para>

        <figure float="1"><title>Remote Datasources connected to Virtuoso</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/rmtconnected_01.png"/></figure>
			<para>
			If you need to alter the authentication details of a particular Data
			Source then select the "Change Credentials" link. If you want to link new objects,
select the "Link objects" link.</para>
		</sect4>
   	<sect4 id="configureddsns"><title>Configure Data Sources</title>
			<para>
			This section will allow you to configure the data sources themselves on
			the remote machine.  The table that will be presented to you will
			contain both User and System data sources.  You will be able to edit
			and create either User or System data sources, however, Virtuoso will
			only be able to use the User data sources that belong to the user that
			started the Virtuoso Server.</para>

        <figure float="1"><title>Configuring ODBC Datasources</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/odbcadm_01.png"/></figure>

      <para>Follow the buttons on the screen as to how you want to manage a data
			source.  You can create new, edit or remove existing data sources.</para>

        <figure float="1"><title>Configuring A Virtuoso ODBC Datasources</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/virtdsn_01.png"/></figure>

      <para>The Virtuoso Server can make use of File Data Sources too.  This 
      provides the usual associated conveniences.  These enable you to migrate 
      a Virtuoso database to another machine hosting the same ODBC Driver, 
      Virtuoso then has enough information to connect using the installed 
      driver to a remote data source, the tables would not need to be 
      relinked.  File DSN's are read from server's root directory.  File DSN's can 
      only be read if this directory is contained in the Virtuoso INI file parameter 
      DirsAllows.</para>

      <note><title>Note:</title>
      <para>Windows NT or 2000 services by default start as the LocalSystem 
      special user account.  This account will not contain the same User DSNs 
      as your own user.  The Virtuoso service can be started with other users 
      but you must be aware of any possible system permission problems.  It is 
      recommended that Virtuoso make use of System or File DSNs wherever 
      possible.</para></note>


		</sect4>

   	<sect4 id="remotetables"><title>External Linked Objects</title>
			<para>
			This page will allow you to manage the remote objects that are linked
			into Virtuoso. You can unlink objects by selecting them and pressing the
			"Unlink selected" button. </para>
        <figure float="1"><title>Linking Tables from Remote Datasources</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/admrmttbls_01.png"/></figure>
			<para>
			To link new tables into Virtuoso select "Link objects" link or go to
                        the "Data Sources" tab.
			Click the "Connect" link for a data source. If this data source has been used
                        before then the existing authentication details will automatically be provided.
                        Otherwise you will have to provide these details in the username and password fields provided.
			When you are ready press the "Link objects" link.</para>
			<para>
			As results you should be presented with list of available
			remote tables and optionally views and procedures. If the connection fails then an
			error will be returned to the top of the page instead.  You should be
			able to link any of the listed tables or views into Virtuoso.  In order
			for Virtuoso to be able to correctly query the underlying table it needs
			to be able to uniquely identify each row (record) within the table or
			view.  Tables should always be created with a primary key, and details
			of which should be available from the data source.  With a primary key
			available Virtuoso will be able to link the table in to the server easily.
			In some cases and certainly in the case of views Virtuoso may not be
			able to determine a primary key or what constitutes uniqueness in the
			table.  On the right most column will be an action link to a page that
			allows you to alter the primary key information about the table or view
			that is to be linked.  Some primary key information is italized to indicate 
			the explicit definition of a primary key.</para>
			<para>
			You will be required to enter primary key information for views before
			they can be linked.</para>
			<para>Select the tables that you want to link into the Virtuoso Server
			by checking the check box on the left most column of the list for table
			or view in question. When you are ready press the <emphasis>Link ...
			</emphasis> button at the bottom of the page.</para>
			<para>
			As result the selected tables will be linked and
			listed in the first list as Currently Linked.</para>
		</sect4>

     	<sect4 id="remoteprocedures"><title>Remote Procedures</title>
			<para>
			In order to view the list of remote procedures, you should check the "Stored Procedures" check-box and click the button "Apply".
                        As result the procedures that are already connected to
			Virtuoso will be shown with checked check-box. You can unlink these by selecting them and pressing the
			<emphasis>Unlink</emphasis> button.</para>

      <para>To link new procedures into Virtuoso select the Data Source from
      the list of available n t ab "Data Sources". If this data source has been used before then the existing
      authentication details will automatically be provided.  Otherwise you 
      will have to provide these details in the username and password fields 
      provided. When you are ready press the <emphasis>Link Objects</emphasis> link.
      The page will next require you to select the catalog/owner combination 
      to refine the search list of procedures on the remote datasource. Check the
      check-box "Stored procedures" and click the "Apply" button to list the available stored procedures.</para>

        <figure float="1"><title>Linking Procedures from Remote Datasources</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/admrmtprocs002.png"/></figure>

      <para>When the page returns you will be presented with a list of 
      available remote procedures.  You should be able to link any of the listed 
      procedures into Virtuoso.</para>  

        <figure float="1"><title>Linking Procedures from Remote Datasources</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/admrmtprocs003.png"/></figure>

      <para>Select the procedures that you want to link into the Virtuoso Server
			by checking the check box on the left most column of the list for the 
			procedure in question. When you are ready press the <emphasis>Link ...
			</emphasis> button at the bottom of the page.</para>

      <para>You will be presented with a new page that lists the procedures chosen 
      and the data type information regarding them.  This gives you an opportunity  
      to alter the  data type mappings that Virtuoso will use both internally and 
      for any future interactions with the SOAP server.  If you do not want to
      specify any special type information the details can be left as default.</para>

        <figure float="1"><title>Linking Procedures from Remote Datasources</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/admrmtprocs004.png"/></figure>

      <para>For each remote procedure you have the option to change how they 
      will be referenced within Virtuoso by making changes to the fields for 
      <emphasis>Local Name</emphasis>, <emphasis>Database</emphasis>, and 
      <emphasis>Schema</emphasis>.  These fields define how you will find the 
      linked procedure locally to Virtuoso only and do not affect the remote 
      data source.</para>
      
      <para>For each procedure there are radio buttons for selecting the 
      <emphasis>PL Wrapper Requirements</emphasis>.  This option is of particular 
      importance for remote procedures capable of returning a resultset.  Remote 
      procedures can be linked using a Virtuoso PL wrapper meaning that Virtuoso 
      procedure language code provides a mechanism for negotiating the result set.  
      The available options are:</para>
      <simplelist>
        <member><emphasis>Soap Execution</emphasis> - Generates a PL wrapper 
          that can be published to Web Services.</member>
        <member><emphasis>SQL Execution</emphasis> - Generates a PL Wrapper 
          that is more suitable for general SQL use.</member>
        <member><emphasis>None</emphasis> - Does not generate and PL Wrapper 
          code and simply links the procedure by reference.</member>
      </simplelist>

      <para>There is a description input box for you to write a description or 
      comment for the linked procedure.  This comment will only be applicable to 
      procedures that are linked using a PL Wrapper, and is only directly 
      applicable for PL Wrappers for SOAP execution.</para>

		</sect4>
</sect3>

 	<sect3 id="eventscheduler"><title>Event Scheduler</title>
		<para>
		The System Admin / Scheduler tab allows you to view, edit and remove events that
		can be scheduled to run from a particular time at a defined interval.</para>
    <figure float="1"><title>Event Scheduler</title>
       <graphic fileref="ui/admevt_01.png"/></figure>
		<para>
		To add a new scheduled event click the "Create New Event" link in tha last column of the shown form.
		The Event Name is a unique name required to uniquely identify each event. Start
		Time is when the event will be run for the first time and takes the form
		of a normal SQL timestamp value. Interval(minutes) is the length of time in minutes
		to wait to run the event again.  SQL is a valid piece of SQL that you want
		to schedule to run. You can also check for "Enable Error Notification" and enter E-Mail for
                error notification.</para>
    <figure float="1"><title>Event Scheduler</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admevt_01a.png"/></figure>
		<para>
		Events write possible error messages into the Virtuoso log file.</para>
  </sect3>

<!-- ################## dbpump ################ -->

  <!-- sect2 id="dbpump"><title>DB Pump</title>
    <sect3 id="dbpumpintro"><title>Introduction</title>
    <para>DBPUMP is a reincarnation of the existing DBDUMP utility.  DBDUMP was
		a RDBMS-independent application for managing data and schema within the
		database for backup and restore purposes in particular.  Its successor now
		incorporates a web based interface to make the
		application more appealing to the end user.  Due to Virtuoso's extended support
		DBPump has been updated to include the more uncommon data types and schema
		features Virtuoso has to offer as well as all plain RDBMS features.  DBPUMP
		has three parts:
		</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
		    <listitem>Single command-line program with ability to be run via CGI</listitem>
			<listitem>A set of VSP-pages to provide user interface for the mentioned program</listitem>
			<listitem>A set of PL-SQL procedures in 'PUMP' qualifier to support interaction as above</listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
	</sect3>
    <sect3 id="dbpumppages"><title>VSP - Pages</title>
    <para>Currently there are nine basic pages:</para>
    <sect4 id="dbpumpdumppg"><title>Dump Page</title>
      <para>enables you to make a dump of selected tables.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Available Tables</emphasis> listbox provided a list of tables
      which satisfy the filter conditions specified below</para>
      <para><emphasis>Select All</emphasis> lets you select all available tables automatically</para>
      <para><emphasis>Deselect All</emphasis> automatically releases all selected tables</para>
      <para><emphasis>Filter</emphasis> lets you choose the type of filter you
      require.  It has the following options:</para>

      <simplelist>
        <member><emphasis>none</emphasis> (default) all existing non-system tables will be available</member>
        <member><emphasis>advanced</emphasis> advanced options will be used</member>
        <member>all existing sub-schemas also will be represented</member>
      </simplelist>

      <para>The <emphasis>Advanced Filter</emphasis> button will direct you to the
      Advanced Filter page.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Dump Type</emphasis> allows you to define what should be
      included in dump from the following options:</para>

      <simplelist>
        <member><emphasis>everything</emphasis> (default) all possible data will be saved</member>
        <member><emphasis>schema-only</emphasis> will only dump the schema and ignore the data residing</member>
        <member><emphasis>data-only</emphasis> only table data will be processed</member>
        <member><emphasis>custom</emphasis> specifies that your settings from Dump Options will be used</member>
      </simplelist>

      <para><emphasis>More Options</emphasis> is where you can define which objects
      should be processed during the dump.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Sql-Binary</emphasis> lets you choose the type of dump required.
      Sql type means plain sql text.  In some cases this can be inconvenient e.g.
      when the table contains blobs which in any case will be dumped separately
      with absolute path.  The binary type corresponds to dbpump's default binary format.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Dump Directory</emphasis> dump location specified as a relative
      path from the server's root directory to the root directory of dump.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Browse</emphasis> lets you browse to the desired location</para>
      <para><emphasis>Dump Name</emphasis> is the name of the dump file name, hence
      'dump_1' will be converted to 'dump_1.dbk' and will reside in the specified directory</para>
      <para><emphasis>Dump</emphasis> performs dump with current options.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Restore Defaults</emphasis> restores default values of the page.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="dbpumpfilteropt"><title>Filter Options</title>
      <para>This page lets you set the filtering options such as:</para>
      <para><emphasis>Match Qualifier</emphasis> (default &apos;%&apos;)lets
      you define filter for qualifier as it would be used in SQL like operator.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Match User</emphasis> filter based on table owner.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Match Table</emphasis> filter based table name.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Restore Defaults</emphasis> restores defaults.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Apply</emphasis> saves above values.  If any of these values
      is not equal to '%', this will change the value of parent's filter-type listbox
      to 'Advanced'.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Cancel</emphasis> discards changes.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="dbpumpbrowsepg"><title>Browse</title>
      <para>The Browse page allows you to select the path for objects to dump</para>
      <para><emphasis>Directory Listing</emphasis> provides a tree-like list of
      existing directory on the server root.</para>
      <para>The root directory for dbpump's backup tree is the <emphasis>backup</emphasis>
      directory found the server's root directory.  Directories with dbpump's
      special extension '.dbk' are not taken into account.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Dir Content</emphasis> shows the current dumps stored in the
      current directory.  The dump itself is a subtree, of which the root directory
      has the extension .dbk.  The list shows the dump name and its creation
      date and time.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Current Directory</emphasis> displays the current dump
      directory</para>
      <para><emphasis>Change Directory</emphasis> will refresh the content of
      selected directory.  To change your current directory select it in
      <emphasis>Directory Listing</emphasis> and press this <emphasis>Change
      Directory</emphasis> button.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Directory Listing</emphasis> lets you choose what to view
      in the Dir Content listbox.  Possible values are:</para>

      <simplelist>
        <member><emphasis>Schema</emphasis> lists schema dumps only</member>
        <member><emphasis>Data</emphasis> displays table data dumps only</member>
        <member><emphasis>Both</emphasis> (default) will display both types.</member>
      </simplelist>

      <para><emphasis>Show Manifest</emphasis> will open a new window of the
      Dump's Manifest.  The Manifest is an xml file placed in dump's root directory
      containing information about its content with name of creator and creation date/time.
      The Manifest window will display an appropriate transformation rather than raw XML.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Select</emphasis> saves the actual value of Current Dir and passes
      it to Dump Page</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="dbpumpadvdmpopt"><title>Advanced Dump Options</title>
      <para>The Advanced Dump Options page allows you to select objects to dump</para>
      <para><emphasis>Dump Type</emphasis> displays the dump type as in the prior page.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Table Definitions</emphasis> checkbox instructs DBPUMP to
      output table definitions.  This only applies to plain SQL dumps.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Triggers</emphasis> checkbox indicates whether to include trigger
      bodies in the dump.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Stored Procedures</emphasis> checkbox for including stored procedures
      in the dump.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Constraints</emphasis> checkbox for including constraints such as
      indices, procedures ... in the dump.</para>
      <para><emphasis>FK Constraints</emphasis> includes foreign key constraint
      information in dump.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Views</emphasis> includes view declarations.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Users</emphasis> includes users.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Grants</emphasis> includes grants.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Table Data</emphasis> includes the data within the tables selected.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Insert Mode</emphasis> defines the method for returning
      the data to the database during a restore.  Possible options are:</para>

      <simplelist>
        <member><emphasis>Regular</emphasis> corresponds to &apos;insert into ...&apos;</member>
        <member><emphasis>Soft</emphasis> corresponds to &apos;insert soft into ...&apos;</member>
        <member><emphasis>Replacing</emphasis> corresponds to &apos;insert replacing ...&apos;</member>
      </simplelist>

      <para><emphasis>Change Qualifier</emphasis> when checked all qualifiers in saved
      data will be changed to pointed.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Change User</emphasis> when checked all owners in saved data
      will be changed to pointed. </para>
      <para><emphasis>Restore</emphasis> restores the default values of the page.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Apply</emphasis> saves page values.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Cancel</emphasis> discards changes to the page.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="dbpumprestore"><title>Restore</title>
      <para>The Restore page lets you restore previously dumped data</para>

      <para><emphasis>Directory Listing</emphasis>this is the same as in 'Browse' page tree-like list of existing folders on server root.
The root folder for dbpump's backup tree is also 'backup'.
Folders with dbpump's special extension '.dbk' are not been taken into account.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Dir Content</emphasis>here you can see a list of dumps placed in current folder.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Current Directory</emphasis>this is the same as 'Dump Directory' in 'Dump Page'.
The value of this field will be changed with every click in 'Directory Listing'</para>
      <para><emphasis>Change Directory</emphasis> will refresh the content of
      selected directory.  To change your current directory select it in
      <emphasis>Directory Listing</emphasis> and press this <emphasis>Change
      Directory</emphasis> button.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Directory Listing</emphasis> lets you choose what to view
      in the Dir Content listbox.  Possible values are:</para>

      <simplelist>
        <member><emphasis>Schema</emphasis> lists schema dumps only</member>
        <member><emphasis>Data</emphasis> displays table data dumps only</member>
        <member><emphasis>Both</emphasis> (default) will display both types.</member>
      </simplelist>

      <para><emphasis>Show Manifest</emphasis> will open a new window of the
      Dump's Manifest.  The Manifest is an XML file placed in dump's root directory
      containing information about its content with name of creator and creation date/time.
      The Manifest window will display an appropriate transformation rather than raw XML.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Select</emphasis> saves the actual value of Current Dir and passes
      it to Dump Page</para>
      <para><emphasis>More Options</emphasis> goes to the Advanced Restore Options page.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Restore</emphasis> starts the restoration.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="dbpumpadvrestoreopt"><title>Advanced Restore Options</title>
      <para>The Advanced Restore Options page lets you change some aspects of
      the restoration process.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Restore Users</emphasis> includes users.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Grants</emphasis> includes grants.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Table Data</emphasis> includes the data within the tables selected.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Insert Mode</emphasis> defines the method for returning
      the data to the database during a restore.  Possible options are:</para>

      <simplelist>
        <member><emphasis>Regular</emphasis> (default) corresponds to &apos;insert into ...&apos;</member>
        <member><emphasis>Soft</emphasis> corresponds to &apos;insert soft into ...&apos;</member>
        <member><emphasis>Replacing</emphasis> corresponds to &apos;insert replacing ...&apos;</member>
      </simplelist>

      <para><emphasis></emphasis></para>

      <para><emphasis>Change Qualifier</emphasis> when checked all qualifiers in saved
      data will be changed to pointed.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Change User</emphasis> when checked all owners in saved data
      will be changed to pointed. </para>
      <para><emphasis>Apply</emphasis> saves page values.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Cancel</emphasis> discards changes to the page.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="dbpumppasswdpg"><title>Password Page</title>
      <para>You will arrive at this page from the Dump and Restore pages when you
      try to dump or restore respectively.</para>
      <para><emphasis>User</emphasis> the user name.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Password</emphasis> the password from that user.</para>
      <para><emphasis>Start</emphasis> to begin the operation.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="dbpumpdumpres"><title>Tables Dump Results</title>
      <para>The Tables Dump Results page displays the results of the last
      dump.  The <emphasis>OK</emphasis> button returns you back to the Dump
      page.</para>
    </sect4>

    <sect4 id="dbpumptabrestres"><title>Tables Restore Results</title>
      <para>The Tables Restore Results page displays the results of the last restore
      including the output from the stderr of isql.  The <emphasis>OK</emphasis>
      button will return you to the restore page.</para>
    </sect4>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="activities"><title>Example scenarios.</title>
    <sect4 id="savingschema"><title>Saving Schema</title>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>Go to 'Dump' page</listitem>
        <listitem>Press 'More Options</listitem>
        <listitem>Select 'Dump Type' = 'Schema only'</listitem>
        <listitem>Press 'Apply'</listitem>
        <listitem>Press 'Dump' button and confirm your action</listitem>
        <listitem>Enter password and press 'Start'</listitem>
        <listitem>Press 'OK' button after getting results</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect4>
    <sect4 id="dumpingtables"><title>Dumping Tables</title>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>Go to 'Dump' page</listitem>
        <listitem>Press 'More Options'</listitem>
        <listitem>Select 'Dump Type' = 'Data only'</listitem>
        <listitem>Press 'Apply'</listitem>
        <listitem>Select 'UDDI' in 'Filter' listbox</listitem>
        <listitem>Press 'Dump' button and confirm your action</listitem>
        <listitem>Enter password and press 'Start'</listitem>
        <listitem>Press 'OK' button after getting results</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect4>
    <sect4 id="restoreschemadata"><title>Restoring Schema and Data</title>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>Go to 'Restore' page</listitem>
        <listitem>Define restore directory where you have stored schema (tables),
        you can ensure that by selecting interesting dump in listbox and
        pressing 'Show manifest'.</listitem>
        <listitem>Press 'Restore' button</listitem>
        <listitem>Enter password and press 'Start'</listitem>
        <listitem>Press 'OK' button after getting results</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect4>
  </sect3>
</sect2 -->

    <sect3 id="virtiniadm"><title>Virtuoso Configuration Editor</title>
     <para>From System Admin/Parameters you can change the Virtuoso Configuration settings:
     </para>
        <figure float="1"><title>Virtuoso (virtuoso.ini) Configuration File Editor</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/db_strtp_01.png"/></figure>

         <figure float="1"><title>Virtuoso (virtuoso.ini) Configuration File Editor</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/db_strtp_02.png"/></figure>

        <figure float="1"><title>Virtuoso (virtuoso.ini) Configuration File Editor</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/db_strtp_03.png"/></figure>

        <figure float="1"><title>Virtuoso (virtuoso.ini) Configuration File Editor</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/db_strtp_04.png"/></figure>

        <figure float="1"><title>Virtuoso (virtuoso.ini) Configuration File Editor</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/db_strtp_05.png"/></figure>

        <figure float="1"><title>Virtuoso (virtuoso.ini) Configuration File Editor</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/db_strtp_06.png"/></figure>

        <figure float="1"><title>Virtuoso (virtuoso.ini) Configuration File Editor</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/db_strtp_07.png"/></figure>

   </sect3>

      	<sect3 id="statistics"><title>Dashboard and Monitor</title>
<para>The System Admin/Dashboard consists of a collection of statistical information about
your Virtuoso server. This includes general licensing information, locking, webserver hits statistics and more.
     </para>
        <figure float="1"><title>Dashboard</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/sts_dsk_01.png"/></figure>
<para>The System Admin/Monitor shows in details statistical information about your server.
     </para>

        <figure float="1"><title>Monitor - General Information</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/sts_gen_01.png"/></figure>

        <figure float="1"><title>Monitor - HTTP Usage</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/sts_httpsvr_01.png"/></figure>

        <figure float="1"><title>Monitor - Index Usage</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/sts_idx_01.png"/></figure>

        <figure float="1"><title>Monitor - Profiling</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/sts_profile_01.png"/></figure>

		</sect3>

</sect2>
