<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2006 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->

<sect1 id="admui.webservices"><title>Web Services</title>

		<sect2 id="importtargets">
			<title>Import Targets</title>

    <para>Virtuoso can be set up to retrieve content from external web sites and
    host it in its own WebDAV repository via this page.</para>

        <figure float="1"><title>Web Robot - Target</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/dav_rbt_trgt_01.jpg" width="608px" depth="473px"/></figure>
		<para>
<emphasis>Target Description</emphasis> lets you provide a friendly description
for the target that you are defining.</para>
		<para>
<emphasis>Target Host Name</emphasis> is the hostname of the web site
that you are trying to retrieve content from.  Only the hostname should be
provided here, along with the protocol.  For example http://www.myhost.com.</para>
		<para>
<emphasis>Start Path in Target</emphasis> must contain the root page to begin
the web copy from.   If you wanted to copy the pages below
http://www.myhost.com/things/thispage.html then you would
place /things/thispage.html in this field.</para>
		<para>
<emphasis>Login name on target</emphasis> is the username for accessing
the remote server, if required.</para>
		<para>
<emphasis>Login password on target</emphasis> is the password for the login name above</para>
		<para>
<emphasis>Copy to Local DAV collection</emphasis> is the name of the collection
(folder) where retrieved content will be stored in Dav.</para>
		<para>
<emphasis>Single page download</emphasis> radio button specifies whether
Virtuoso will retrieved linked content also.</para>
		<para>
<emphasis>Local Resources Owner</emphasis> The DAV user that will be the owner
of the content that will copied to DAV.
</para>
		<para>
The <emphasis>Download only newer than</emphasis> field allows you to specify
a datetime value to prevent Virtuoso downloading files that are older than
that datetime.</para>
		<para>
Use the <emphasis>Follow Links Matching</emphasis> field to limit the content
that is downloaded by specify pattern matching criteria.</para>
		<para>
<emphasis>Do NOT follow links matching</emphasis> allows you limit content by
specifying what files not to download.</para>
		<para>
<emphasis>Download Images</emphasis> radio buttons to allow Virtuoso to pull
down image type also.  You may want to prevent this if you are more interested
in the textual content rather than bandwidth draining images.</para>
		<para>
<emphasis>Use WebDAV methods</emphasis> can be checked if the host is known to
support WebDAV methods.  This would enable better copying of sites that support DAV.</para>
		<para>
<emphasis>Delete if Remove on Remote is Detected</emphasis> can be switched on
so that when Virtuoso synchronizes its content with that on the remote host
it will check for files that have been removed on the remote and remove
them from the local copy also.</para>
		<para>
When all details have been completed press the <emphasis>Add</emphasis> (or
Update if updating) button to submit the web robot task to the queue.
</para>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="importqueues">
			<title>Import Queues</title>
		<para>
The queues page shows you a list of web copy targets that have been enlisted with the Virtuoso Server,
and a list of web robot update schedules.  Several options are available for each item listed: Start, Update,
Schedule, Reset, and Stop.  You can configure the scheduled update interval by pressing the Schedule
link and entering a value in minutes.  Once that is done you can start the schedule by pressing the Start
link.  You make a manual update of the content by pressing the Update link.  You can stop the scheduled
updates taking place by pressing the Stop link.  To reset the details of the web copy item press the Reset link.
</para>
        <figure float="1"><title>Web Robot - Queues</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/dav_rbt_que_01.jpg" width="635px" depth="243px"/></figure>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="retrievedsites">
			<title>Retrieved Sites</title>
		<para>
You can view a list of the links retrieved from the web copy from this page.  You are also able to remove
some of the content from this page by following the Edit link.
</para>
        <figure float="1"><title>Web Robot - Retrieved Links</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/dav_rbt_rtrd_01.jpg" width="582px" depth="136px"/></figure>
		</sect2>

    <sect2 id="exportlocalcontent">
			<title>Export</title>
		<para>
This page allows you to export content from the WebDAV repository. You can
only export content that has been retrieved using Virtuoso's Web Robot. This
page lists the targets that have been retrieved.
</para>
<para>Each item on the table has an <emphasis>Export</emphasis> link to be
clicked on to export that content.</para>

        <figure float="1"><title>Web Robot - Exporting Content</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/dav_rbt_expt_01.jpg" width="597px" depth="136px"/></figure>

<para>When you click an Export link you will be presented with a screen for
selecting the export target location.  Choose the export method: either File System
or DAV.  This lets you indicate to the remote target where to store the exported
content.  Then type the target URL to an existing location on the server.
Finally press the <emphasis>Export</emphasis> button to export.  A confirmation
will be supplied once the operation is complete.</para>

        <figure float="1" id="dav_rbt_expt_02"><title>Web Robot - Exporting Content</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/dav_rbt_expt_02.jpg" width="597px" depth="136px"/></figure>

<note><title>Note:</title><para>When selecting the filesystem method you are
restricted to Virtuoso targets, however WebDAV methods can be applied to any
WebDAV server.  WebDAV methods assume that the target is publically available for writing.</para></note>
	</sect2>

  <sect2 id="admiui.accesscontrol"><title>Access Control</title>



          <figure float="1" id="acl001"><title>Access Control Lists</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/acl001.jpg" width="317px" depth="146px"/></figure>

          <figure float="1" id="acl002"><title>Access Control Lists</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/acl002.jpg" width="403px" depth="191px"/></figure>

          <figure float="1" id="acl003"><title>Access Control Lists</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/acl003.jpg" width="340px" depth="232px"/></figure>

          <figure float="1" id="acl004"><title>Access Control Lists</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/acl004.jpg" width="405px" depth="210px"/></figure>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="admiui.wsdl"><title>Import WSDL</title>

  <para>This interface allows you to use the description of external web services
  to provide Virtuoso system usable procedures.  You provide a URL to a WSDL
  description, in return Virtuoso will automatically provide a wrapper for the services
  available, hence stored procedures and user-defined types that are callable
  within Virtuoso while the processing and mechanics of the services are actually
  handled at the source.  </para>

        <figure float="1" id="wsdlimp001"><title>WSDL Import</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/wsdlimp001.jpg" width="412px" depth="127px"/></figure>

  <para>After Virtuoso examines the supplied URL to a WSDL you are
  presented with the source code for the PL wrappers and Virtuoso user-defined
  types to be created.  You have the chance to edit the code for more specific
  needs and then you can either save this to a file for later work, or execute it
  in Virtuoso to create the procedures and types.</para>

          <figure float="1" id="wsdlimp002"><title>WSDL Import</title>
          <graphic fileref="ui/wsdlimp002.jpg" width="510px" depth="333px"/></figure>

   <para>Any errors in the code will be highlighted if you try and execute it.</para>

   <para>If you wish to save the file the appropriate file system ACLs must be in
   place for the destination.</para>

  </sect2>


</sect1>
