<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2015 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<sect2 id="backup"><title>Data Backup &amp; Recovery</title>

  <para>Administering a database involves taking backups and having a readiness
  to recover from backups and subsequent transaction logs.</para>

  <para>Backups can be taken in two principal ways:</para>
	<simplelist>
	  <member>Using the Virtuoso backup function/procedures.</member>
		<member>Copying the database files.</member>
  </simplelist>

  <para>The Virtuoso backup functions can be used from any client directly, such
  as ISQL.  It is possible, and perhaps preferable, to create stored procedures
  for performing the backup functions and scheduling these with the Virtuoso
  scheduler.</para>

  <para>The actual database file(s) can be copied while the database is running
  so long as no checkpoint is made during the copy process.  Checkpointing can
  be disabled for this, but make sure it is re-enabled after the backup has been
  made.</para>

  <para>Making a full backup of a large database can take several hours if not
  days just due to the speed of tapes or local area networks.  Full backups
  must in all cases be done without an intervening checkpoint.  This is why
  frequent full backups are not desirable.  To ensure the possibility of full
  recovery one must have the complete set of transaction logs (audit trail log)
  since the last  backup.</para>

  <para>Restarting the database after restoring backed up files will show the
  state in effect since the last checkpoint preceding the backup.  Any
  transaction log files made after the point of backup can be replayed to bring
  the state up to the last recorded transaction.</para>


  <!-- ======================================== -->
	<sect3 id="BACKUP_AUDIT">
		<title>Log Audit Trail</title>

    <para>Virtuoso can maintain a transaction audit trail.  This is enabled using
    the <link linkend="checkpointAuditTrail">CheckpointAuditTrail</link> setting
    in the virtuoso.ini file.  When this setting is non-zero, Virtuoso will
    begin a new transaction log after each checkpoint.  Thus one automatically gets
    a full, unbroken sequence of transaction logs for the entire age of the database.
    These logs are named as specified in virtuoso.ini and are suffixed with their creation
    time.</para>



    <para>Transaction logs older than the log that was current at the time of the
    last  backup are superfluous for recovery, since their transactions were
    checkpointed before the backup started.  Transactions of the log current at
    the time of the backup are NOT in the backed up state since they were not
    checkpointed, i.e. written into the read-only section of the database containing the data being backed up.</para>
    <para>We strongly advise having the CheckpointAuditTrail enabled in any
    production environment.</para>

		<para>It is good practice to have at least two generations of full backup,
    since the last backup may contain errors that were not known at the time of
    its making.  If such precaution is taken then only transactions logs older than
    the oldest backup  are safe to remove.  If we needed to recover from the oldest
    backup for any reason we would require all audit transaction logs created during
    and after that backup.</para>

    <para>A Virtuoso database can be restored from the last full backup and
    all Audit Trail transaction files created during and after the backup.  You
    would need to start the database as normal with the backup version of the
    database file.  Once the database has been started, connect using iSQL.
    You can then use the <link linkend="fn_replay">replay()</link> function to
    replay the transaction files up to the required point.  It is vital that
    these files are replayed in the correct order.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="onlinebackups"><title>On-Line Backups</title>

  <sect4 id="usingbackuponline"><title>Backup Using Backup_Online()</title>

  <para>Virtuoso is capable of performing online backups so that normal database
  operation does not have to be disrupted in order to take backups.
  The <link linkend="fn_backup_online"><function>backup_online()</function></link>
  can be used to backup the database in the state effective at the last checkpoint
  to a series of backup files.</para>

  <para>

The database storage is divided into a checkpoint space that is a read
only image from the time of the last checkpoint and thus can be safely
backed up anytime between checkpoints and the commit space where
updates subsequent to the last checkpoint data are stored.
Additionally, the database records what pages have changed since the
last checkpoint every time new checkpoint is made.  This change
tracking makes it possible to make incremental backups.  The first
time the backup_online function is called, it saves a compressed copy
of the then current checkpoint state into one or more files.  The next
time it is called, it will write the changes that have come into the
checkpoint space since the last time backup_online was called.  It is
possible to erase the change tracking data with the
backup_context_clear function.  The next call to backup_online will
then make a full backup.  Files generated by one or more calls to
backup_online without intervening backup_context_clear form a series
with distinct serial numbers and will be restored together.  In order
to restore such files, the administrator must delete the previous
database files and start the server with a special flag and indicate
the location of the backup files.  This will bring the database to the
state corresponding to the state as of the checkpoint immediately
preceding the last call to backup_online, i.e. the one that wrote the
newest of the backup files being restored.  To restore onwards from
this state, the administrator must replay transaction logs, starting
with the log that was current when the last call to backup_online was
made.  In order to preserve all such logs, one must run with the
CheckpointAuditTrail ini parameter set to 1.
</para>

  <para>A database checkpoint cannot be performed while an online backup
  is in progress.  </para>

  <example id="ex_anonlinebackup"><title>Performing an Online Backup</title>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[
SQL> backup_context_clear ();
SQL> checkpoint;
SQL> backup_online ('virt-inc_dump_#', 150);
]]></programlisting>
  </example>

  <para>The <function>backup_online()</function> procedure differs from the
  the CheckPointAuditTrail mainly because it can be started from any point
  in the database.  Unless CheckPointAuditTrail was enabled when the database
  was created, the database file at a particular state and all transaction logs
  created by the AuditTrail since that state would be required to restore
  the database.  Only the backup set files would be required to restore
  from <function>backup_online()</function>.  The <function>backup_online()</function>
  also makes a compressed backup, making it far more suitable for large
  databases.</para>

  <para>The last optional parameter allows to point the directory(ies) where the
  backup files must be stored. See <function>backup_online()</function> description
  for details. </para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4 id="rstrfrmbckuponline"><title>Restoring From an Online Backup Series</title>

  <para>To restore from a backup series the administrator must first shutdown
  the Virtuoso database server and move all database files (e.g. virtuoso.db
  and virtuoso.trx) out of the database directory.  It is recommended that copies
  by taken rather than deleting them entirely.  Then the command:</para>

<programlisting>
&lt;virtuoso exe&gt; +restore-backup &lt;FILE_PREFIX&gt;
</programlisting>


<programlisting><![CDATA[
-- for example:
virtuoso-iodbc-t +restore-backup dump-20011010_#
]]></programlisting>

  <para>must be issued in the directory where the "*.bp" were stored.  The
  database will then be restored.  The expression &lt;virtuoso exe&gt; above must
  be replaced with the path and filename to the Virtuoso server executable used
  on your system (e.g. ..\virtuoso-odbc-t.exe).</para>

  <para>Each file in the series has a header containing a unique identifier,
  for the backup set and the sequence number of the file in the backup set .  If
  an identifier in any file in the backup sequence differs from the identifier
  contained in the first file, the restoration process will stop and report an
  error, which is written to the Virtuoso log file.</para>

  <para>At times the backup or restoration commands may return errors.  Use the
  following list to help diagnose and resolve them:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><formalpara><title>Timestamp [%lx] is wrong in file %s</title>
    <para>The unique identifier in header of the file differs from the identifier
    of the first file.  It is possible that the file was renamed or corrupt or
    belongs to another backup set.</para>
    </formalpara></listitem>

    <listitem><formalpara><title>Number of file %s differs from internal number [%ld]</title>
    <para>The sequence number of the file does not correspond to the internal sequence number of file.
    This could be caused by the file being renamed or corrupt.</para>
    </formalpara></listitem>

    <listitem><formalpara><title>Prefix is wrong in file %s</title>
    <para>The prefix of the file does not correspond to internal information.
    Possible reason: file was renamed or corrupt or belongs to another backup set.</para>
    </formalpara></listitem>

    <listitem><formalpara><title>Could not begin online-backup</title>
    <para>Read error.  Possible reason: Virtuoso database file was corrupt.</para>
    </formalpara></listitem>

    <listitem><formalpara><title>Seek/Read failure on stripe %s/database</title>
    <para>Read error.  Possible reason: Virtuoso database file was truncated or hardware error.</para>
    </formalpara></listitem>

    <listitem><formalpara><title>Read of page %ld failed</title>
    <para>Read error.  Possible reason: Virtuoso database file was truncated or hardware error.</para>
    </formalpara></listitem>

    <listitem><formalpara><title>Backup file writing error</title>
    <para>Write error.  Possible reason: disk is malfunctioning  or  full.</para>
    </formalpara></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <example id="ex_anonlinebackuprestore"><title>Restoring an Online Backup</title>
  <para>Following the online backup example above:</para>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[
SQL> backup_context_clear ();
SQL> checkpoint;
SQL> backup_online ('virt-inc_dump_#', 150);
]]></programlisting>
  <para>The following command could be used to restore the database from the 
	backup files created:</para>
	  <programlisting><![CDATA[
		virtuoso-iodbc-t -c <db-ini-file> +restore-backup virt-inc_dump_#
	]]></programlisting>
  <para>or:</para>
	  <programlisting><![CDATA[
		virtuoso-odbc-t.exe -c <db-ini-file> +restore-backup virt-inc_dump_#
	]]></programlisting>
	
  </example>

  </sect4>
  </sect3>

    <sect3 id="otherbackupmethods"><title>Other Backup Methods</title>
			<para>
A possible  way of making a full backup of a large databases is first to
turn off any automatic checkpoints and make a compressed copy of the
files.  After the back up is complete, checkpointing should be re-enabled.  The
files should be compressed to make efficient use of space, and should be copied
to a disk separate from  the location of the database, and preferably to an external
backup medium such as tape.
</para>
<sect4 id="manualbackup"><title>Manual Backup</title>
			<para>
For a large database it is best to turn off any automatic checkpoints and copy the
database files to external storage.  Checkpoints should be turned off by
issuing the command:
</para>
			<programlisting>
checkpoint_interval (-1);
</programlisting>
			<para>
at the SQL prompt.  Checkpoints can be re-enabled in a post-backup
script by:
</para>
			<programlisting>
checkpoint_interval (&lt;n&gt;);
</programlisting>
			<para>
which sets the automatic checkpoint interval to &lt;n&gt; minutes.  The backup will
be unusable if there are checkpoints made while it is in progress.  Thus it is
important to guarantee that checkpoints do not occur.  The only safe way of
doing this is the above, since it is in principle possible to have a server crash during the
backup and a roll forward following restart, all while the backup is in progress.  If this
happens the backup will be readable and consistent with the state of the last checkpoint
if and only if there are no checkpoints between its start and completion.
Setting the interval to -1 will guarantee that the server, when starting after recovery
will not make a checkpoint.
</para>
			<para>
The dba must make sure that clients do not issue checkpoint
or shutdown statements while a backup is in progress.
</para>
			<para>The presence or absence of checkpoints at a given point in time can be
ascertained from the virtuoso.log event log file.
</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4 id="offlinebackups">
			<title>Off-Line Backups</title>
			<para>
When Virtuoso is not running a complete and clean backup can be taken by making
a copy of the database file and transaction file(s) created after the last
checkpoint.

</para>
			<para>
To get an up to the minute copy of a running database one can copy
the database file and the associated log, i.e. the file specified in
TransactionFile in the database&apos;s configuration file.  When started, the log
will roll forward and restore the database to the state following the
last logged transaction.
</para>
	</sect4>
	</sect3>
	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<sect3 id="vdbrecovery">
		<title>Database Recovery</title>
		<sect4 id="dbrebuild">
			<title>Rebuilding A Database</title>
			<para>
The process of rebuilding a database consists of dumping its contents
into a large log file, or log files, and doing a roll forward from an empty database
with that log.
</para>
			<para>
The general steps to rebuild a database are:
</para>
  <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
    <listitem><para>Shut down the running server, making a checkpoint.  This is done with
the SHUTDOWN command from interactive SQL.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Make sure there is a log file specified in virtuoso.ini.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Start the server process virtuoso with the -b command line
option: e.g. % ./virtuoso -b (+backup-dump)</para>
<para>This will write the contents of the database into the log file specified
in virtuoso.ini and exit when complete.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Take a backup of the old database file.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Change the DatabaseFile setting in virtuoso.ini to a
non-existing database file or delete the old database file.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Start the server with the +restore-crash-dump option. The option is essential.</para>
              <para>Important: When restore on v6 you also must give it +log6 flag i.e.: +restore-crash-dump +log6 .</para>
              <para>
                <tip><title>See Also:</title>
                  <para><ulink linkend="http://virtuoso.openlinksw.com/dataspace/dav/wiki/Main/VirtTipsAndTricksDBMSBackupCrashDump">How can I move a Virtuoso database from one hardware and/or software platform to another?</ulink></para>
                </tip>	
              </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>The server will build a new database file from the log and
once completed it will, by default, perform a checkpoint of the transactions to the
database file and start listening at the specified port.  Virtuoso can be
started without a checkpoint using the -n (+no-checkpoint) option.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>You may then connect to the database with interactive SQL
and if necessary make a checkpoint.  The checkpoint will write freeze the state
following roll forward and delete the log used for the rebuild.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>The database is now ready for normal use.</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
			<important>
				<para>It is recommended you take a backup copy of the database file(s)prior to this procedure.
</para>
			</important>

  <para>
	It may sometimes be useful to rebuild a database as above to save space.
	Virtuoso does not relinquish space in the DB file back to the file system as
	records are removed, however, Virtuoso does reuse pages that are made
	available from a deletion of records.  The steps above will build a new
	compact database file.  You would ordinarily not have to worry about this.
	</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4 id="diagnosingrepairing">
			<title>Diagnosing and Recovering a Damaged Database File</title>
			<para>
It is possible to recover data from a damaged Virtuoso database by
a procedure similar to rebuilding a database as described above.  A
database file may be corrupt if the database repeatedly crashes during
a specific operation.
</para>
			<para>
To determine whether a database is corrupt, you may use the backup to a null file
command in isql, for Unix platforms:
</para>
			<programlisting>
SQL&gt; backup &apos;/dev/null&apos;;
</programlisting>
      <para>For windows platforms you can use:</para>
			<programlisting>
SQL&gt; backup &apos;NUL&apos;;
</programlisting>

			<para>This command will read through the database checking
its integrity.  If the server crashes before completing the backup process, then
the database is indeed corrupt and needs to be recovered.  No other
activity should take place while the command is executing.
</para>
			<para>
To recover the database, follow the procedure for rebuilding it, except
use the -D &apos;capital D&apos; or +crash-dump switch instead of -b.  This will construct a
log file which you can replay to make a new database.  The database
will contain the transactions that were committed as of the last
successful checkpoint. If the database altogether fails to open it
may be the case that the schema is damaged.
<!-- In such a cases or if
the -D recovery crashes before completing consult the section,
<link linkend="Xcrashrecovery">Crash Recover When Normal
Crash Recovery Fails</link>. -->
</para>
			<para>
It is possible that the database to be recovered is too large
to fit in a single log file.  The crash dump feature therefore allows segmenting the
recovery log into a number of files. See the virtuoso.ini configuration file documentation
for details.  It is possible to make a crash dump in several pieces if there is not enough
total disk space to hold the dump on the system where the database is running.
</para>
			<para>
If the recovery log is split over several files it is  necessary to set the transaction file in the ini to point to the first of these files, delete the database file(s) and start the server with the +restore-crash-dump  option.  When the server comes online,
one can connect to it with isql and use the replay () function for replaying the remaining logs, one by one, in their original order.

</para>
			<para>
For example,assuming the virtuoso.ini fragment:
</para>
			<programlisting>
Log1	= rec-1.log 100M
Log2  = rec-2.log 100M
</programlisting>
			<para>
we would make the dump with
</para>
			<programlisting>
virtuoso +crash-dump
</programlisting>
			<para>
and once the server has been started with +restore-crash-dump, with the ini setting TransactionFile set to rec1.log, 
replay the remaining log with the isql commands:
</para>
			<programlisting>

SQL&gt; replay (&apos;rec-2.log&apos;);
Done.
SQL&gt; checkpoint;
</programlisting>
			<note>
				<title>Note:</title>
				<para>If the recovery is interrupted it can be restarted at the last checkpoint
made during the recovery.  Note that a mid recovery checkpoint may take a very long time, e.g.
1 hour  for a 10GB database, since it is possible that the delta since the
previous recovery checkpoint comprise almost all the database.
</para>
			</note>
		</sect4>

		<sect4 id="Xcrashrecovery">
			<title>Crash Recovery When The Normal Crash Recovery Fails</title>
			<para>
			    When the schema tables (e.g. DB.DBA.SYS_COLS, DB.DBA.SYS_KEYS) have corrupt rows
			    the normal crash dump/crash restore procedure will not be possible because the server
			    relies on the schema tables to know the key layouts for reading the
			    data rows of other tables upon crash dump.</para>

			    <para>In such situations there is a special procedure to be followed to save as much data as
			    possible from the corrupt database. The general steps are:</para>

<simplelist>
  <member>dump the intact schema table rows, and read them into a fresh database</member>
  <member>read the schema from the fresh database in the normal way</member>
  <member>proceed with dumping the rest of the tables from the corrupt database</member>
</simplelist>

				<para>Thus the transaction log produced from the corrupt database, when replayed
				on the new database file (the one holding the schema tables data) makes the closest
				approximation to the corrupt database's data.  However, this will not produce
				a workable database by itself - it may possibly deny inserting of data into tables
				with IDENTITY columns and will lose all the data within the Virtuoso registry
				(accessible from <function>registry_get()</function>/<function>registry_set()</function>
				functions).</para>

			    <para>Because of the very nature of the crash-restore process described here and
			    because of the fact that data is lost in the database schema, the server will not
			    attempt to dump tables whose schema description is lost.  So care should be
				taken when reading the data from the database.</para>

			    <para>This restoration procedure in no way replaces the regular database backup
				procedures, it merely tries to save whatever reasonable data there may be left
				from the database file.</para>

			<para>
The recovery sequence is as follows:
</para>

<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>
	Do a crash dump of the schema tables (using the
	'<computeroutput>+crash-dump +mode oa +dumpkeys schema</computeroutput>'
	virtuoso command line options).
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
	Create a new INI file to describe the layout of the new database you'll use to temporarily fill up the restored data.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
	Move the transaction log file(s) produced in step 1 to the location required by the new INI file.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
	Replay the transaction log from step 1 on an empty database using the new INI file.
	You will now have the schema tables readable in the new database (and nothing else):</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
Virtuoso options : -c <your new ini file> +restore-crash-dump -f
]]></programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>
	Make a crashdump of the data in the non-schema tables of the old database while
	having read the schema tables from the new database: </para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
    +crash-dump -c <your new ini file> +crash-dump-data-ini <your old ini file> +mode o -f
]]></programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>
	Move the transaction log file(s) produced in step 1 to the location required by the new INI file.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
	Replay the transaction log from the previous step into the new db file using: </para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
    -c <your new ini file> +restore-crash-dump
]]></programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>
	Do a normal crash dump of the new database:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
    -c <your new ini file> +crash-dump
]]></programlisting>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>
	Move away (backup) the original (old) database files and put the transaction log
	produced by the above step into the location specified in the original INI file.
	You can also delete the rest of the DB files of the new database at that point.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
	Replay the transaction log to make the old database afresh.
</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
			<para>
To automate the above procedure, a sample Unix script follows that automates it somewhat.
This script expects the crashed database virtuoso.db.save and an appropriate INI file
(no striping, no log segmentation, transaction log file name virtuoso.trx)
in the current directory and creates the restored database.
It also expects the virtuoso-iodbc-t executable to be in the operating
system path. Also, make sure that you have a
suitable <computeroutput>virtuoso.lic</computeroutput> license file in the current directory.
</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
#!/bin/sh

rm -rf xmemdump.txt virtuoso.trx virtuoso.tdb virtuoso.log virtuoso.db virtuoso.lck core.* new.lck new.log new.trx new.tdb new.db new.ini
cp -f virtuoso.db.save virtuoso.db
cat virtuoso.ini | sed 's/virtuoso\./new./g' > new.ini

virtuoso-iodbc-t -f +crash-dump +mode oa +dumpkeys schema

ls -la *.trx
mv virtuoso.trx new.trx

virtuoso-iodbc-t -c new -f -R
virtuoso-iodbc-t -c new +crash-dump +crash-dump-data-ini virtuoso.ini +mode o -f

ls -la *.trx
mv virtuoso.trx new.trx

virtuoso-iodbc-t -c new -R -f

virtuoso-iodbc-t -c new +crash-dump -f

rm -f virtuoso.trx virtuoso.tdb virtuoso.log virtuoso.db virtuoso.lck
ls -la *.trx
mv new.trx virtuoso.trx

virtuoso-iodbc-t -R -f
]]></programlisting>
		</sect4>

		<sect4 id="XversionRecovery">
			<title>Crash Recovery Across Virtuoso VDBMS Server Versions</title>
			<para>
If the database was created with a version prior to the one being used for
rebuilding, the system tables may be different.  The creation here refers to
the first time the database was made, a crash recovery does not count as a
fresh start here.
</para>
			<para>
If this is or may be the case, the first log must be rolled forward into the
empty database BEFORE the new and possibly incompatible system tables are created.
This is done by setting the TransactionFile parameter to the first of the
recovery logs and starting the server with the -R or +restore-crash-dump switch. For
good practice one should also specify  the no checkpoint switch, so that the log
will in no case be damaged after the initial step of the roll forward.
After this initial step the system tables will be compatible and the
dba can proceed to replay the remaining recovery logs with the replay function.
</para>
		</sect4>
		<sect4 id="procindexrecov"> 
      <title>Backup and Restore individual table(s) and individual index(s) on a new fresh db</title>			
      <para>This section describes how to get a part of db tables and restore on a new db.</para>
      <para>Additionally, part of the steps from below can be used to backup separate table and recover 
      	on same db.</para>
      <para>Note: Only effective with Virtuoso 6.0 and later.</para>        
      <para>Basic steps:</para>             
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>Create a function for dumping the key:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure bkp_key (in f any, in tb_name varchar, in key_name varchar)
{
  backup_prepare (f);
  backup_index (tb_name, key_name);
  backup_flush ();
  backup_close ();
}
;	
]]></programlisting>        	
        </listitem>
        <listitem>On the source db execute: 
<programlisting><![CDATA[
bkp_key ('mylog.txn', 'DB.DBA.T1', 'T1');	
]]></programlisting>        	
          <para>This will dump in a "mylog.txn" file the T1 table's primary key.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>On source db stop server and do: 
<programlisting><![CDATA[
virtuoso +backup-dump +foreground +mode l   ## ( lower case L )
]]></programlisting>        	
          <para>This will dump the schema tables only into the trx file.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>On the target db make sure there is no db file and place the trx file produced 
        	by previous step. Execute: 
<programlisting><![CDATA[
virtuoso +restore-crash-dump +foreground ;
]]></programlisting>        	
          <para>This will create a new db with same db schema as on the source db.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>Start the target and do: 
<programlisting><![CDATA[
replay ('mylog.txn') ;	
]]></programlisting>        	
          <para>This will insert the PK data into the table from the source db dump.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>If the table in question has other indexes must drop them and re-create them, since they 
        	are empty as in previous step we have been restoring only the PK.
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>      
      <para><emphasis>Note</emphasis>: following the steps from above can be dumped each index and 
      then replay. Also the steps may be combined for multiple tables and keys in the backup procedure - 
      just needs to be added the corresponding calls to the backup_index() function.</para>
    </sect4>
		</sect3>
</sect2>
