<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2013 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<sect2 id="bidirrepl"><title>Bi-Directional Snapshot Replication</title>

<para>Bi-directional snapshot replication allows you to set up snapshot replication
between multiple servers where updates can be performed on all servers.  
Bidirectional snapshot replication uses the publisher-subscriber model
where each table or DAV collection has only one publisher and when an
update is performed on subscriber it goes to publisher first, and then
to all other subscribers. Conflict resolution may need to take place on 
the publisher when data coming from a subscriber is processed.
Bi-directional snapshot replication uses snapshot logs on
publisher and subscribers to track changes in published table and its
replicas.</para>

<para>It is assumed that all tables published using bi-directional snapshot
replication have primary keys columns that are never modified.</para>

<para>To perform conflict resolution a ROWGUID column is added to every
published table. This column should never be modified manually.
All INSERT statements should specify exact column-select-lists that do not
include the ROWGUID column. Likewise the ROWGUID column should never feature
in any UPDATE statements.</para>

<para>Each server participating in bi-directional snapshot replication
must have unique name (replication name). For Virtuoso servers replication name
is assigned to the server in its virtuoso.ini file in the DBName setting.
For other RDBMS servers replication name is the name of instance or the
name of database. Replication name of remote server can be obtained
using <function>REPL_SERVER_NAME()</function> (after this server is defined,
see below).</para>

<para><function>REPL_CREATE_SNAPSHOT_PUB()</function> function should be used
to create bi-directional snapshot publication.</para>

<para>To create subscription for the publication, replication subscriber
server should be defined first using <function>REPL_SNP_SERVER()</function>
function. The name of the server can be obtained later using
<function>REPL_SERVER_NAME()</function> function.
After this <function>REPL_CREATE_SNAPSHOT_SUB()</function> function
should be used to create a subscription (and create replicated table on
subscriber if table replication takes place).</para>

<para>To load initial data on
subscriber <function>REPL_INIT_SNAPSHOT()</function> should be used
after subscription is created. Loading initial data can take some time
so <function>REPL_INIT_SNAPSHOT()</function> performs commits after every 100
rows are copied from source table to the table on subscriber to prevent
running out of transaction log or deadlocks.
It is possible to specify an alternative value for number of rows
per transaction (last parameter of <function>REPL_INIT_SNAPSHOT()</function>
function). In DAV case commits are performed per copied resource.
</para>

<para><function>REPL_UPDATE_SNAPSHOT()</function>
should be called periodically after initial data is loaded on subscriber
to sync published items (tables or DAV collections) on publisher and
subscribers. This function reads snapshot logs attached from subscribers
and replays them with possible conflict resolution. After all snapshot logs
from subscribers are processed an updating procedure reads snapshot
log on publisher and replays it on all subscribers.</para>

<note><title>Note:</title>
<para>Please note that all operations in bi-directional snapshot replication
(publication, subscription, doing initial copy, syncing) should be performed
on publisher.</para>
</note>

<example><title>Creating bi-directional snapshot publication</title>
<para>This example demonstrates creating bi-directional snapshot publication
of table 'Demo.demo.Shippers'.</para>
<screen>
SQL> REPL_CREATE_SNAPSHOT_PUB ('Demo.demo.Shippers', 2);
</screen>
</example>

<example><title>Creating bi-directional snapshot subscription</title>
<para>This example demonstrates creating bi-directional snapshot subscription
for table 'Demo.demo.Shippers' and loading initial data on subscriber with
DSN 'localhost:1121'.</para>
<screen>
SQL> REPL_SNP_SERVER ('localhost:1121', 'dba', 'dba');
SQL> REPL_CREATE_SNAPSHOT_SUB (REPL_SERVER_NAME ('localhost:1121'), 'Demo.demo.Shippers', 2);
SQL> REPL_INIT_SNAPSHOT (REPL_SERVER_NAME ('localhost:1121'), 'Demo.demo.Shippers', 2);
</screen>
</example>

<example><title>Syncing bi-directional snapshot publication</title>
<para>This example demonstrates syncing bi-directional snapshot publication
of table 'Demo.demo.Shippers'.</para>
<screen>
SQL> REPL_UPDATE_SNAPSHOT ('Demo.demo.Shippers', 2);
</screen>
</example>

<tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para>The following functions are used for creating, dropping and updating 
  publications and subscriptions to them:</para>
	<para><link linkend="fn_REPL_CREATE_SNAPSHOT_SUB"><function>REPL_CREATE_SNAPSHOT_SUB()</function></link></para>
	<para><link linkend="fn_REPL_CREATE_SNAPSHOT_PUB"><function>REPL_CREATE_SNAPSHOT_PUB()</function></link></para>
	<para><link linkend="fn_REPL_DROP_SNAPSHOT_SUB"><function>REPL_DROP_SNAPSHOT_SUB()</function></link></para>
	<para><link linkend="fn_REPL_DROP_SNAPSHOT_PUB"><function>REPL_DROP_SNAPSHOT_PUB()</function></link></para>
	<para><link linkend="fn_REPL_INIT_SNAPSHOT"><function>REPL_INIT_SNAPSHOT()</function></link></para>
	<para><link linkend="fn_REPL_UPDATE_SNAPSHOT"><function>REPL_UPDATE_SNAPSHOT()</function></link></para>
	<para><link linkend="fn_REPL_SNP_SERVER"><function>REPL_SNP_SERVER()</function></link></para>
	<para><link linkend="fn_REPL_SERVER_NAME"><function>REPL_SERVER_NAME()</function></link></para>
</tip>

<sect3 id="bidireplconflictrsln"><title>Conflict Resolution</title>

  <para>Since every table can have only one publisher, conflicts can only 
  occur on the publisher when modifications from a subscriber are attempted.  
  When DML operations originating on a subscriber are being replayed 
  on the publisher, three types of conflicts can arise:</para>

<orderedlist>
 <listitem><formalpara><title>uniqueness conflict (insert conflict)</title>
	<para>occurs when the row with some primary key &lt;PK&gt;
	already exists in publisher's table.</para></formalpara></listitem>

 <listitem><formalpara><title>update conflict</title>
	<para>occurs when UPDATE modifies a row which has already been modified
	on publisher (by the publisher or another subscriber)</para></formalpara></listitem>

 <listitem><formalpara><title>delete conflict</title>
	<para>occurs when DELETE deletes a row that does not exist on publisher
        anymore.</para></formalpara></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>Delete conflicts when UPDATE modifies a row that does not exist
on publisher can't be detected in snapshot replication case.</para>

<para>Every table has a number of conflict resolvers which are used
for conflict resolution which are enlisted in the 
<computeroutput>DB.DBA.SYS_SNAPSHOT_CR</computeroutput> system table. 
Each conflict resolver has a type, one of ('I', 'U', or 'D'), and an order.  Conflict 
resolvers are applied in ascending order.</para>

<para>The conflict resolver is a Virtuoso/PL procedure that receives a 
conflicting row from a subscriber and some other arguments.  The conflict 
resolver can modify the row, which is passed as an 'inout' argument.
The conflict resolver should return an integer value, which will be used
for conflict resolution.</para>

<para>Conflict resolvers of different types have different signatures:</para>

<simplelist>
 <member>
   <para><emphasis>'I' - Insert conflict resolvers</emphasis></para>
   <para>(&lt;ALLCOLS&gt;, inout _origin varchar)</para></member>

 <member>
   <para><emphasis>'U' - Update conflict resolvers</emphasis></para>
   <para>(&lt;ALLCOLS&gt;, inout _origin varchar)</para></member>

 <member>
   <para><emphasis>'D' - Deletion conflict resolvers</emphasis></para>
   <para>(&lt;PK&gt;, inout _origin varchar)</para></member>
   </simplelist>

<para>where</para>

<para>&lt;ALLCOLS&gt; are the new values of all columns 
(including the ROWGUID column), &lt;PK&gt; are the values of primary 
key columns, and _origin is transaction originator.</para>

<para>Conflict resolvers can return the following integer values; 
The conflict resolver types concerned for each are listed in parentheses:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>0 - un-decide (I, U, D)</title>
	<para>next conflict resolver will be fired.</para></formalpara></listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>1 - subscriber wins (I, U, D)</title>
	<para>DML operation will be applied with &lt;ALLCOLS&gt;
	All the subscribers except originator will receive modifications
	(originator already has them).</para></formalpara></listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>2 - subscriber wins, change origin (I, U)</title>
	<para>DML operation will be applied with &lt;ALLCOLS&gt; and origin
	of transaction will be changed to publisher's server name.
	All the subscribers (including originator) will receive modifications.
	This return value is useful when conflict resolver changed some of
	the columns of the row that were passed in.
    Although all parameters of conflict resolver are inout
    only changing of &lt;ALLCOLS&gt; (non-PK columns) parameters 
	makes sense.</para></formalpara></listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>3 - publisher wins (U)</title>
	<para>DML operation will be applied with &lt;ALLCOLS&gt; taken from
	publisher's table. All the subscribers will receive
	modifications.</para></formalpara></listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>4 - reserved</title><para /></formalpara></listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>5 - ignore (D)</title>
	<para>DML operation is ignored.</para></formalpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Conflict resolution stops when some conflict resolver returns a non-zero
value meaning that it has made a decision.</para>

<example id="ex_conflictresln"><title>Conflict Resolution</title>
<para>Suppose we have the following table:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
create table items(
  item_id integer primary key,

  name varchar,
  price decimal
);
]]></programlisting>

<para>"Publisher wins" 'I' conflict resolver will look like:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure items_cr(
    inout _item_id integer,
    inout _name varchar,
    inout _price decimal,
    inout _origin varchar)
  returns integer
{
  return 3;
}
]]></programlisting>

<para>The conflict resolver that will make a decision based on the 
minimal price column will look like:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure items_cr(
    inout _item_id integer,
    inout _name varchar,
    inout _price decimal,
    inout _rowguid varchar,
    inout _origin varchar)
  returns integer
{
  declare p decimal;
  -- get current price value
  select price into p from items where item_id = _item_id;
  if (p < _price)
    return 3;			-- publisher wins
  else if (p > _price)
    return 1;			-- subscriber wins
  return 0;			-- can't decide
}
]]></programlisting>

<para>The conflict resolver that will change the price to the minimal value 
will look like:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure items_cr(
    inout _item_id integer,
    inout _name varchar,
    inout _price decimal,
    inout _rowguid varchar,
    inout _origin varchar)
  returns integer
{
  declare p decimal;
  -- get current price value
  select price into p from items where item_id = _item_id;
  if (p < _price)
    {
      _price := p;
      return 2;			-- publisher wins, change origin
    }
  return 1;			-- subscriber wins
}
]]></programlisting>
</example>

<para>Conflict resolution occurs differently for each kind of DML operation:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>INSERT</title>
	<para>When INSERT of some row with primary key &lt;PK&gt; is replayed,
	the row in the publisher's table with such &lt;PK&gt; is looked-up.
	If the row does not exist then there is no conflict, conflict 
	resolution stops and the INSERT is replayed.
	If the row exists then we have a "uniqueness conflict".  In this case 'I'
	conflict resolvers are fired-up.
	If none of the 'I' conflict resolvers were able to make a decision
	(return non-zero value) the default action is 'publisher wins'.</para>
	</formalpara></listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>UPDATE</title>

	<para>When there is an UPDATE of some row with primary 
	key &lt;PK&gt; is replayed, the row (and its ROWGUID) in 
	publisher's table with such &lt;PK&gt; is looked-up.
	If the row does not exist then we have a "delete conflict", 
	'D' conflict resolvers are fired up.  If none of the 'D' conflict 
	resolvers were able to make a decision the default action will be 
	to 'ignore'.
	If the row exists in the publisher's table and its ROWGUID is the same
	as that from the subscriber then there is no conflict.  Conflict
	resolution stops and the UPDATE is replayed.
	If the row exists and its ROWGUID differs from the one that came
	from subscriber then we have an "update conflict".  In this case the 
	'U' conflict resolvers are fired-up.
	If none of the 'U' conflict resolvers were able to make a decision 
	(return non-zero value) the default action will be 'publisher wins'.</para>
	</formalpara></listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>DELETE</title>

	<para>When DELETE operation of some row with primary key &lt;PK&gt;
        is replayed, the row in the publisher's table with such &lt;PK&gt;
        is looked-up.  
	If the row does not exist or if the row exists but its
	ROWGUID differs from the one that came from subscriber then
	we have "delete conflict".  The 'D' conflict resolvers are fired-up.  
	If none of the 'D' conflict resolvers were able to make a decision then the 
	default action will be taken to 'ignore'.
	Otherwise it is assumed that there is no conflict and DELETE statement 
	is replayed.</para>
	</formalpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect3>


<sect3 id="bidirreplconflictdav"><title>Conflict Resolution in WebDAV</title>

<para>Conflict resolvers in DAV are found based on the collection.
The closest collection that specifies resolvers will be the one providing
the resolver set. Resolvers from any enclosing collection will
not be invoked.</para>

<para>There is special subcollection in each replicated collection
named '_SYS_REPL_BACKUP'. This subcollection is never replicated and
is used to store backup copies of resources that lose conflict
resolution.</para>

<para>If a resource is locked during an update it will be stored in temporary 
location.  Conflict resolution will take place after the lock is released.  
If the update was performed on the publisher then no conflict resolution 
will be performed on the subscribers and the resource from temporary location 
will simply replace an existing resource after the lock is released.</para>

<para>Default conflict resolution is 'publisher wins'.</para>

<para>Delete conflicts are not handled when replicating DAV because updates 
are the same as inserts -- if the resource that was updated does not exist it will
be created.  INSERT or uniqueness conflict for the same reasons.</para>

<para>Subcollections are not considered in conflict resolution.
Subcollections are always created as needed during an update.   
This means that if a resource is updated locally but collection that holds
this resource does not exist on remote peer it will be created.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="bidirreplsutogenres"><title>Automatically Generated Conflict Resolvers</title>

<para>Simple table conflict resolvers can be generated automatically 
by calling the <function>REPL_ADD_SNAPSHOT_CR()</function> function.  
DAV conflict resolvers be generated by calling 
<function>REPL_ADD_DAV_CR()</function> function.</para>

<tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para><link linkend="fn_REPL_ADD_DAV_CR"><function>REPL_ADD_DAV_CR()</function></link></para>
  <para><link linkend="fn_REPL_ADD_SNAPSHOT_CR"><function>REPL_ADD_SNAPSHOT_CR()</function></link></para>
  </tip>

<para>The generated procedures can be modified afterwards.  In particular it is 
possible to change the notification e-mail address by setting the _notify_email parameter, 
and the notification text by setting the _notify_text parameter.</para>

<para>The default behaviour for generated procedures is 'pub_wins', making a 
backup and notifying the owner by e-mail.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
