<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2013 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<chapter label="concepts.xml" id="concepts">
  <title>Conceptual Overview</title>
  <abstract>
    <para>Virtuoso provides both a native database capability and a
    virtual database that integrates remote or third-party ODBC data
    sources seamlessly with Virtuoso's own.  The virtual database (VDB)
    allows transparent unified queries across all linked data sources. The
    Virtuoso server supports ANSI SQL92, object extensions, and a
    significant set of PL extensions.  The most important extensions
    include support for modern Internet standards for communication, data,
    and document exchange.  Virtuoso supports communications protocols
    such as HTTP, SMTP and NNTP as well as a full suite of XML-based
    protocols including XML, XSL, SOAP, and WSDL.</para>
  </abstract>

<!-- ########################################### -->

&dbconcepts;

<!-- ########################################### -->

  <sect1 id="thevdbrel"><title>Virtual Database (VDB) Engine</title>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem><link linkend="consneed4vdb">The Need for VDB Engines</link></listitem>
      <listitem><link linkend="consfirstvdbps">First Generation Virtual Database Products</link></listitem>
      <listitem><link linkend="vdbimpliss">VDB Implementation Issues</link></listitem>
      <listitem><link linkend="vdbcomponents">VDB Engine Components</link></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webinternetproto"><title>Web &amp; Internet Protocol Support</title>
  <para>Virtuoso provides direct access to a number of Internet protocols through
  built in procedures.  These protocols include SMTP, NNTP, POP3, HTTP, XML and many
  more.  Combined with Virtuoso's native database and virtual database capabilities
  applications can be developed very rapidly from scratch or existing systems can be
  enhanced with a rich set of tools.  An old customer table can be used to create a
  mail shot; a products table can now generate an XML file which can be converted to
  plain text and or HTML via XSLT which can be emailed to the customers every week
  automatically using the scheduler, or on request from a VSP page served by the
	HTTP server.  The possibilities are endless and all these abilities are contained
	within a single server.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="websrvcsproto"><title>Web Services Protocol Support</title>
	<para>The Internet is reaching a stage where automatic processes want to rely
	on other sites and services presenting their uses in a standard way.  This is
	Web Services.  What ever an organization or repository of data contains the
	it needs to be exploited as fully as possibly.  This is exposing existing
	systems as Web Services.  These need to be accessible over well known protocols
	which combine to provide a service over the web.</para>
	<para>SQL provides the means to query data within a database.  This is a very
	well known and supported operation.  The query may or may not be able to
	make use of free text indexes to obtain results faster and more accurately from
	textual sources.  The source could even come from a remote database contacted
	over ODBC, JDBC or OLEDB - more well supported standards.  The results may be
	shipped to another server for further processing.  Further processing could
	include transformations into various XML's directly or via an XSLT stylesheet.
	This collaboration of services can be enhanced further with other Web and Internet
	protocols for the grand objective of making parts of useful information or
	ability consumable over the Internet as a Web Service. </para>
    <figure id="virtpyramid" float="1"><title>Towards Web Services...</title>
    <graphic fileref="virtpyramid.jpg" width="322px" depth="239px"/></figure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="conceptarchitecture"><title>Architecture</title>

	<para>The base of Virtuoso is the Virtuoso Data Management.  This
	handles the normal tasks of the database and virtual database collaborating
	between local native and remote SQL and XML based resources.  Web and Internet
	services and protocols then sit atop of this layer to expose Virtuoso to the Web
	and its users.</para>

<figure id="varch322" float="1"><title>OpenLink Virtuoso Product Architecture</title>
  <graphic fileref="varch32.jpg" width="384px" depth="377px"/></figure>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
