<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2015 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<sect2 id="dbpumpdev"><title>DBPump Developers Reference</title>

  <para>DBPump is a VSP application for selective data and schema export of 
  Virtuoso content.  DBPump is also a backup and restore utility</para>

  <sect3 id="vspintrinsics"><title>VSP - Pages Intrinsics</title>

    <para>The implementation of the DBPUMP VSP pages has been abstracted into 
    interface content and sensible work.  DBPUMP consists of a number of independent 
    components each of which can be called by name and VSP pages can be considered 
    just as a visually convenient method to call this components.  Each page consists 
    of three parts - header, body and footer.  In header we can see the title of 
    current page and the set of buttons - jumps to other pages. Page body contains 
    the current contest and footer currently is empty with exception for possibility 
    to turn on a debug printing.  All DBPUMP VSP-pages use the  component 
   'retrieve_oper_pars' explicitly implicitly and we will not refer to this 
   component later.</para>

  <para>The Dump Page (dump_page.vsp) lets you save the current database schema 
  and selected tables.  The Schema dump contains:</para>
  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
    <listitem>creation of all users in file 'users.sql'</listitem>
    <listitem>creation of new qualifiers in the same file</listitem>
    <listitem>views section, and normal and XML views are created here in 'views.sql' file</listitem>
    <listitem>stored procedures in 'procs.sql' file</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The <emphasis>Current Directory</emphasis> or Folder in the 
  context of a DBPUMP dump denotes the root directory of the tables 
  dump.  This directory will contain the schema (if needed) and temporary 
  files for Isql.  Each table dump will be placed in a subdirectory.  
  The name of such subdirectories is not the same as the table name because 
  the name of a table can be too long and/or contain characters considered invalid 
  by the file system.  The name is devised as a string representation 
  of subsequent number with suffix '.table'.  In these subdirectories there can be 
  files of 3 kinds:</para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
    <listitem><emphasis>blob.xxxx</emphasis> files with outlined blobs, file size is 
    in general limited by 'split_by' option in 'Options' page, if the blob is greater 
    then 'split_by' parameter,  the current blob file will be closed and the next will be 
    written without size restriction.  xxxx here means 0000 for first file, 0001 for 
    second, etc...</listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>data.xxxx</emphasis> files with table data.  The same file 
    length rules apply.  These files have their structure as follows:  

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>magic: "--DBPUMP--\n" written through 
      'PrpcWriteObject', we should note here that all values in this file 
      are written via this mechanism.</listitem>
      <listitem>Raw table name e.g.: 'Demo.demo.Order_Details'</listitem>
      <listitem>comment defined by user in 'T-Dump' page</listitem>
      <listitem>serialization of DBPUMP's internal state at the moment of 
      dump (we will talk about the mechanism of permanent state transmission few later).</listitem>
      <listitem>the beginning of a SQL insert statement up to the data values, this 
      will be used for data restore.  Certainly this can be easily calculated 
      through column info but in such form it is very useful to control data 
      serialization and in general you can consider it as additional reserve point.</listitem>
      <listitem>reserve</listitem>
      <listitem>number of 'before tables' - tables which should be created before 
      the current one (and, obviously, drooped after it)</listitem>
      <listitem>above described number of strings with tables names</listitem>
      <listitem>number of 'after tables' - which are antipodes of 'before tables'</listitem>
      <listitem>above described number of strings with tables names</listitem>
      <listitem>number of schema clauses which are:  drops, table and indices 
      creations, grants and triggers</listitem>
      <listitem>above described number of strings with SQL statements</listitem>
      <listitem>number of columns</listitem>
      <listitem><para>for each column we have:</para>
        <simplelist>
        <member>column type as returned by ODBC SQLColumns</member>
        <member>column bind type - as was used in ODBC SQLBindCol for main loop's 'select'</member>
        <member>is that blob flag</member>
        <member>column name</member>
        <member>reserve</member>
        </simplelist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>the rest of the file is filled with data row by row, column by column 
        in the same order as filled above.  The number of 'PrpcWriteObject' calls 
        per column depends only on the column type, usually this is 1 call for integers 
        or varchar, up to 7 calls in case of TIMESTAMP.  The most complex case is the 
        blob type (SQL_LONGVARCHAR, SQL_LONGVARBINARY, SQL_WLONGVARCHAR).  If blob length 
        is less then some threshold (currently 64 bytes) it will be written as varchar 
        with pre-written integer zero, in other case the blob's record consists of three 
        items: integer length in bytes, starting position of blob in file, the name of blob file.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><emphasis>text.xxxx</emphasis> files for dump in plain text mode, this 
      is very similar to what you get at 'T-Restore' procedure with the following 
      exceptions:
        <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>It will not be possible to restore this data by no means 
          except manual Isql call</listitem>
          <listitem>even this will not work if your table has foreign key(s) 
          and/or super-table</listitem>
          <listitem>each table slice will have stored procedure with table creation, 
          but only in first one there will be explicit call of this procedure</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      <listitem><emphasis>isql.code</emphasis> temporary log file with all SQL 
      statements concerning this table</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Now let's glance at the T-Dump page itself.  In the upper area you can see two 
    list-box for tables selection.  In left one there are available tables.  
    With buttons '&lt;', '&lt;&lt;', '&gt;&gt;' and '&gt;' you can manipulate by them.  
    It should be noticed that the number of really dumped tables can be greater then 
    the number of selected tables.  The reason is that there exists dependencies with 
    other tables via foreign keys and super-tables.  Below table filters and comments 
    are placed.  Filter works on the list of available tables, to activate them you 
    should enter some values in one of them and press the Refresh button below.</para>


    <para>The Filter Options page (filter_options.vsp) represents all options for filtering management.</para>

    <para>The Advanced Dump Options page (dump_options.vsp) represents all options and execution parameters which 
    can be found in DBPUMP VSP pages.</para>

    <para>The Advanced Restore Options page (restore_options.vsp) represents all options and execution 
    parameters which can be found in DBPUMP VSP pages.</para>

    <para>The Password page (passwd_page.vsp) is a gate way from interface to action pages.</para>

    <para>The Restore page (restore_page.vsp) can restore previously saved state 
    of selected tables.  This page uses following DBPUMP components:</para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem><emphasis>choice_rpath</emphasis> gets tree-like list of dbpump's subtree</listitem>
      <listitem><emphasis>choice_rschema</emphasis> - gets *.dbk sub folders in current folder</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The Browse page (browse_page.vsp) can choice real path from dbpump's server's root. 
    This page uses following DBPUMP components:</para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem><emphasis>choice_rpath</emphasis> gets tree-like list of dbpump's subtree</listitem>
      <listitem><emphasis>choice_rschema</emphasis> gets *.dbk sub folders in current folder</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The algorithm of those page's action is relatively complex.  For every requested table 
    we should recursively get lists of dependent tables.  As result of this procedure we will 
    get new (probably greater) ordered list of requested tables.  Having this list we can 
    execute a set of sequent ODBC calls through 4 passes:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem>drops in back order</listitem>
      <listitem>creations in normal order</listitem>
      <listitem>rows of data in normal order</listitem>
      <listitem>triggers creations in any order</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The result of the conversion piece by piece will be executed and 
    a common error output will be returned to http client.  
    </para>
  
    <para>The Dump Results page (dump_itself.vsp) is an action page.  It calls 
    'dump_tables' component and displays results.</para>

    <para>The Restore Results page (restore_itself.vsp) is an action page.  It calls 
    'restore_tables' component and displays results.</para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="context"><title>DBPUMP's context.</title>
    <para>This context consists of the set of named and internally registered 
    character values.  Internally each component can get a value of every such 
    value and use its value by any way.  There exists the only parameter with 
    pre-defined name 'all_together_now' and trying to obtain its value you'll 
    get the serialization of all other parameters. Symmetrically, an attempt to 
    set value of this parameter will yield to deserialization of previously 
    saved state.  Consequently every VSP-page should have hidden input element 
    with such name.  Because of every VSP page in first steps runs 'retrieve_oper_pars' 
    (or its relative) which returns deserialization of all parameters including that 
    (without recursion, sure).  So if we have synonymous hidden field, at hotel 
    form submission its value will be posted and values of all (not only existing 
    in current form) parameters will be restored.  So if hotel form has input elements 
    with registered in DBPUMP names, values of this parameters will be also accepted 
    by DBPUMP and serialized in the next iteration of 'all_together_now'.</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="commandline"><title>DBPUMP's command line.</title>
    <para>DBPUMP has different variants of execution:</para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
      <listitem><para>normal. Command line syntax is: </para> 
<programlisting>
dbpump component-name [ component-arg [ output-file-name ] ] 
  [oper-par1-name=oper-par1-value] ... [oper-parN-name=oper-parN-value]
</programlisting>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>via file: dbpump @file-name and in this file we 
      should store all arguments in the first(normal) form</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>component-name is one of the set of internally registered components 
    names, if this name is unknown the result will be void.  Some components have 
    arguments, some not.  Extra arguments can not break something  and if component 
    doesn't require argument but you are interested in file output, you can freely 
    pass as argument whatever you want.  All parameters have names consisting only 
    from printable chars but in value of parameter there can be placed any string.  
    Due to this, values of parameters should be passed in urlified form (i.e. ' '='+', 
    printable chars as is, other in form '%xx').</para>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="components"><title>DBPUMP's Components.</title>
    <para>DBPUMP does not have its own behavior, all that it can do is to construct 
    operational parameters pool, run required component, pass to it argument and 
    print out component's messages.  In fact DBPUMP is a set of independent 
    mini-programs under one roof.  Such components are:</para>

    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
					<listitem>
	  'retrieve_oper_pars' - we have already talked about it. This component just prints all not-empty parameters in form:
	  par1-name=par1-urlified-value&amp;par2-name=par2-urlified-value&amp;...
	  Used operational parameters: all or required 
	  Argument: '*' for all or list of parameters with delimiter '@'
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
	  'select_datasources' - when on WIN32 DBPUMP was not linked with native odbc32.lib this returns a list of available datasources in form:
	  dsn1-name=dsn1-description&amp;dsn2-name=dsn2-description&amp;...
	  In other cases this returns nothing.
	  Used operational parameters: none 
	  Argument: none
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
	  'retrieve_tables' - this returns list of available tables in similar form:
	  table1-name=table1-name&amp;table2-name=table2-name&amp;...
	  Used operational parameters:
						<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
							<listitem>
		  'datasource'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'user'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'password'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'qualifier'
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
	  Argument: none
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
	  'choice_tables' - this will give you the list of tables selected for dump in the same form as previous component.
	  Used operational parameters:
						<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
							<listitem>
		  'choice_sav' - summarization of all 'choice_tables' from listbox with such name
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
	  Argument: none
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
	  'choice_rpath' - this component will give you the sub-tree of server file system. This component will recursively fall into each 
	  sub folder (including symlinks, this generates the problem of cycling, this situation yields to zero output after maximal depth will be achieved). 
	  The root folder of this sub-tree will be placed in  'ServerRoot' parameter of section [HTTPServer] of Virtuoso config file. 
	  Each sub folders will occupy one pair of output:
	  real_path1=indented-name1&amp;real_path2=indented-name2&amp;...
	  Used operational parameters: none 
	  Argument: none
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
	  'choice_rdir' - returns the content of current folder. To do this it should descend in all sub folders and try to find file 'data.0000'.
	  If it exists, the header should be read and table name found. The result will be in form:
	  table1-name=table1-name&amp;table2-name=table2-name&amp;...
	  Used operational parameters:
						<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
							<listitem>
		  'rpath' - selected row in corresponding listbox
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
	  Argument: none
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
	  'dump_tables' this component will try to do the above described procedure of tables dump, the error and info output of which 
	  will be put into operational parameter 'result' and then all parameters will be output as in 'retrieve_oper_pars'.
	  This component is called from 'dump_tables_itself.vsp'
	  Used operational parameters:
						<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
							<listitem>
		  'datasource'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'user'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'password'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'comment'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'dump_path' remote path, the root path for all dump
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'dump_dir' remote path, the name of dump folder, if not ended with '.dbk', will be concatenated with it
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'choice_sav' - summarization of all 'choice_tables' from listbox with such name
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'table_defs' - if is equal to 'on', the create table statement will be included into the dump
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'triggers' - if is equal to 'on', the create trigger statements will be included into the dump
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'stored_procs' - if is equal to 'on', the create procedure statements will be put into dump root's procs.sql file
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'constraints' - if is equal to 'on', the create index statements will be included into the dump
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'constraints' - if is equal to 'on', the foreign keys create statements will be included into the dump
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'views' - if is equal to 'on', the create view will be put into dump root's views.sql file
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'users' - if is equal to 'on', the create user statements will be put into dump root's users.sql file
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'grants' - if is equal to 'on', the grant statements will be included into dump file
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'table_data' - if is equal to 'on', the data themselves will be included into dump file
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'change_qualifier' - if is equal to 'on', all statements will be put with the qualifier from 'new_qualifier'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'change_owner' - if is equal to 'on', all statements will be put with the owner from 'new_owner'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'new_qualifier' - this will be used if 'change_qualifier' is set to 'on'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'new_owner' - this will be used if 'change_owner' is set to 'on'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'custom_qual' - integer, if not zero, the value from 'selected_qualifier' will be used as filter in procedures and views output but not in tables filter such as tables can have foreign references across qualifiers.
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'selected_qualifier' - this will be used when 'custom_qual' is not zero
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'split_by' - integer, means the length in MB of created data and blob slice.
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
	  Argument N1: '*' for all or list of parameters with delimiter '@'
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
	  'restore_tables' - the same but the procedure is tables restore.
	  This component is called from 'restore_tables_itself.vsp'
	  Used operational parameters:
						<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
							<listitem>
		  'datasource'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'user'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'password'
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'dump_path' remote path, the root path for all dump
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'dump_dir' remote path, the name of dump folder, if not ended with '.dbk', will be concatenated with it
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
		  'choice_sav' - summarization of all 'choice_tables' from listbox with such name
							</listitem>
						</itemizedlist>
	  Argument: none
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>

			</sect3>
	      	<sect3 id="sql_api">
			<title>SQL API.</title>
			<para>
				<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
					<listitem>
"DB"."DBA"."BACKUP_ALL_VIA_DBPUMP"  - returns varchar. Backs up tables with all qualifiers. Arguments are:
					<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
						<listitem>
in username varchar
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
in passwd varchar - password
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
in datasource varchar - something like 'localhost:1111'
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
in dump_path varchar - means 'dump directory' in 'Dump' page.
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
in dump_dir varchar - means 'dump name' in 'Dump' page.
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
"DB"."DBA"."BACKUP_SCHEMA_VIA_DBPUMP"  - returns varchar. Backs up tables with selected qualifier. Arguments are:
					<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
						<listitem>
in username varchar
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
in passwd varchar - password
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
in datasource varchar - something like 'localhost:1111'
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
in qualifier varchar - selected qualifier
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
in dump_path varchar - means 'dump directory' in 'Dump' page.
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
in dump_dir varchar - means 'dump name' in 'Dump' page.
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
"DB"."DBA"."RESTORE_DBPUMP'S_FOLDER"  - returns varchar. Restores what you have backed up. Arguments are:
					<itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
						<listitem>
in username varchar
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
in passwd varchar - password
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
in datasource varchar - something like 'localhost:1111'
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
in dump_path varchar - means 'dump directory' in 'Dump' page.
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
in dump_dir varchar - means 'dump name' in 'Dump' page.
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
</para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
