<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2006 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->

<sect1 id="expwsmodules"><title>Exposing Persistent Stored Modules as Web Services</title>
  <para>Virtuoso SQL stored procedures and functions can be exposed as SOAP
  services very simply from Virtuoso, whether they are native Virtuoso or
  on remote data sources.  This powerful ability means that any database servers
  already existing within an organization can easily become a component in an
  eBusiness solution using Virtuoso.  All you need is a few simple steps that
  typically take mere minutes to complete:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Choose your stored procedure(s)</title>
    <para>The procedures that you want to expose can either be native Virtuoso
    stored procedures, or remote stored procedures that can be linked in using
    the Remote Procedures user interface.</para></formalpara>
    </listitem>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Choose a virtual directory</title>
    <para>Because SOAP services need to be exposed and accessed via HTTP a
    Virtuoso virtual directory must be used.  Either use the existing
    SOAP virtual directory or create a new one.</para></formalpara>
    </listitem>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Publish procedures to virtual directory</title>
    <para>The user specified as SOAP account on the virtual directorymust have execute privileges on the procedures.
    Use the Publish options on the virtual directory user interface.</para></formalpara>
    </listitem>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Test the VSMX output</title>
    <para>Once procedures have been published as SOAP services they are
    automatically described by WSDL and testable using Virtuoso's VSMX feature.</para>
    </formalpara></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>XML Query Templates provide a direct way to store SQL in an XML file on
  the Virtuoso server that when executed, i.e. fetched from a web browser, actually
  returns the results of the query.</para>

  <para>The Virtuoso Server Extension Interface (VSEI) chapter describes how
  users can define custom Virtuoso functions from C or other programming
  languages, which can be used from within Virtuoso PL.  This also means
  that VSEs can also be published as Web Services.</para>

<sect2 id="expwspls"><title>Publishing Stored Procedures as Web Services</title>

  <sect3 id="expwssps"><title>Choosing Stored Procedures to Expose</title>
  <para>You can either expose native Virtuoso stored procedures
  (previously defined or newly created) using the CREATE PROCEDURE
  statement, or stored procedures from other database types can be linked
  into Virtuoso using an ODBC data source.</para>
  <para>Virtuoso lists available stored procedures for each catalog under the option:
  <emphasis>/Database/Databases/&lt;catalog_name&gt;/Stored Procedures</emphasis>
  from the menu of the Virtuoso Server Administration Interface.  This list will
  also include any remote procedures already linked into Virtuoso.</para>

  <para>To link a stored procedure from another database system we must first
  create a valid data source that leads to a connection to that database.
  Once verified proceed to the Remote Procedures page.</para>

  <figure float="1"><title>Linking Procedures from Remote Data Sources</title>
    <graphic fileref="ui/admrmtprocs001.jpg" width="561px" depth="245px"/></figure>

	<para>The data source will be listed in the data sources list.  Select the
  data source that you want to used, check the Username and Password fields
  and press the <emphasis>List</emphasis> button.  The page will next require
  you to select the catalog/owner combination
  to refine the search list of procedures on the remote data source.  Use
  the drop-down to select relevant option and press <emphasis>List Selected</emphasis>
  to list the available stored procedures.</para>

  <figure float="1"><title>Linking Procedures from Remote Data Sources</title>
    <graphic fileref="ui/admrmtprocs002.jpg" width="307px" depth="66px"/></figure>

  <para>When the page returns you will be presented with a list of
  available remote procedures.  You can link any of the listed
  procedures into Virtuoso by selecting them from the list and pressing the
  <emphasis>Link Selected</emphasis> button.</para>

  <figure float="1"><title>Linking Procedures from Remote Data Sources</title>
    <graphic fileref="ui/admrmtprocs003.jpg" width="383px" depth="145px"/></figure>

  <para>You will be presented with a new page listing the chosen procedures
  and their data type information.  This gives you an opportunity
  to alter the  data type mappings that Virtuoso will use both internally and
  for any future interactions with the SOAP server.  If you do not want to
  specify any special type information the details can be left as default.</para>

  <figure float="1"><title>Linking Procedures from Remote Data Sources</title>
    <graphic fileref="ui/admrmtprocs004.jpg" width="553px" depth="260px"/></figure>

  <para>For each remote procedure you may change how they
  will be referenced within Virtuoso by making changes to the fields for
  <emphasis>Local Name</emphasis>, <emphasis>Database</emphasis>, and
  <emphasis>Schema</emphasis> fields.  These fields define how you will find the
  linked procedure locally to Virtuoso only and do not affect the remote
  data source.</para>

  <para>For each procedure there is an option to <emphasis>Use PL Wrapper</emphasis>.
  This option is required if your remote procedure is capable of returning
  a resultset that you want to process via Virtuoso.</para>

  <para>Once the details are correct press the Link button to proceed to the next
  step: Defining Virtual Directories.</para>

  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para><link linkend="remoteprocedures">Linking Remote Procedures</link></para></tip>
  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="expwsvirtdir"><title>Defining Virtual Directories</title>
  <para>Before any procedures native or linked can be exposed as SOAP Services
  a location in HTTP space must be defined.  The
  <emphasis>/WebDAV/HTTP Virtual Directories</emphasis> page lets you
  make a new URL Mappings.  The HTTP Virtual Directories page should contain a
  table with a row for {Default Web Site}.  Click on the
  <emphasis>Edit URL Mappings</emphasis> link for the {Default Web Site}
  line to begin defining a new SOAP mapping.</para>

      <figure float="1"><title>Virtual Directories</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir001.jpg" width="583px" depth="338px"/></figure>

  <para>You will be presented with a list of existing mappings.  Press the
  <emphasis>Add Virtual Directory</emphasis> button to create a new mapping.
  You will then be presented with a list of templates.  Select the SOAP
  template.</para>

      <figure float="1"><title>Virtual Directories Mappings</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir003.jpg" width="584px" depth="273px"/></figure>

  <para>You will then be presented with the main configuration page.  Particular
  options to note are Listener Details and SOAP Options.</para>

      <figure float="1"><title>Virtual Directories</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir004.jpg" width="598px" depth="727px"/></figure>

  <para><emphasis>Logical Path</emphasis> will be the path to which Virtuoso will respond
  for this virtual directory mapping.  This is what will be placed on the URL.
  <emphasis>Physical Path or URL</emphasis> is to which Virtuoso will map the logical path.
  In either case you can use the Browse buttons to traverse the file systems
  graphically.  Use the WebDAV Source Checkbox to instruct Virtuoso to use the
  WebDAV store for the physical location.</para>

  <para>In <emphasis>SOAP Options</emphasis> you can use the Publish button to select Virtuoso
  stored procedures, or remotely linked procedures to be published as SOAP
  web services.  Press this button to select the procedures previously linked.
  Click on the database where your procedure resides.  The next page will list the
  procedures in that database.  Select the procedures you want to link using
  the checkboxes on the left most column and finally click the Publish button
  to complete the task.  The SOAP Options text-area allows you to specify other
  SOAP options such as DIME encapsulations and WS-security settings.  These
  options are supplied as name=value pairs terminated with a semi-colon and a
  carriage-return.  Here is an example of the options used for the default Interop
  test based demo virtual directory:</para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
Namespace=http://soapinterop.org/;
MethodInSoapAction=no;
ServiceName=InteropTests;
HeaderNS=http://soapinterop.org/echoheader/;
CR-escape=yes;
]]></programlisting>

  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para>For a list of available SOAP Options review the end section of the SOAP
  chapter: <link linkend="soapoptions">Optional Parameters to the SOAP Endpoint</link>.</para></tip>

  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para><link linkend="httpvirtualdirs">Virtual Directories</link></para></tip>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="expspublishbtn"><title>Publishing Procedures to a Virtual Directory</title>
  <para>If you already have a virtual directory defined and know what procedures
  you want to expose as web services you will have to repeat some of the steps
  in the section above.  From the menu select <emphasis>/WebDAV/The HTTP
  Virtual Directories</emphasis>.  Click on the <emphasis>Edit URL mappings</emphasis>
  link for the site that you want to edit.  You will find the list of previously
  existing mappings, from which you can select the mapping that you want to edit
  by pressing on the <emphasis>edit</emphasis> link on the last column of the table.</para>

      <figure float="1"><title>Virtual Directories</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir006.jpg" width="544px" depth="395px"/></figure>

  <para>When the virtual directory configuration page is displayed scroll down
  to the SOAP Options section and use the Publish/UnPublish buttons to
  expose/hide your procedures and XML Templates as required.</para>

      <figure float="1"><title>Publish/UnPublish Buttons</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir008.jpg" width="278px" depth="62px"/></figure>

  <para>You will be presented with a screen for selecting the procedures or
  XML templates.  For selecting the procedures you first have to select the
  appropriate catalogue that contains the procedure that you want to publish.
  For the XML Templates you simply select the template using the checkbox and
  provide an <emphasis>Export As</emphasis> name to choose the new SOAP name
  that this XML template will be referred as.</para>

      <figure float="1"><title>Choosing Procedure and XML Templates to Publish</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/admvirtdir007.jpg" width="486px" depth="332px"/></figure>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="expsvsmxtest"><title>Testing SOAP Services Using VSMX</title>
  <para>Virtual directory definitions have a <emphasis>Logical Path</emphasis>
  field, which is reference in URL to find the correct SOAP services.  If you
  connect to Virtuoso on <emphasis>http://localhost:8890/</emphasis>, and
  defined your virtual directory with the logical path of <emphasis>/mysoap</emphasis>
  then you will be able to test the following URLs:</para>
    <simplelist>
      <member>http://localhost:8890/mysoap/services.wsdl</member>
      <member>http://localhost:8890/mysoap/services.vsmx</member>
    </simplelist>

  <para>The WSDL description is a standards-based description of the Web Services
  available from /mysoap.  The VSMX page is a Virtuoso generated test page
  allowing you to test SOAP services.  This feature should improve your
  development time.</para>

  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para><link linkend="vsmx">VSMX</link>;
    <link linkend="soap">SOAP</link>;
    <link linkend="wsdl">WSDL</link>.</para></tip>
  </sect3>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="xmlqtemplates"><title>XML Query Templates</title>
  <para>Virtuoso XML templates allow execution of SQL/XML queries over HTTP to
  obtain an XML document in response and/or perform some operation in the database
  using <link linkend="updategrams">updategrams</link>.  XML templates can be
  executed from within Virtuoso procedure language using the
  <link linkend="fn_xml_template"><function>xml_template()</function></link> function.
  XML templates support two types of action: SQL based or updategram based.
  SQL query based templates must contain the FOR XML clause used in a SELECT
  statement and hence cannot update the database.  Updates to the database
  can only occur from an updategram.  The XML document returned from calling
  an XML template can be served either raw, or transformed using XSLT.</para>

  <para>XML templates provide quick easy access to results from a SQL query
  as usual, but now this can be saved to a file.  The results are not saved, just
  the query definition.  You can use this feature to rapidly produce dynamic
  reports that can potentially be rendered in different ways by providing
  an alternate style sheet.  The report can be refined on the fly by providing
  parameters for the query.  The output is reachable via HTTP directly by
  providing the URL to the template.</para>

  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para>The <link linkend="xmltemplates">XML Templates</link> Section</para></tip>

  <para>XML Templates can also be published just like normal store procedures.
  This is achieved by using a PL wrapper around the XML template.  Then the
  store procedure is published in the normal way.</para>
  <para>Style sheets transformations with be inactive for published
  XML templates invoked from SOAP.</para>

  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para>The <link linkend="expspublishbtn">Publishing Stored Procedures</link>
  Section above for a further description of publishing XML Templates.</para></tip>

</sect2>

  <sect2 id="publishbifs"><title>Publishing VSEs as Web Services</title>
  <para>The Virtuoso distribution includes the sample VSE, bif_sample.c.
  It is thus possible to create a function such as:</para>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[
.....
static caddr_t
bif_hello_world (caddr_t * qst, caddr_t * err_ret, state_slot_t ** args)
{
  return box_dv_short_string ("Hello world.");
}
....
]]></programlisting>
  <para>Then declare it in the <function>init_func()</function> by adding the
  following code:</para>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
  bif_define_typed ("hello_world", bif_hello_world, &bt_any);
...
]]></programlisting>
  <para>The next step is creating a stored procedure that calls this function and
  you are back to publishing a Virtuoso stored procedure again, as in the above section.</para>

<programlisting>
create procedure BIF_HELLO_WORLD () { return hello_world (); };
</programlisting>

  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para>The <link linkend="cinterface">Virtuoso Server Extension Interface (VSEI)</link> Chapter</para></tip>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
