<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2014 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<chapter label="hooks.xml" id="hooks">
<title>Database Event Hooks</title>

  <abstract>
    <para>Virtuoso provides a number of hooks that enable you to traps events
    within the database such as startup, shutdown, connection, disconnection and
    SQL compilation events.</para>
  </abstract>

  <para>
Virtuoso allows the dba to set hooks for various events, such as:
</para>

<simplelist>
  <member>Startup</member>
  <member>Shutdown</member>
  <member>Client Connect</member>
  <member>Client Disconnect</member>
  <member>Compilation of a Dynamic SQL Statement</member>
</simplelist>

  <para>
These events are intercepted by calling a SQL procedure if one is defined.
</para>

  <para>
In the following we will examine each hook in the context of a simplified
database security system.  The system will record all logins
and logouts and will enforce custom security rules on reading a
specific application table.
</para>

<sect1 id="fn_dbev_startup"><title>Database Startup</title>

<para><function>DB.DBA.DBEV_STARTUP()</function></para>
  <para>
If defined, this is called after the server initialization, including
roll forward of transaction logs, compilation of stored procedures, etc...,
but before starting to listen for clients.  Hence this is guaranteed
to run before any clients connect or any HTTP messages are serviced.
</para>
  <para>
The procedure will run in its own transaction, which will be
automatically committed upon return, regardless of run time errors.
Result sets are not allowed and return values are discarded.
All custom Virtuoso Server Extensions (VSEs) will be defined when calling this procedure.
</para>

<example><title>Sample Startup Procedure Hook</title>
<programlisting>
create procedure DB.DBA.DBEV_STARTUP ()
{
  dbg_obj_print (' server started ');
}
</programlisting>
</example>

</sect1>
<sect1 id="fn_dbev_connect"><title>Database Connections</title>

<para><function>DB.DBA.DBEV_CONNECT()</function></para>
  <para>
If defined, this hook is called for each successful ODBC
or JDBC connection.  The hook is only called after password and
license checks have passed.  The hook is called before the server acknowledges a
successful connect and is therefore guaranteed to run before any other action
by the connected client.
</para>
  <para>
The function runs in its own transaction, which is automatically committed following
successful return.  Result sets may not be generated and return values are discarded.
The connection_id () and user are defined in the function.
SQL states signalled inside this hook will be sent to the client and will cause the
connection to be closed server side.
</para>

<example><title>Simple Connection Logging</title>
<programlisting>
create table security_log (
  sl_user varchar,
  sl_logged_in datetime,
  sl_logged_out datetime,
  primary key (sl_user, sl_logged_in)
);
</programlisting>
<programlisting>
create procedure DB.DBA.DBEV_CONNECT ()
{
  dbg_obj_print (user, ' connected');
  if (user = 'NOGO')
    signal ('EAUTH', '	External Authorization Failed');
  insert into security_log (sl_user, sl_logged_in) values (user, curdatetime ());
  connection_set ('login_time', curdatetime ());
}
</programlisting>

  <para>
This function will print a message to the server's standard output, check if
the username of the logged in user is NOGO and disconnect the user if so,
This will thereafter insert a row into the security_log table and set the
connection variable 'login_time' to be the current time.
This information will be used at disconnect time to identify which entry to
mark closed.
</para>
</example>

<para><function>DB.DBA.DBEV_DSN_LOGIN
  <paramdef>inout <parameter>dsn</parameter> varchar</paramdef>
  <paramdef>inout <parameter>user_id</parameter> varchar</paramdef>
  <paramdef>inout <parameter>pwd</parameter> varchar</paramdef>
  </function></para>

<para>If defined this function is executed just before Virtuoso makes connections
to remote data sources. It can change all of it's inout parameters depending on
it's logic.</para>

<example id="ex_dbev_dsn_login"><title>Remote Connection Hook</title>
<para>
This examples contains a sample DBEV_DSN_LOGIN hook that will be called
just before the Virtual Database connection to a datasource is made.  The
following parameters can be used in this function as demonstrated in this example:</para>
<simplelist>
  <member><emphasis>dsn</emphasis>: the dsn to connect to</member>
  <member><emphasis>user_id</emphasis>: the user id used in connecting to the DSN</member>
  <member><emphasis>pwd</emphasis>: the password used in connecting to the DSN</member>
</simplelist>
<programlisting>
create procedure "DB"."DBA"."DBEV_DSN_LOGIN"
(in dsn varchar,
 inout user_id varchar,
 inout pwd varchar)
{
  if (user_id = 'U1' and pwd = 'U1')
    {
      -- map U1 to U2
      dbg_obj_print ('mapping U1 to U2');
      user_id := 'U2';
      pwd := 'U2';
    }
   dbg_obj_print (dsn, user_id, pwd);
};
</programlisting>
</example>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="fn_logins"><title>Database Logins</title>
<para><function>DB.DBA.DBEV_LOGIN
    <paramdef>inout <parameter>user_name</parameter> varchar</paramdef>
    <paramdef>in <parameter>digest</parameter> varchar</paramdef>
    <paramdef>in <parameter>session_random</parameter> varchar</paramdef>
    </function></para>

<para>This function, if defined, will always be called by Virtuoso just before
a client is authenticated against the Virtuoso Server.  Three parameters
are available for audit purposes or any other pre-processing purpose totally
user definable.</para>

<simplelist>
  <member><emphasis>user_name:</emphasis>
    <simplelist>
    <member><emphasis>IN</emphasis> : the user name from the login data</member>
    <member><emphasis>OUT</emphasis> : the user name used by Virtuoso for this connection</member>
    </simplelist></member>
  <member><emphasis>digest</emphasis> : the password digest calculated by the client
  (or the password itself for older clients)</member>
  <member><emphasis>session_random</emphasis> : the random key used to
  calculate the digest</member>
</simplelist>

<para>This hook can be used to control how Virtuoso proceeds with the client login
by responding to 3 possible return values:</para>

<simplelist>
  <member>-1 - continue with normal verification</member>
  <member>0 - reject the login</member>
  <member>1 - allow the login (the user returned should be a valid Virtuoso local user name</member>
</simplelist>

<example id="ex_dbev_login"><title>Sample Database Login Hook</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure "DB"."DBA"."DBEV_LOGIN" (
    inout user_name varchar,
    in digest varchar,
    in session_random varchar)
{
  -- the hook runs as DBA
  dbg_obj_print ('user=', user);

  -- and is compiled as DBA
  declare uid_cnt integer;
  uid_cnt := 0;
  select count (*) into uid_cnt from SYS_USERS where U_NAME = user_name;
  dbg_printf ('%ld local users found with this name', uid_cnt);

  if (user_name = 'masterdba')
    {
      -- 'masterdba' is a valid remotely defined user
      -- it's password is 'masterdbapwd'
      -- we're going to check it's password and then map it to dba

      declare md5_ctx any;
      declare my_digest varchar;
      declare pwd varchar;

      -- this is our assumption for the user's password
      -- this can come from an external source as well
      pwd := 'masterdbapwd';

      -- calculate the MD5 digest for checking the password that the client supplied.
      -- note that it uses the 'masterdba'/'masterdbapwd' to calculate it since we
      -- assume that these are the data the client supplied as user id and password
      --
      -- The way to calculate this is FIXED.
      -- The ONLY variables are the user id and the password

      -- START of the FIXED digest calculation sequence
      md5_ctx := md5_init();
      md5_ctx := md5_update(md5_ctx, session_random);
      md5_ctx := md5_update(md5_ctx, user_name);
      md5_ctx := md5_update(md5_ctx, pwd);
      -- the 0 parameter to the md5_final causes it to return the bytes
      -- instead of representing it as hexadecimal characters
      my_digest := md5_final (md5_ctx, 0);
      -- END of the FIXED digest calculation sequence

      -- now compare the calculated digest with the one supplied by the client
      -- note the OR here - some older clients MAY supply the password in plain text
      if (my_digest = digest or pwd = digest)
        {
	  -- the match says that the client indeed supplied 'masterdbapwd' as a password
          dbg_obj_print ('masterdba validated');

	  -- so map it to the local 'dba' user
	  user_name := 'dba';

          -- and skip further verification
          return 1;
	}
      else
	{
	  -- the password is not the one that we verify against
          dbg_obj_print ('masterdba pwd wrong');

          -- not allow the login at all
	  return 0;
	}
    }
  else if (user_name = 'nobody')
    {
      -- the hook can signal :
      -- this is equal to returning -1, but has the additional benefit of an error message printed into the log
      signal ('28000', 'we don''t map nobody');
    }
  else if (user_name = 'attacker')
    {
      -- that's a way to print a message to the log and reject the login
      log_message ('trying invalid user');
      return 0;
    }
  else
    {
      -- all local user_name/pwd are subject to normal verification
      dbg_obj_print (user_name);
      return -1;
    }
  -- note that not returning value causes the Virtuoso to print an appropriate message to the log
  -- and then continue with the normal verification
  -- same happens if the value returned is not 0, -1 or 1
};
]]></programlisting>
</example>

<para><function>DB.DBA.USER_FIND
    <paramdef>in <parameter>name</parameter> varchar</paramdef>
    </function></para>

<para>This is a user-defined PL function hook which, if it exists, will be
executed before doing the SQL/ODBC login.  In this hook the user can find a
user account from some other server and register it in the local database.  Or,
this can be used to perform some pre-login actions.  It is similar to the
DBEV_LOGIN, but it does not change any account validation rule, it is
purely for pre-processing.</para>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="fn_disconnect"><title>Database Disconnections</title>
<para><function>DB.DBA.DBEV_DISCONNECT()</function></para>
  <para>
If defined, this procedure is called after a connection
has been found to be disconnected, either as a result of the client  process disconnecting,
the client process terminating or the server deciding
to disconnect, see <link linkend="fn_disconnect_user">disconnect_user()</link>.
This will also be called if the DBEV_CONNECT hook signals an error, leading to the connection being closed
during the connect sequence.
</para>
  <para>
All activity on behalf of the disconnecting client is terminated by the time this
function is called.  This function runs in its own transaction.
Result sets are prohibited, return values discarded and errors are
logged in the error log file but not otherwise processed.  The transaction is
committed regardless of errors.  The user and connection_id and any connection variables are defined
during this hook.
</para>

<example><title>Disconnect Interception</title>
<programlisting>
create procedure DB.DBA.DBEV_DISCONNECT ()
{
  declare ctime datetime;
  dbg_obj_print (user, ' disconnected');
  ctime := connection_get ('login_time');
  update security_log set sl_logged_out = now () where
    sl_user = user and sl_logged_in = ctime;
  if (row_count () = 0)
    signal ('ELOGO', 'Logout by user with no login record.  This occurs when DBEV_CONNECT denied permission');
}
</programlisting>
<para>
This function updates the row created by the connect hook to set the
logout time.
</para>
</example>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="fn_dbev_shutdown"><title>Database Shutdown</title>
<para><function>DB.DBA.DBEV_SHUTDOWN()</function></para>
  <para>
If defined, this function is called when shutting down the server,
following disconnection of all clients and making a checkpoint.  When
a disconnect occurs as a result of server shutdown the DBEV_DISCONNECT hook is not called
and this function is expected to perform any logout processing.
The rationale is that all disconnect hooks would be called at the same time,
creating likely deadlocks, resource contention and there could be no
guarantee of time consumed by them or of even whether
they would terminate at all.
</para>
  <para>
The shutdown will do a checkpoint before calling this hook.  This checkpoint
will terminate all transactions with a deadlock state.  If transactions
contain automatic retries, etc...,  we cannot guarantee that all activity would
have terminated when this hook starts.  However, the hook function can try
</para>

<programlisting>
txn_killall (6);
rollback work;
</programlisting>

  <para>
to signal an error on all other transactions to prompt them to
terminate.  Again, this is not a sure-fire termination since this
could be handled by procedures.
</para>
  <para>
When this hook returns the server commits the transaction
in which this was running and exits regardless of any lingering
activity.  There is no hard time limit for this function.
Killing the process during this function has no specific ill effect, besides losing
uncommitted work by said function.
</para>
  <para>
Result sets are prohibited, return values are discarded, errors are logged
but not otherwise processed.
</para>

<example><title>The Shutdown Hook</title>
<programlisting>
create procedure DB.DBA.DBEV_SHUTDOWN ()
{
  dbg_obj_print (' server shut down.');
  update security_log set sl_logged_out = now () where sl_logged_out is null;
}
</programlisting>
<para>
This just marks all open connections to be disconnected at the current time.
</para>
</example>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="fn_dbev_prepare"><title>SQL Statement Preparation</title>
  <para>
    <function>DB.DBA.DBEV_PREPARE(<parameter>inout tree any</parameter>)</function>
</para>
<programlisting>
DB.DBA.DBEV_PREPARE (inout tree any)
</programlisting>

  <para>
If defined, this function is called after parsing any dynamic SQL
statements by any users.  The parse tree will be a
syntactically correct SQL parse tree.  The user and connection variables are defined.
The hook should not produce a result set and any return values are discarded.
The function runs in the transaction which is current on the connection and
the transaction is not automatically committed, so that the hook does not
modify application transaction boundaries.
</para>
  <para>
The tree may be modified by replacing it with any other correct parse tree
or destructively splicing it.  The tree is a regular SQL heterogeneous array.
If the tree is modified incorrectly, it is probable that the server will crash.
</para>
  <para>
The parse tree manipulation is best written in C as a Virtuoso Server
Extension  using the supplied SQL parse tree typedef and constants.
</para>
  <para>
If an error occurs inside this hook the error is simply ignored and the unmodified parse tree is used.
To signal an error to a user it is possible to change the parse tree into a call to the signal SQL function.
</para>

<example><title>SQL Prepare Hook</title>
<programlisting>
CREATE TABLE REPORT (
  R_AUTHOR VARCHAR,
  R_ID INTEGER IDENTITY,
  R_CLASS INTEGER,
  R_TEXT LONG VARCHAR,
  PRIMARY KEY (R_ID)
);

CREATE TABLE NEED_TO_KNOW (
  NK_CLASS INTEGER,
  NK_USER INTEGER,
  PRIMARY KEY (NK_CLASS, NK_USER)
);

grant select on REPORT to public;

create procedure DB.DBA.DBEV_PREPARE (inout tree any)
{
  declare uid integer;
  uid := (select U_ID from SYS_USERS where U_NAME = user);
  need_to_know (uid, tree);
  dbg_obj_print ('compiled by ', user, ': ', tree);
}
</programlisting>
  <para>
This example has a table of variously secret reports,  each having a class or
compartment and different users having a need to know about a certain collection of compartments.
The need_to_know table references U_ID in SYS_USERS and R_CLASS in REPORT.  Each select referencing
REPORT is modified by the <function>need_to_know</function> VSE in order to add a check for the need to know.
</para>
  <para>
For example,
</para>
<programlisting>
select * from REPORT
</programlisting>
  <para>becomes</para>
<programlisting>
select * from REPORT
  where exists (select 1 from NEED_TO_KNOW
    where NK_CLASS = R_CLASS and NK_USER = &lt;user&gt;)
</programlisting>
  <para>
where &lt;user&gt; is the id of the user preparing the query.
</para>
  <para>
As a result, all queries referencing the REPORT table, no matter how they are phrased,
will not access rows for which the user does not have a need to know.
Note that the REPORT table can be granted to public, unauthorized users will just get an empty result.
Further, note that the NEED_TO_KNOW table is not granted to anyone, hence the user does
not even need to know the extent of his need to know let alone that of any other user.
The expansion of the need to know test inserts the table reference as in a view expansion,
where it's privileges are not those of the user but of the view owner, or in this case the
procedure owner, which is always dba.
</para>
</example>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="sqlparsetree"><title>SQL Parse Tree</title>
  <para>
The SQL parse tree is composed of DV_ARRAY_OF_POINTER boxes.  Other types of
boxes may occur as leaves, where they are interpreted as literals.  All nodes'
first element (index 0) is the type of the node, one of the constants in sqlparext.h.
</para>
  <para>
The nodes' various fields can be accessed through the data members of the
sql_tree_t union.  Most data members are pointers to the same type.  Sometimes they
are double pointers, denoting a variable length array of pointers to the struct.
The caddr_t type is used to denote a terminal, like a string or other constant.
The types are only for declarative value, the entire structure is a self describing,
run time typed tree of boxes.
</para>
  <para>
The correspondence of the tree to the SQL syntax is documented by the yacc grammar
supplied as appendix.
</para>

<para>
We will next examine the need to know example:
</para>

<programlisting>
ST *
nk_tree_and (ST* left, ST * right)
{
  if (left &amp;&amp; right)
    return ((ST*) list (4, BOP_AND, left, right, NULL));
  if (left)
    return left;
  return right;
}
</programlisting>

  <para>
This function adds anAND operation between 2 sub trees.  If either is NULL, the
non-null one is returned.  The list function is used as a universal constructor of
the parse tree, where the first argument is the count of arguments to follow.
</para>
  <para>
The above could have been written as follows without list:
</para>
<programlisting>
ST * r = (ST*) dk_alloc_box (4 * sizeof (caddr_t), DV_ARRAY_OF_POINTER);
r-&gt;type = BOP_AND;
r-&gt;_.bin_exp.left = left;
r-&gt;_.bin_exp.right = right;
r-&gt;_.bin_exp.more = NULL;
</programlisting>

<para>
We see that the list notation is more concise.
</para>

<programlisting>
void
nk_test_add (ST * outer_texp, char * corr_name, int uid)
{
  /* add a exists (select 1 from need_to_know where nk_class = &lt;corr_name&gt;.r_class) */
  ST * sel, * exists, * texp, **from;
  ST * where = (ST*) list (4, BOP_EQ, list (3, COL_DOTTED, NULL, box_string ("NK_CLASS")),
			   list (3, COL_DOTTED, box_string (corr_name), box_string ("R_CLASS")), NULL);
  where = nk_tree_and (where, listst (4, BOP_EQ, list (3, COL_DOTTED, NULL, box_string ("NK_USER")), box_num (uid), NULL));
  from = (ST**)
    list (1, list (3, TABLE_REF,
		   list (5, TABLE_DOTTED,
			 box_string ("DB.DBA.NEED_TO_KNOW"),
			 NULL, box_num (0), box_num (0)),
		   NULL));
  texp = listst (7, TABLE_EXP, from,
	       where, NULL, NULL, NULL, -1);
  sel = listst (5, SELECT_STMT, NULL, list (1, box_num (1)), NULL, texp);
  exists = (ST*) list (5, EXISTS_PRED, NULL, sel, NULL, NULL);
  outer_texp-&gt;_.table_exp.where = nk_tree_and (outer_texp-&gt;_.table_exp.where, exists);
}
</programlisting>

  <para>
This function takes the table expression referencing the REPORT table and the correlation
name used for the table and the user id of the querying user.  It adds the existence test for the
need to know.  The logic is self evident when examined in the context of the yacc grammar.
Note that the table in the FROM of the sub query is a TABLE_REF node with a TABLE_DOTTED
node, which finally contains the table and correlation names.  Note that all strings must
be allocated as string boxes.  This is because the tree may only reference other boxes.  Note
that all numbers except for the types of the nodes are boxed with box_num.  This will make
sure that numbers and pointers are always distinguishable.  The node types are distinguishable
by definition due to their small absolute value.
</para>

<programlisting>
caddr_t
bif_need_to_know (caddr_t * qst, caddr_t * err_ret, state_slot_t ** args)
{
  unsigned inx;
  caddr_t uid = (caddr_t) bif_long_arg (qst, args, 0, "need_to_know");
  ST * tree = (ST*) bif_array_arg (qst, args, 1, "need_to_know");
  if (ST_P (tree, SELECT_STMT))
    {
      ST * texp = tree-&gt;_.select_stmt.table_exp;
      if (!texp)
	return 0; /* select w/o a from */
      for (inx = 0; inx &lt; BOX_ELEMENTS (texp-&gt;_.table_exp.from); inx++)
	{
	  ST * tref = texp-&gt;_.table_exp.from[inx];
	  if (ST_P (tref, TABLE_REF))
	    tref = tref-&gt;_.table_ref.table;
	  if (ST_P (tref, TABLE_DOTTED))
	    {
	      char * corr_name;
	      if (tref-&gt;_.table.prefix)
		corr_name = tref-&gt;_.table.prefix;
	      else
		corr_name = tref-&gt;_.table.name;
	      if (strstr (tref-&gt;_.table.name, "REPORT"))
		nk_test_add (texp, corr_name, (int)uid);
	    }
	}
    }
  return 0;
}
</programlisting>
  <para>
This is the top level need to know function.  It first checks to see that the
statement is a select, that it has a FROM clause (table expression).
For each table in the FROM which has REPORT as part of its name the function adds an existence test
to check the user's need to know.  Note that the correlation name is taken from the
table and that the table name is used in the absence of a correlation name
to disambiguate the reference.  Note that the table_exp.from is of type
ST **, meaning a variable length array of boxes.  Note that BOX_ELEMENTS returns the length
in pointer-size units.
</para>
  <para>
Note that in this example the tree is spliced in place, only adding nodes.  There is
no need to free data or to modify the top node.
</para>

<sect2 id="notesonspecialparsetree"><title>Notes on Special Features of the Parse Tree</title>
  <para>
The parse tree structure has a 1 to 1 correspondence with the yacc grammar.  The members
of the union in sql_tree_t are mostly named after the syntactic element and the constant
that identifies them.  There are however some points worth noting:
</para>

<simplelist>
<member>Literals - All boxes whose tag is not DV_ARRAY_OF_POINTER are considered literals and
may appear in all places where a literal is allowed.</member>
<member>Identifier Case - The case conversion of identifiers is controlled by the CaseMode ini file setting.
When introducing a constant name referencing a VSE, one should use sqlp_box_id_upcase to get the right case for all modes.</member>
<member>The identifiers, once in the tree, are compared case sensitively in all modes case modes except 2.</member>
<member>Hook functions should use the appropriate comparison functions for the desired case sensitivity.</member>
<member>When generating references to names the case should be correct as defined by the case mode.</member>
</simplelist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="sqlsecandparsetrees"><title>SQL Security and Parse Trees</title>
  <para>
When compiling table access the access rights granted on the table are checked against
the user and group marked on the table reference (TABLE_DOTTED) parse tree node.  When
a user writes a table reference the user id and group of the user are marked in the
parse tree and these are compared against the grants in effect.
</para>
  <para>
When a table reference comes from a view the reference is annotated with the view owner's
user id and group.  Hence a view may introduce references that would not otherwise be granted to a user.
</para>
  <para>
This is used in the need to know example, marking the group and user of the reference to
NEED_TO_KNOW to be 0, meaning dba.
</para>
  <para>
There are no other security related features in the parse tree.  Procedure security is resolved
exclusively at run time.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="debuggingparsetree"><title>Debugging with Parse Trees</title>
  <para>
It is extremely easy to make errors when manipulating parse trees in code.
A useful technique will be to print out the tree before and after the operation.  This
can be conveniently done in the hook function with dbg_obj_print, as shown in the example.
</para>
  <para>
Once the modified tree is returned to the SQL compilation, the
system checks for it for absence of cycles, so that no two branches are the same.  There
is an assertion failure if this happens.  Otherwise the tree is not checked.  Hence a
malformed tree will in all likelihood crash the server during the compilation.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="fn_davlogins"><title>WebDAV Logins</title>
<para><function>DB.DBA.DBEV_DAV_LOGIN
    <paramdef>inout <parameter>user_name</parameter> varchar</paramdef>
    <paramdef>in <parameter>password</parameter> varchar</paramdef>
    <paramdef>in <parameter>http_auth</parameter> any</paramdef>
    </function></para>

<para>This function, if defined, will always be called by Virtuoso just before
a HTTP client is authenticated against the WebDAV Server.  Three parameters
are available for audit purposes or any other pre-processing purpose totally
user definable.</para>

<simplelist>
  <member><emphasis>user_name:</emphasis>
    <simplelist>
    <member><emphasis>IN</emphasis> : the user name from the login data</member>
    <member><emphasis>OUT</emphasis> : the user name used by WebDAV server for this request</member>
    </simplelist></member>
    <member><emphasis>password</emphasis> : the encrypted password that corresponding to the
	<parameter>user_name</parameter>
    </member>
  <member><emphasis>http_auth</emphasis> : HTTP authentication information (see below)</member>
</simplelist>

<para>
    The data structure of the <parameter>http_auth</parameter> is an array
    containing name/value pairs as described below.
</para>

<para>
    For HTTP Basic authentication:
</para>

<simplelist>
    <member>method - HTTP method : GET/POST/PUT etc.</member>
    <member>authtype - string 'Basic'</member>
    <member>username - the same as <parameter>user_name</parameter> parameter</member>
    <member>pass - the password (in case of basic authentication only)</member>
</simplelist>

<para>
    For HTTP Digest authentication:
</para>

<simplelist>
    <member>method - HTTP method : GET/POST/PUT etc.</member>
    <member>authtype - string 'Digest'</member>
    <member>username - the same as <parameter>user_name</parameter> parameter</member>
    <member>realm - authentication realm</member>
    <member>qop - Indicates what "quality of protection" the client has applied to the message</member>
    <member>algorithm - hashing algorithm used to create the checksum or digest</member>
    <member>uri - the URI from Request-URI of the Request-Line</member>
    <member>nonce - data string which may be uniquely generated</member>
    <member>nc - The nc-value is the hexadecimal count of the number of requests (including the current request)</member>
    <member>cnonce - The cnonce-value is an opaque quoted string value provided by the client</member>
    <member>opaque - string value provided by the server and returned by the client unchanged</member>
    <member>response - string containing password hash as described in RFC 2617</member>
</simplelist>

<para>An example of the <parameter>http_auth</parameter> value:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
    vector ('method', 'GET', 'authtype', 'basic', 'username', 'MyUser', 'pass', 'My!Secret')
    ]]>
</programlisting>

<para>This hook can be used to control how Virtuoso proceeds with the WebDAV client login
by responding to 3 possible return values:</para>

<simplelist>
  <member>-1 - continue with normal verification</member>
  <member>0 - reject the login</member>
  <member>1 - allow the login (the user returned should be a valid Virtuoso local user name)</member>
</simplelist>

<example id="ex_dbev_dav_login"><title>Sample WebDAV Login Hook</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure
DB.DBA.DBEV_DAV_LOGIN (inout user_name varchar, in pwd any, in auth any)
{
  declare result any;

  WHENEVER SQLSTATE '28000' GOTO validation_failure;

  -- All accounts that are not WebDAV admin are going here
  if (lcase(user_name) <> 'dav')
    {
      declare pass any;

      -- use password from request if basic HTTP authentication is used
      if (get_keyword ('authtype', auth) = 'basic')
        pass := get_keyword ('pass', auth);
      else -- or use the password from database if digest
        pass := pwd_magic_calc (user_name, pwd, 1);

      -- set appropriate LDAP protocol version
      connection_set ('LDAP_VERSION', 2);
      commit work;
      result := LDAP_SEARCH('ldap://mail2.openlinksw.com:389',
		0, 'ou=Accounts, o=OpenLink Software, c=US', sprintf ('(uid=%s)', user_name),
		sprintf('uid=%s, ou=Accounts, o=OpenLink Software, c=US', user_name),
                pass);
      return 1;
    }
  -- normal authentication for WebDAV admin
  return -1;

  -- all accounts that are not authenticated by LDAP are rejected
validation_failure:
  return 0;
};
]]></programlisting>
</example>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="assocauxdata"><title>Associating Auxiliary Data With A Connection</title>

<para>The following functions allow you to set and retrieve connection variables:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><link linkend="fn_connection_id">connection_id()</link></listitem>
  <listitem><link linkend="fn_connection_set">connection_set()</link></listitem>
  <listitem><link linkend="fn_connection_get">connection_get()</link></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>
</chapter>
