<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2012 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<sect1 id="migrxx">
	<title>Database Migration Guides</title>
	
<sect2 id="migrate27to30"><title>Migration of Virtuoso from Version 2.7 to Version 3.0</title>

  <para>The Virtuoso 3.0 database file format is not compatible with 
  database files of previous versions.  If you have previous versions of 
  Virtuoso installed you should perform &quot;data migration&quot;.  The 
  migration routine connects to both old and newly installed Virtuoso servers 
  to read all schema information, data, stored procedures and user 
  accounts from the old server and inserts them into a new one.</para>

  <para>Not all stored procedures will work after the migration exactly 
  as they were in the original installation.  Applications than are portable 
  across SQL-92 compatible servers are usually version-independent 
  because both Virtuoso 2.7 and Virtuoso 3.0 are SQL-92 compatible.  Other 
  applications may be sensitive to features that varied from version to version.  
  Typical compatibility issues are discussed below.</para>

  <sect3 id="migraroutine"><title>How Migration Processes Data</title>

    <para>The migration utility takes the form of a script on Unix platforms, 
    or a utility available via a short-cut from the Start/Programs menu on Windows. 
    The behavior is identical in both cases.  
    First of all, the utility asks for the location of two servers, source and
destination and ensures that it can establish database connections to them.
Then it checks the schema of the source database for critical errors, such as
invalid data types in index columns, and subsequently calculates checksums 
of the data within the source database for future integrity checking.  
Next it reads data from the source database tables and inserts them into
the destination database, creating the tables as necessary.  
When all of the data is copied, the triggers and foreign keys are then added 
to the schema of the destination server.  
Then stored procedures are compiled on the destination server.
At this point a checkpoint is made on the destination server, stabilizing server state.  
Next the migration utility calculates the checksums of the migrated data in the
destination database to compare with the source database, after verifying that 
they are identical the free-text indexes are filled and the checksums are 
calculated and compared once again.
The final action is the shutdown of the destination server.</para>
    <para>The utility will report all errors that may affect the result of the migration.
When the migration is complete, please review the log.</para>
    <para>The source and destination servers may reside on the same machine or on 
two different machines; the migration utility can be started on the machine where
one of databases resides or on a third machine. Migration works faster 
started on the same server as one or other database.  If the source and 
destination servers are on two different machines, migration works slightly 
faster if the utility is on the source side.</para>
  </sect3>
  <sect3 id="migracompat">
    <title>Typical Compatibility Issues</title>
    <formalpara>
      <title>User accounts get changed numeric IDs.</title>
      <para>While names of database users and their access rights are 
      identical in both databases, their numeric IDs may vary.
It will cause problems if an application refers to these numeric IDs in its own tables.  
Migration updates &quot;owner user&quot; and &quot;owner group&quot; IDs
for DAV resources and collections, but not in application-specific tables.
</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>A DAV user account can be renamed if there is in the source database a SQL account with the same name .</title>
      <para>The suffix "_dav" will be added to the name of such a user.  This is because DAV accounts had their own namespace in 2.7 but are part of the SQL user account namespace in 3.0.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>&quot;dav&quot; group is renamed to &quot;administrators&quot;.</title>
      <para>Some applications may be affected by this change.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>The row of a database table may store other amount of data than before</title>
      <para>If an application causes SQL errors like "data truncated", its behavior may vary from
version to version.
The database page layout for Virtuoso 3.0 has been significantly changed.  It is 
especially important for tables that have columns of both fixed and variable width 
and the total width of fixed-width columns is close to the maximum allowed 
length of the row.  In Virtuoso 3.0, the maximum allowed length of the row 
has been doubled so an application may get a surprisingly long data row that 
may have been truncated in the past.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Virtuoso 3.0 stores CHAR(n) columns differently</title>
      <para>In Virtuoso 2.7, columns of types CHAR(n) and VARCHAR(n) were 
      physically stored identically, as strings of variable (but limited) length.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Virtuoso 3.0 does not allow the use of LONG VARCHAR columns in comparison operators.</title>
      <para>It is illegal to use LONG VARCHAR values for comparison operations, 
so they may not appear in key columns of indexes.  However it has been 
to &quot;inline&quot; very short LOBs and write them into table 
rows as if they were short VARCHAR values.  Thus an application was able to 
work fine if comparison arguments are very short LOBs.  Virtuoso 3.0 
can &quot;inline&quot; LOBs too, but compile-time type checking is stricter 
than before so some procedures and SQL statements may fail to compile.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Virtuoso 3.0 does not allow the use of LONG VARCHAR columns as key columns of indexes.</title>
      <para>Building of an index assumes applying  comparison operators to  
      values from key columns.  As noted above, Virtuoso 3.0 contains more checks 
      against comparison of LOBs.
Virtuoso 3.0 detects more schema errors when the declaration of an index is created,
instead of signaling an error when a long value is added to the index.
Migration will  fail to create such indexes and will  create a table with no primary key
if LOB column is listed as a part of primary key of the table.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Error recovery is improved in the XML parser of the Virtuoso 3.0</title>
      <para>If an application parses invalid XML or HTML texts, the parser may recover
from parsing errors in a different way. It may affect free-text indexing of columns that
contain invalid XMLs so the content of the free-text index may differ from version
to version.</para>
    </formalpara>
  </sect3>
  <sect3 id="migraprepare">
    <title>Preparing to Migrate</title>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Install the Virtuoso 3.0 server</title>
      <para>Please make sure that the disk space is sufficient  to store data from the source database
plus the transaction log.
The migrated database may be greater or smaller than the
source one so providing at least 20% more space on the destination side is a good idea.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>It is especially important to have &quot;CaseMode&quot; and &quot;Collation&quot; parameters identical on both sides.</title>
      <para>Difference in &quot;CaseMode&quot; parameter may cause major schema errors and major problems in
migration of stored procedures.
Mismatch in &quot;Collation&quot; parameter may invalidate indexes.
Please double-check these parameters in configuration files.
If they were changed, please re-create the destination database.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Some other parameters should be the same too.</title>
      <para>Many applications will depend on &quot;NullUnspecifiedParams&quot;, &quot;AllowOSCalls&quot;,
&quot;DirsAllowed&quot; and &quot;DirsDenied&quot; parameters.
In addition, free text indexes may use &quot;noise.txt&quot; file and files listed in &quot;[Ucms]&quot;
section of the configuration file.  
Please keep them synchronized and restart the destination server after changing them.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>You should check port numbers, host names and database server names.</title>
      <para>If both databases should work on the same machine, their port numbers should not conflict.
E.g. If virtual hosts are defined, it is probable that the destination server will fail to listen on their
ports after the migration because they are already be used by the source server 
on the same machine.  Note that the destination server will fail to listen for multiple 
web hosts if the listening addresses specify specific interfaces which do not exist or 
are occupied on the machine in question.  </para>
</formalpara>

<formalpara><title>Replication server name conflicts</title>
<para>You may need to set a temporary unique replication server name for  the 
destination server, and set it to the name of the source server when the 
migration is complete and the source server has been turned off.
These problems are very common for any changes of the location of the database.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Check memory consumption.</title>
      <para>If you use a configuration file of source server as a template for 
      new server, please check if it matches the amount of available RAM on the  
      destination machine.  Note that the sizes of cache pools are measured in 
      database disk pages; one page was 4096 bytes in Virtuoso 2.7 but has been 
      increased to 8192 bytes in Virtuoso 3.0 hence the same number of pages in 
      the pool doubles the required amount of RAM.  If both source and destination 
      servers are started on the same machine, please ensure that there is 
      enough available memory to run them simultaneously without heavy 
      swapping.</para>
    </formalpara>
    <formalpara>
      <title>Check system clock accuracy and timezone settings.</title>
      <para>If source and destination servers are located in different timezones (i.e.,
their machines have different timezone settings),
then errors may occur in some applications that uses datetime values with default timezones,
because the timezone of datetime values will differ from the default (local) timezone.
The time reported by the system clock may also be important if an application
logs times of some events and expect that they are properly ordered.
Time issues may be especially important to web applications that uses cookie variables, because
cookies are time-sensitive.</para>
    </formalpara>
  </sect3>
  <sect3 id="migrarun"><title>Performing the migration on Unix using migration shell script</title>
    <para>The script expects that both source and destination servers are already started.
It ensures that all required programs are available and then asks connection parameters of
two servers (host names, ports, database user names and passwords).
To make the migration successful, database users should have granted all privileges on their servers,
so the use of DBA account is the best choice.
The script will test connections to both source and destination database to check the 
given parameters are valid.</para>
<para>If the source database resides on the machine where the migration script is started,
the script may ask whether you want to use a special temporary server instance to perform the migration.
It will shutdown your source server but will eliminate the risk of changing the data by third parties
during the migration.
If you want to use such a server, the effective OS user should have write permissions on
directories and files of the source database, otherwise the processing will fail.</para>
<para>If the original server is left running, please make sure that nobody else uses it
and there are no scheduled tasks (e.g., replication tasks) that may change data in the database.
</para>
<para>
In case of serious schema errors in the source database, the script may list them for review and
ask if you agree to run a &quot;dirty migration&quot;. The result of such migration will
contain the same data rows but the schema will be altered to eliminate the reported errors.  
One such example is when you have a table with LONG VARCHAR primary key, the resultant 
table will have all the fields copied, but the primary key will not be copied.
</para>
<para>
To ensure that data are copied correctly, the script will calculate MD5 signatures of
all columns of all migrated tables. The differences of two such signatures will indicate
that data in some column were changed during the migration.
Possible reasons are data truncation, typecasting of invalid values to the declared type of the column,
difference in character sets or collations, transaction performed by other connections on source or
destination servers during the migration.
</para>
  </sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>



