<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2006 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<chapter id="overview" label="overview.xml">
  <title>Overview</title>
  <abstract>
    <para>A quick overview on Virtuoso providing answers to simple questions that may
    already be in mind.</para>
  </abstract>
<!-- ======================================== -->
  <sect1 id="WhatIsVirtuoso">
    <title>What is Virtuoso?</title>
    <para>OpenLink Virtuoso is the first CROSS PLATFORM Universal Server to
		implement Web, File, and Database server functionality alongside Native XML
		Storage, and Universal Data Access Middleware, as a single server solution.
		It includes support for key Internet, Web, and Data Access standards such
		as: XML, XPATH, XSLT, SOAP, WSDL, UDDI, WebDAV, SMTP, SQL-92, ODBC, JDBC,
		and OLE-DB. Virtuoso currently supports the following Operating systems -
		Windows 95/98/NT/2000, Linux (Intel, Alpha, Mips, PPC), Solaris, AIX, HP-UX,
		Unixware, IRIX, Digital UNIX, DYNIX/PTX, FreeBSD, SCO, MacOS X.</para>
    <para>Virtuoso is a revolutionary, next generation, high-performance virtual database engine
    for the Distributed Computing Age. It is a core universal data access technology set to
    accelerate our advances into the emerging Information Age.</para>
    <para>Virtuoso provides transparent access to your existing data sources, which are typically
    databases from different database vendors.</para>
    <para>Through a single connection, Virtuoso will simultaneously connect your ODBC, JDBC,
    UDBC, OLE-DB client applications and services to data within Oracle, Microsoft SQL Server,
    DB/2, Informix, Progress, CA-Ingres and other ODBC compliant database engines. All your
    databases are treated as single logical unit.</para>
    <para>The diagram below depicts how applications that are built in conformance with industry
    standards (such as ODBC, JDBC, UDBC, and OLE-DB) only need to make a single connection via
    Virtuoso&apos;s Virtual Database Engine and end up with concurrent and real-time access to data
    within different database types.</para>
		<para>Further still, Virtuoso exposes all of its functionality to Web Services.
		This means that your existing infrastructure can be used support Web Services
		directly without any hint of replacement.
		</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="virtwhydoi">
    <title>Why Do I Need Virtuoso?</title>
    <para>You need Virtuoso because Knowledge is power or competitive advantage (depending on how
    you choose to exploit it). All Knowledge comes from Information. Information is produced
    from Data. </para>
    <para>The Internet is reducing the cost of accessing Information, thereby increasing the
    appetite and rates at which Information is produced and consumed. Unfortunately data
    required for the production of Information simply does not reside within one database
    engine within your organization. </para>
    <para>Whether you know it or not it is highly probable that the quest for critical
    information within your organization actually requires traversing several data sources
    served by numerous database engines from different database vendors.</para>
    <para>Virtuoso simply reduces the cost of bringing together data from different data sources
    with the view to accelerating the production of information by your Query Tools, Web &amp;
    Internet Application Development Environments, Traditional Application Development Tools,
    and Desktop Productivity Tools.</para>
    <para>Virtuoso enables you to compete effectively in the Information Age.</para>

	  <para>One of the biggest challenges facing the uptake of XML is the
		availability of key XML Data itself. Virtuoso simplifies the process of
		creating XML data from existing HTML, syndicated XML, and SQL databases.
		Virtuoso enables real-time creation of Dynamic XML documents (DTD or
		XML Schema based) from homogeneous or heterogeneous SQL Databases "on the fly".</para>
		<para>By implementing a number of protocols in a single server solution,
		Virtuoso provides you with a unifying foundation upon which next generation
		eBusiness solutions can be developed and deployed. Virtuoso reduces the cost
		of bringing together data from different data sources and leverages this
		into increased effectiveness of your Query Tools, Web &amp; Internet Application
		Development Environments, Traditional Application Development Tools, and
		Desktop Productivity Tools. Virtuoso enables you compete effectively in the
		Information Age.</para>
		<para>OpenLink Software is an acclaimed technology innovator and leading
		vendor of High-Performance &amp; CROSS PLATFORM eBuisiness solutions that
		adhere to a broad range of industry standards that include: ODBC, JDBC,
		OLE DB, SQL, WebDAV, HTTP, XML, SOAP, UDDI, WSDL, SMTP, NNTP, POP3, LDAP
		amongst others.</para>
		<para>Our product &amp; services portfolio includes a suite of
		High-Performance Universal Data Access Drivers for ODBC, OLE DB and JDBC,
		Internet Data Integration Servers, Virtual and Federated Database Engines,
		Embeddable SQL-Database Engines, Application Servers, Enterprise Portal
		Servers and professional services expertise capable of handling the most
		demanding eBusiness application development, deployment, and integration
		challenges.</para>

  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="whatisnewto2x">
    <title>Key Features of Virtuoso</title>

<figure id="varch32" float="1"><title>OpenLink Virtuoso Product Architecture</title>
  <graphic fileref="varch32.jpg" width="384px" depth="377px"/></figure>

		<sect2 id="oxmldocstore"><title>XML Document Storage &amp; Creation</title>
  	<para>Virtuoso enables you to develop eBusiness solutions that use <emphasis>XML</emphasis>
		as a common data access foundation layer that provides transparent access
		to structured and unstructured data. XML Data documents can be created
		internally, or imported from around the Web and then stored in Virtuoso.
		You can also create dynamic XML documents by transforming SQL to XML
		on the fly, leveraging data that resides within homogeneous and/or
		heterogeneous database(s). <emphasis>XPATH 2.0</emphasis> query language support enables you to
		query entire XML Documents using and industry standard query language.
		The Virtuoso Server provides some basic support for the
		<link linkend="xq"><emphasis>XQuery 1.0</emphasis> XML Query Language</link>
		specification.
		There is <emphasis>XML Schema</emphasis> support for extending Virtuoso Data
		types used by SOAP Services.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="ointernetsrv"><title>Web Page Hosting</title>
		<para>Virtuoso has an integrated HTTP web server, for static HTML pages, or
		dynamic content using <link linkend="vsp1">Virtuoso Server Pages
		(<emphasis>VSP</emphasis>)</link>.
		Hosting and execution of <emphasis>PHP4</emphasis> scripts is supported
		via Virtuoso Server Extensions Interface (VSEI) for Zend.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="owebsrvhost"><title>Web Services Creation &amp; Hosting</title>
		<para>Enables the creation of <emphasis>SOAP</emphasis> compliant Web Services from SQL Stored
		Procedures, these procedures may be native to Virtuoso or resident in
		third party databases that support ODBC or JDBC. Virtuoso automatically
		generates <emphasis>WSDL</emphasis> files for the Stored Procedures that it exposes as Web
		Services. As a <emphasis>UDDI</emphasis> server (registry) all of your Web Services can be
		stored for access across the internet or within an intranet. It can also
		synchronize data with other UDDI servers.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="owebdavstore"><title>WebDAV Compliant Web Store</title>
		<para><emphasis>WebDAV</emphasis> support enables Virtuoso to act as the Web Content Store for
		all of your eBusiness data, this includes Text, Graphics and Multimedia
		files. WebDAV support also enables Virtuoso to play the familiar roles of
		a FILE &amp; WEB SERVER, hosting entire Web sites within a single database
		file, or across multiple database files.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="oreplandsync"><title>Content Replication &amp; Synchronization</title>
		<para>Virtuoso's sophisticated data replication and synchronization engine
		enables the automated distribution and updating of SQL and Web Content
		across distributed Virtuoso servers.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="ophetdata"><title>Transparent Access To Heterogeneous Data</title>
		<para>Virtuoso's Virtual Database Engine enables you to produce Dynamic Web
		Content from any major database management system. This enables dynamic,
		real-time HTML and XML generation from any number of different database
		engines concurrently.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="omaildelresrv"><title>Mail Delivery &amp; Retrieval Services</title>
		<para>Virtuoso can act as an <emphasis>SMTP</emphasis>, <emphasis>POP3</emphasis>, and <emphasis>IMAP4</emphasis> proxy to any email
		client. This enables the development and deployment of sophisticated
		database driven email solutions.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="onntp"><title>NNTP Aggregation &amp; Serving</title>
		<para>Virtuoso supports the Network News Transfer Protocol used by Internet
		newsgroup forums. <emphasis>NNTP</emphasis> servers manage the global network of collected
		newsgroup postings and represent a vast repository of targeted information
		archives. As an NNTP aggregator, Virtuoso enables integration of multiple
		news forums around the world. All news content in Virtuoso is dynamically
		indexed to provide keyword searches, enabling rapid transformation of
		disparate text data into information. Virtuoso also acts as an NNTP server,
		enabling creation of new Internet and Intranet News Forums to leverage the
		global knowledgebase into eBusiness Intelligence.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
