<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2012 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<sect3 id="rendezvous"><title>ZeroConfig ("Zero Configuration") Support</title>

<para>The "ZeroConfig" protocol, also known as "Zeroconf" or 
"Zero Configuration" is a protocol that allows discovery of services on the 
network that are advertised by their hosts.  It also has provisions for 
automatic discovery of computers and various devices.  
The main benefit of ZeroConfig is that it does not require DHCP, DNS or 
directory servers.</para>
<para>ZeroConfig is an open protocol that Apple submitted to the IETF for 
a standard-creation process.</para>
<para>The Virtuoso server and ODBC driver use the capabilities of ZeroConfig to
facilitate DSN (Data Source Name) setup and usage.  This is divided in  two parts:  
Server-side and Client-side.</para>

<para>The Virtuoso server (Server-side) is configured via the Virtuoso INI 
file to advertise its availability on a network with a given name.  This allows 
applications, and in particular the Virtuoso ODBC driver, to receive information 
about a server, such as its network address, default login, etc, and use it 
for configuring a data source or directory making a connection.</para>
  
<para>The Virtuoso ODBC driver (Client side) uses ZeroConfig to locate 
the desired Virtuoso server during the set-up phase of a data source, and 
determine available connection options such as:</para>

 <simplelist>
  <member>secure connection options</member>
  <member>default database</member>
  <member>default user </member>
  <member>default password (if public/demo login is required)</member>
  <member>default character set </member>
 </simplelist>

<para>ZeroConfig provides the client with a service name, which must be bound to 
the IP address/port of a host of the chosen service during DSN configuration.  
This is used when existing DSN using a ZeroConfig name is used to connect,
it will map name with IP address and port before making a connection.</para>

 <sect4 id="rendezvousserverside"><title>Setting-up the Server for Service Advertising</title>

  <para>The Virtuoso server is configured to advertise itself based on the 
  details specified in the <computeroutput>[Zero Config]</computeroutput> 
  section of the Virtuoso INI file.  Below is an example of such:</para>

  <programlisting><![CDATA[
...
[Zero Config]
ServerName    = Virtuoso Server
ServerDSN     = UID=demo;PWD=
SSLServerName = Virtuoso Server (via SSL)
SSLServerDSN  = UID=dba;PWD=;ENCRYPT=1
...
]]></programlisting>

  <para>The ServerName and SSLServerName are human readable 
  strings chosen by the administrator to provide clients with a suitable 
  description of the service being provided.</para>
  
  <note><title>Note:</title>
  <para>If the Virtuoso does not have the SSL listener enabled then the 
  SSL service will not be advertised automatically.
  The SSL* keys will simply be ignored and do not need to be removed.
  </para></note>

  <para>The ServerDSN and SSLServerDSN are default connection 
  strings that can be used by clients to make the advertised connection.  You only 
  need to to specify default username and password in these strings.  The 
  default database can be specified or left to the setting for the username.  
  You cannot specify the server hostname, IP address or port number, these 
  are supplied by Virtuoso automatically.</para>

  <para>ZeroConfig service advertising is multicast, hence it is advertised 
  on all available network interfaces.</para>

  </sect4>

  <sect4 id="rendezvous"><title>Using the Windows ODBC Driver with ZeroConfig</title>

  <para>Upon DSN set-up the ODBC driver listens for advertising servers, and 
  compiles a roster.  This is displayed for the user to choose the desired 
  service to connect to.  </para>
  <para>If ZeroConfig is used to for data source set-up then the 
  set-up dialog will be initialized based on the details in the connection 
  string configured on the server.</para>
 
  <para>When a DSN is configured based on a ZeroConfig service, the driver will 
  resolve the service name before making the connection to the server.  The driver 
  does not store the network address or port number of the Virtuoso server, only 
  the ZeroConfig server name, so if the server's physical address is changed 
  the client DSNs associated with it do not all have to reconfigured; they will 
  resolve to the new address automatically on next use.</para>

  </sect4>
  </sect3>
  
  

