<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2014 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->

  <sect1 id="rthwritaspxapps"><title>Deploying ASP.Net Web Applications</title>

 <para>Virtuoso is a CLR host.  It is responsible for initializing the runtime,
 defining the application domain (its runtime boundaries, security settings, etc),
 and executing user code within such domains.  Windows can be used
 as the development platform, a very developer friendly environment with
 a rich set of tools, but you  will not be restricted to Windows, .NET
 and IIS to run the assemblies produced.  Where .NET is not readily available
 or desired Virtuoso contains Mono, an open source re-implementation of
 Microsoft .NET, a vehicle taking .NET cross-platform.  </para>

 <para>The CLR run-time is a part of the Virtuoso process.  The Mono run time may be
run either as in-process or as out-of-process.  Hosted applications can make use of
the regular Virtuoso .Net data provider to access Virtuoso SQL data and procedures.
 Microsoft ASPX files can also be run directly from Virtuoso either from
 the file system or WebDAV.  Each of these capabilities releases you from
 the Microsoft platforms without compromising your development platform.</para>

 <para>The Virtuoso CLR hosting is implemented using the VSEI.</para>


<figure id="http_handler_aspx" float="1"><title>The HTTP ASP.Net handler</title>
  <graphic fileref="http_handler_aspx.jpg" format="jpeg"></graphic></figure>

<tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para><link linkend="rthclrenvsetdotnet">CLR Host Environment Setup</link></para>
  <para><link linkend="cinterface">VSEI</link></para>
  <para><link linkend="inprocess">In-Process Data Access Client</link></para></tip>

   <sect2 id="rthprogramming"><title>Programming Concepts</title>

   <para>ASP.Net Web Forms are divided into two sections: the user interface
   and the application logic.  The user interface comprises HTML markup and
   ASP.Net web controls whereas the application logic contains all the
   programming code that allows the controls to interact with themselves and
   the server back-end.  This provides the level of abstractions required
   for dynamic efficient Web application design.  The interface can be altered
   without any backward or forward dependence on the code (logic).
   The Web Form interface should be created with the .aspx extension.  The
   application logic can be contained in-line within the ASPX application, but
   developers should strive to keep the code in a separate location known as
   the "CodeBehind".  This is a file that contains the logic (code) for the Web
   Form which should end in an extension appropriate for the programming
   language used, such as .vb for Visual Basic or .cs for C#.  The
   CodeBehind can be written in any language for which there is a .Net
   compiler for.  The compiler generates bytecode that can be deployed
   anywhere the .Net runtime exists.</para>

   <para>The ASPX Web Form is compiled into an object that takes its place on a
   tree of controls and classes.  The CodeBehind is compiled into an object on
   this tree when the page is requested.  The Web Form must inherit from a
   "base-class" defined in the CodeBehind class file.</para>

  <figure id="rthwriteaspx001" float="0"><title>ASPX Web Form class hierarchy</title>
    <graphic fileref="rth/writeaspx001.jpg" /></figure>

    <para>Now we will create a new Web Form containing an HTML
    heading and an ASP.Net DataGrid control that will display results from
    the local Virtuoso server.  </para>

<example id="ex_VirtTest.aspx"><title>Sample .Net Web Application: VirtTest.aspx</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
<%@ Page Language="vb" Inherits="VirtTest" Src="VirtTest.aspx.vb" %>
<!DOCTYPE HTML PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD HTML 4.0 Transitional//EN">
<html>
	<head>
		<title>Virtuoso Provider to DataGrid in VB</title>
	</head>
	<body>
	<h1>Simple VB Virtuoso DataBinding Demo</h1>
		<form id="Form1" method="post" runat="server">
			<asp:DataGrid id=DataGrid1 runat="server" DataMember="Customers"
				BorderColor="silver"
				BorderWidth="1"
				CellPadding="2"
				Font-Name="Tahoma"
				Font-Size="10pt">
			  <HeaderStyle BackColor="#2222ff" ForeColor="yellow"/>
			  <PagerStyle Mode="NextPrev" />
			</asp:DataGrid>
		</form>
	<hr>
	</body>
</html>
]]></programlisting>
</example>

<para>On the first line of the file we use the
<computeroutput>@ page</computeroutput> directive to inherit the
CodeBehind class we will create in the CodeBehind file.  The source of which can be
optionally declared here with the <computeroutput>Src=</computeroutput>
attribute.  Visual Studio makes use of
<computeroutput>CodeBehind=</computeroutput> for tracking associated
source code instead.  If either of these two attributes are specified then
the .Net runtime will attempt to compile the code into an assembly
(DLL) upon first execution if it does not already exist or seems out-of-date.
The following code fragment is the CodeBehind, VirtTest.aspx.vb.</para>

<para>Now we want some logic behind the Web Form.  We have placed a
DataGrid control on a web page but we need to supply data to it now:</para>

<example id="ex_VirtTest.aspx.vb"><title>Sample .Net Web Application CodeBehind: VirtTest.aspx.vb</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
imports System
imports System.Web
imports System.Web.UI
imports System.Web.UI.WebControls
imports System.Web.UI.HtmlControls
imports System.Data

imports OpenLink.Data.VirtuosoClient

Public Class VirtTest
    Inherits Page

    Protected WithEvents myConnection As OpenLink.Data.VirtuosoClient.VirtuosoConnection
    Protected WithEvents myCommand As OpenLink.Data.VirtuosoClient.VirtuosoDataAdapter
    Protected WithEvents DataGrid1 As System.Web.UI.WebControls.DataGrid
    Protected WithEvents ds As System.Data.DataSet

    Private Sub Page_Load(sender As Object, e As EventArgs) Handles MyBase.Load
        Dim myConnection As new VirtuosoConnection("HOST=noodle:1112;UID=dba;PWD=dba;Database=Demo")
        Dim myCommand As new VirtuosoDataAdapter("select * from Demo..Customers", myConnection)

	    Dim ds As new DataSet()
        myCommand.Fill(ds, "Customers")

        DataGrid1.DataSource=ds.Tables("Customers")
        DataGrid1.DataBind()

    End Sub

End Class
]]></programlisting>
</example>

<para>This file is compiled using the following command (split across
lines for readability and would otherwise all be on one line):</para>

<programlisting>
E:\myweb\myapp>
  vbc /target:library
    /r:System.dll
    /r: System.Web.dll
    /r:System.Data.dll
    /r:OpenLink.Data.VirtuosoClient.dll
    /r:System.Xml.dll
    /out:bin\VirtTest.dll
    VirtTest.aspx.vb
</programlisting>

<para>Once compiled, the resulting DLL library should be in the bin subdirectory
of the application root.  When the assembly is available in this way the .aspx
file does not need to contain the <computeroutput>Src=</computeroutput>
attribute since there will be no need to compile the CodeBehind.  If the
<computeroutput>Src=</computeroutput> attribute is specified in the .aspx file
but the CodeBehind file is not located on the server then an error will be signalled
indicating that a required resource cannot be found, because the CodeBehind
class is compiled on demand.</para>
  </sect2>

   <sect2 id="rthasp.netdeploymentconf"><title>ASP.Net Deployment &amp; Configuration</title>

   <para>ASP.Net allows multiple Web applications to run on the same machine
   independently of each other.  Web applications have their own directory
   for components (the ".\bin" directory) and its own XML-based
   configuration file (the ".config" file).  This allows us to develop robust applications
   using custom configurations and components (or different versions of
   components) for each one.</para>

   <note><title>Note:</title>
   <para>The ASP.Net machine-wide configuration is held in
   machine.config found in the
   <computeroutput>(C:\Winnt\Microsoft.NET\)Framework\[version number]\CONFIG directory</computeroutput>
    depending on your installation.
   Applications hosting or making use of .Net may have an application
   configuration [App Name].config.  Web applications store
   their individual configurations in Web.config stored in the Web
   application root directory.</para>
   </note>

   <para>Each ASP.Net application uses a local assembly cache to hold application
   specific logic (assemblies, contained in compiled DLLs).  The \bin directory located
   in the application root is the local assembly cache for Web applications.
   This directory is denied access directly from browsers.  This prevents users from
   downloading or executing any DLLs contained within.</para>

   <para>When a Web application is started the .Net Framework constructs a
   new instance of the <computeroutput>System.AppDomain</computeroutput>
   class.  When the instance is constructed it creates in-memory shadow copies
   of the DLLs in the \bin directory.  The .Net Framework keeps an in-memory
   cache (shadow) of all assemblies used so that the actual files (.DLLs)
   are not locked.  The .Net Framework will monitor the original DLL for
   changes.  When changes occur the in-memory cache is updated.
   Applications already loaded and running with calls in-progress
   to the old library will continue using the old version so there is no
   interruption.  All new calls to library will be effected, and use the
   new library.  This means that you are free to replace the DLL with
   new versions as required.  Previously with ASP you were required to
   stop IIS, register the DLL with RegServ32.exe and restart the Web server.  </para>

   <para>When new libraries are added to the .Net Framework for use in any
   application system wide, such as the Virtuoso Data Provider, these need
   to be added to the Global Assembly Cache (GAC).  This is achieved using the
   <computeroutput>gacutil.exe</computeroutput> utility found in the
   <computeroutput>Framework\[version number]</computeroutput>
   directory.  The <computeroutput>gacutil.exe</computeroutput> tool
   registers the DLL along with its version.  One of .Net's strengths is its
   ability to maintain multiple versions of DLLs for multiple applications.
   This prevents "DLL-hell"; new DLLs breaking old applications.
   Applications can also maintain their own local versions of
   DLLs in their \bin directory.</para>

   <programlisting>gacutil.exe /i &lt;full path and file name&gt;.dll</programlisting>

   <para>Registers assemblies with the Global Assembly Cache.</para>

   <programlisting>gacutil.exe /l</programlisting>

   <para>Can be used to list registered assemblies.</para>

   <para>After registering assemblies using the
   <computeroutput>gacutil.exe</computeroutput> tool you must add an
   <computeroutput>&lt;add assembly="..." /&gt;</computeroutput> entry
   into the <computeroutput>&lt;configuration&gt;&lt;system.web&gt;&lt;compilation&gt;&lt;assemblies&gt; </computeroutput>
   section of the machine.config.</para>

<para>The application given in the previous section can be deployed to Virtuoso
in the WebDAV repository or directly on file system under the VSPRoot directory.
You should copy the directory structure as defined, applications in the root of the
new directory and DLLs in a bin subdirectory.  A virtual directory must be configured
with execute permissions enabled.  The application can be tested with a Web browser.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="rthaspvsmono"><title>The Mono Project</title>

    <para>The Mono Project is an open source version of the Microsoft.NET
    development platform.  Incorporating key .NET compliant components, including
    a C# compiler, a Common Language Runtime just-in-time compiler, and a
    full suite of class libraries, the Mono Project will enable developers to
    create .NET applications and run them on Windows or any Mono-supported
    platform.  Besides greatly improving the efficiency of development in the open
    source world, the Mono Project will allow the creation of
    operating-system-independent programs.  Although primarily developed on
    Linux, Mono is being ported to as many operating systems as possible.</para>

    <para>Microsoft.NET development tools, which include the C# compiler and
    Common Language Infrastructure (CLI), let programs written in C# and other
    languages run on non-Windows operating systems.   The Mono Project
    development platform provides open source developers with a true
    "build once, deploy anywhere" tool-set taking advantage
    of the myriad of services enabled by Microsoft.NET.</para>

    <para>The Mono Project will provide three key elements in a development
    framework designed to allow developers to quickly create, deploy and run
    .NET compatible applications on non-Windows platform.  A C# compiler extending
    the GNOME development platform will allow Linux developers to create .NET
    compatible applications. These developers will also be able to build upon a
    complete implementation of class libraries compatible with the Microsoft CLI,
    enabling developers to create end-user applications as well as powerful web
    services using the database functionality available on open source systems.
    Portation of Mono yields versions of the Microsoft Common Language
    Run-Time (CLR)  just-in-time (JIT) run-time engine will allow non-Windows
    systems to run .NET applications built on Windows, Linux or UNIX platforms.</para>

    <para>The example
    in the previous section can be run using the CLR hosting ability of Virtuoso, but
    only with the precompiled assembly which has to be deployed into the Mono/lib
    directory of the Mono installation.</para>

    <para>The Virtuoso installer on non-Windows platforms for which there is a
    port of Mono available installs the latest Mono CLR.  This is required for the
    Virtuoso server to host .Net applications on non-Windows platforms.</para>

    <para>Only a compiler for C#.  Inline ASPX code using C# is a safe way to write and
    experience ASPX hosted from Virtuoso.  Although this goes completely against
    the programming practice guidelines for .Net</para>

    <para>The only permissible Application Domain is the Mono application.  ASP.Net
    applications should have their own self containable Application Domain - the
    ./bin directory.  Mono does not support this as of yet.  The work around is
    to place all assemblies into the Mono domain.</para>
    </sect2>

<sect2 id="rthaspxwalk">
 <title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>

 <sect3 id="rthaspxnew"><title>Creating a Simple Data Bound Application</title>
 <para>This section will describe how to use the MS Visual Studio to create an
 application using as much drag and drop as possible.  We want to
 create a table of data in a web page from a database.</para>

 <orderedlist>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Launch Microsoft's Visual Studio</title>
    <para>Once Visual Studio has been launch it present you with the start
    page that lets you create a New Project.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs001"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs001.jpg" width="600px" depth="400px"/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Create a new <menuchoice><guimenu>Empty Web Project</guimenu></menuchoice></title>
    <para>From the templates select a new Empty Web Project  found in the
    Visual Basic Projects type.  You must also select a location on an IIS web server.
    </para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs002"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs002.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

   <listitem><formalpara><title>Wait for IIS application to be set-up</title>
    <para>You will be shown a progress dialogue as Visual Studio
    contacts your web server creating a new web application there.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs003"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs003.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Add New Web Form</title>
    <para>When the application-space has been configured on the web server
    you will be returned to the main Visual Studio windows.  Now we must create our
    page.  Right-click on the project name in the Solution Explorer and
    select Add New Web Form. </para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs004"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs004.jpg" width="600px" depth="400px"/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>New Web Form</title>
    <para>The <menuchoice><guimenu>Add New Item</guimenu></menuchoice>
    option will appear, automatically selecting the "Web Form" item to add.  Supply
    a name for the page and click Open to begin.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs005"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs005.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Add a SqlDataAdapter Control</title>
    <para>With the fresh "Web Form" we can start.
    From the <menuchoice><guimenu>ToolBox </guimenu></menuchoice>
    double-click on the <menuchoice><guimenu>SqlDataAdapter</guimenu></menuchoice>
    in the <menuchoice><guimenu>Data</guimenu></menuchoice> panel.  This will
    start the <menuchoice><guimenu>Data Adapter Configuration Wizard</guimenu></menuchoice>.
    After reading the description on the first panel click on the Next button.
    You will be asked to choose your connection.  Assuming that you have access
    to a Northwind database hosted in MS SQLServer you can either make use
    of an existing connection to it or configure a new one using the
    <menuchoice><guibutton>New Connection</guibutton></menuchoice> button.
    Pressing the <menuchoice><guibutton>New Connection</guibutton></menuchoice>
    button will present the normal OLEDB dialogues for creating a new datasource.
    Once a data connection has been selected press Next to continue.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs006"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs006.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Choose a Query Type</title>
    <para>The next panel will ask how the data adapter should access the database.
For simplicity we will stick with the default of Use SQL Statements.  Press Next.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs007"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs007.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Generate SQL Statements</title>
    <para>At this point you can either type a SQL statement if you know exactly
    what you are looking to get back from the database, or you can use the
    <menuchoice><guibutton>Query Builder</guibutton></menuchoice> to
    point-and-click to your data.  In our case we will retrieve everything from
    the Customers table using a simple query:<computeroutput>select * from
    Customers</computeroutput>.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs008"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs008.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Advanced Options</title>
    <para>Click on the Advanced Options button.  Unselect the top checkbox.
    This will also unselect the other two automatically.  We will not be performing
    any updates in this example.  OK the advanced options, upon return to the
    main dialogue press the Next button to continue onwards. </para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs009"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs009.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>View Wizard Results</title>
    <para>The next panel confirms all the options selected leaving us to simply
    complete the wizard.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs010"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs010.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Back to the main window...</title>
    <para>When the wizard finishes and returns you to the main Visual Studio
    window you will see that two controls have been added to the Web Form.
    The connection control has been automatically generated to support
    the Data Adapter.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs011"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs011.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Generate Dataset</title>
    <para>Before we can display anything on the page we need to
    form a Dataset.  Right-click on the SQLDataAdapter1 control you previously
    added and select Generate Dataset.  Defaults on the displayed dialog are
    all sufficient.  After verifying them click the OK button
    to generate the dataset.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs015"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs015.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Add a DataGrid Control</title>
    <para>Now we need to show the dataset that we are fetching from the
    database.  We will use a simple DataGrid for this.  Open the toolbox in the
    Web Forms panel and double-click on the DataGrid control.  This add the
    control to the page and will display a table on the web page view.
    </para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs012"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs012.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Table Properties</title>
    <para>Configure the DataGrid control by right-clicking on the table and selecting
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Property Builder</guimenu></menuchoice>.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs013"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs013.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>DataGrid Properties</title>
    <para>You can adjust most properties of the table such as colours,
    fonts, borders, etc.  You can control paging aspects that will be taken care
    of automatically by the control, you only need specify the number of
    results per page.  For now we only want to adjust the most important
    aspects of the table, where the data comes from.  </para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs014"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs014.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>DataGrid Bindings</title>
    <para>From the first <menuchoice><guimenu>General</guimenu></menuchoice>
    properties panel you must select the DataSource, DataMember, and select the
    Data key field (especially important for updatable tables).  These properties
    may be selected via the drop-downs on the panel, allowing you to
    select the now-familiar controls configured earlier.  Once configured, press the
    OK button to save the changes.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs016"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs016.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Preview</title>
    <para>Once the details have been saved the view of the table in the page
    will be updated to reflect the dataset details.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs017"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs017.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Page Initialization</title>
    <para>We are very nearly finished.  The controls are all ready to be
    used, however, the final touch is to edit our Page_Load function.
    Double-click on the empty part of the web page view in Visual Studio
    and the associated <computeroutput>.vb</computeroutput> file will be
    opened.  This is the file containing the actual code.  You will be
    automatically placed at the Page_Load function.  This is the page
    initialization section where will need to instruct the DataAdapter to
    fill with data, and then instruct the DataGrid to bind to that data.</para></formalpara>
    <para>These lines of code need to be added by hand:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
SqlDataAdapter1.Fill(DataSet11)
DataGrid1.DataBind()
]]></programlisting>

    <para>You will find that Visual Studio will offer some assistance in the
    form of intellisense command-completion while you are typing.</para>

    <figure id="rthvs018"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs018.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>The End Result</title>
    <para>Next we will set the project's initial start-page by right-clicking
    on the form name in solution explorer and selecting
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Set as Start Page</guimenu></menuchoice>
    option.  Finally we can run the project using the start button at the top.
    The project will automatically be built and a browser window launched
    automatically.  Admire your results.  When finished, on closing the browser
    windows you will automatically return to Visual Studio.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthvs019"><title>Databound Examples using MS Visual Studio</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/vs019.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

</orderedlist>


 </sect3>

 <sect3 id="rthaspxmigratevirt"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
    <para>The previous section showed us how to build a very basic web
    application using an ASPX data-bound control.  Now we will host this same
    application in Virtuoso demonstrating that IIS is no longer required for
    ASPX application deployment.</para>

    <orderedlist>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Locating your ASPX application</title>
    <para>Use explorer to locate the ASPX application you want to move
    away from IIS and re-deploy under Virtuoso.  The previous section created
    the application in the IIS virtual directory represented by
    <computeroutput>http://ash:8888/aspxdemo1/</computeroutput> which was
    physically located in
    <computeroutput>c:\inetpub\wwwroot\aspxdemo1\</computeroutput>.  We
    can simply copy this directory and place it somewhere under either the
    VSP root directory or WebDAV.  We will copy the application to a
    location in WebDAV for a local Virtuoso server.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthmig001"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/mig001.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Add a Network Place to DAV</title>
    <para>From My Network Places in explorer or Network Neighborhood
    double-click on the <menuchoice><guibutton>Add Network Place</guibutton></menuchoice>
    shortcut to start the wizard.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthmig002"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/mig002.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Network service provider</title>
    <para>Select the default option.  Click next to continue.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthmig003"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/mig003.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Internet or Network Address</title>
    <para>Here you specify the URL of DAV on the Virtuoso server.  We
    are using Virtuoso on the local machine but this could be anywhere on
    the Internet.  Click next to continue.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthmig004"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/mig004.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Name the Network Place</title>
    <para>Provide the network place with a meaningful name so we
    can easily find this location in the future.
    Click on next to continue.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthmig005"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/mig005.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Open the Network Place</title>
    <para>On the final panel of the wizard there is a checkbox to
    "Open this network place when I click Finish" that we will leave checked.
    Click Finish to continue and open the DAV directory.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthmig006"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/mig006.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Connect to DAV</title>
    <para>When you attempt to connect to DAV you will be prompted for a User name and
    Password.  These will be whatever you entered during the installation, possibly
    both dav, in which case type dav in both fields and press the OK
    button to continue.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthmig007"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/mig007.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Copy the ASPX application to DAV</title>
    <para>Once the explorer opens up on the DAV network place we can
    copy the <computeroutput>aspxdemo1</computeroutput> application
    directory to it.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthmig008"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/mig008.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Configure Virtual Directory</title>
    <para>Now we have to configure a Virtuoso virtual directory. Go to Conductor / Web Application Server / HTTP Hosts &mp; Directories.
    </para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthmig009"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/mig009.png"/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Add Virtual Directory</title>
    <para>The "folder" icon for the hosts defined will list all mappings currently present for the Virtuoso
    server. Click on the "New Directory" link to continue.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthmig010"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/mig010.png"/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Select DAV Domain template</title>
    <para>On the next page select for "Type" the DAV Domain template and click "Next".</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthmig011"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/mig011.png"/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>Configure the Virtual Directory parameters</title>
    <para>We must supply a logical path, <computeroutput>/aspxdemo1</computeroutput>,
    in this case.  We must also supply the physical path that this represents,
    we can either type in the DAV location or use the Browse button to the find
    the directory under DAV.  The WebDAV checkbox will correctly already be checked.
    For now we will also set to Allow Directory Browsing, and Override execution
    permissions in WebDAV.  Finally we must set the VSP Execution user to
    <computeroutput>dba</computeroutput> using the drop down.
    To save the changes click on the "Save Changes" button at the bottom of the page.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthmig012"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/mig012.png"/></figure>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><formalpara><title>View the ASPX page hosted in Virtuoso DAV</title>
    <para>With the virtual directory configured we have only to test that it works
    as expected.  On opening a browser at:
    <computeroutput>http://localhost/aspxdemo1/WebForm1.aspx</computeroutput>,
    we will see the same output as before.</para></formalpara>
    <figure id="rthmig013"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Applications to Virtuoso</title>
      <graphic fileref="rth/mig013.jpg" width="" depth=""/></figure>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>

 <note><title>Note:</title>
 <para>If ASPX hosting is attempted on a machine that never had IIS installed
 it is possible that ASP.NET is not configured, although required.  The
 Virtuoso installer will take care of this for you in most cases but if you run into
 problems you may want to confirm that ASP.NET is configured correctly.
 You will have to use the regedit utility to edit the registry, changing a
 search-path so System.Web.dll can find aspnet_asapi.dll.  Always exercise caution
 whenever editing the registry as invalid data can prevent your machine
 from operating properly.</para>
 <para>You will first need to find out what version of the
 <computeroutput>aspnet_isapi.dll</computeroutput> library you have.  The
 simplest way to determine this is by locating the file and right-clicking properties
 on it from explorer.</para>
 <para>Assuming the version is 1.0.3705.288, we should enter the following
 details into the registry if the
 <computeroutput>HKLM\Microsoft\ASP.NET</computeroutput> key
 is missing (if your version differs change it accordingly):</para>
 <programlisting><![CDATA[
[HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\ASP.NET]
     "RootVer"="1.0.3705.288"
[HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\Microsoft\ASP.NET\1.0.3705.288]
     "Path"="C:\WINDOWS\Microsoft.NET\Framework\v1.0.3705"
     "DllFullPath"="C:\WINDOWS\Microsoft.NET\Framework\v1.0.3705\aspnet_isapi.dll"
]]></programlisting>
 </note>

 </sect3>

 </sect2>


 <!-- sect2 id="rthaspxmigratevirtlinux"><title>Migrating ASP.Net Application to Virtuoso on Other Platforms</title>
 </sect2 -->


</sect1>
