<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2016 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<chapter id="runtimehosting" label="runtimehosting.xml">
 <title>Runtime Hosting</title>

 <abstract>
<para>Virtuoso can be extended by in-process hosting of a number
of different run time environments.  This includes: Microsoft's .NET CLR (CLR),
the Mono ECMA-CLI (Mono), and the Java Virtual Machine (JVM).
Thus, you can create persistent stored modules, SQL functions,
and user defined data types using any Microsoft .NET or Mono
bound language, Java, and traditional languages such as 'C'/C++.</para>
<para>Objects provided by hosted run times, such as Java and CLR can be
directly and transparently accessed from SQL.  This also means that
application logic in any hosted language can be exposed as a web
service.  By offering a choice of hosted run times in a cross platform
setting, Virtuoso adds a new degree of freedom for the application
designer.  Applications can now be developed and deployed on either
Windows, Linux or Unix, can be written in Java or any .net CLR bound
language and can talk to any database via Virtuoso's virtual databasing
capabilities.</para>
 <para>The Virtuoso Server Extension Interface (VSEI) provides C
 interfaces and hooks that enable developers to write external functionality
 that can be bolted on the side of Virtuoso and called as SQL functions.
</para>
</abstract>

<sect1 id="rthactivation"><title>Runtime Environments</title>
 <para>The Virtuoso server in its standard build is a single executable.  To
 allow for external customizations based on VSEs the Virtuoso server engine
 becomes a callable library, the main function is re-written to incorporate other
 libraries and a new executable is created.
For example, a Virtuoso server
 that contains PHP support under Windows consists of: </para>

<programlisting>
 65K virtuoso-odbc-php-t.exe
5.2M libvirtuoso-odbc-t.dll
1.2M php4ts.dll
</programlisting>

 <para>which replaces the usual <computeroutput>7M virtuoso-odbc-t.exe</computeroutput>.
 <computeroutput>virtuoso.odbc-php-t.exe</computeroutput> is then executed
 in the usual way.</para>

 <para>The Linux counterpart would be an
 <computeroutput>8M virtuoso-odbc-php-t</computeroutput> binary.</para>

 <para>The Virtuoso executable files provided in the installer are appropriately
 named to indicate which customizations are supported.  e.g. one that
 contains "php" and "clr" in the file name has been built with PHP and
 CLR support.</para>

 <para>The location of the support libraries (.DLL's) for the various
 customizations of Virtuoso on Windows must either be in the %PATH%;
 environment variable or be the same directory as the virtuoso .EXE file.
 Virtuoso will not be able to start otherwise.</para>

 <note><title>Note:</title>
 <para>If Virtuoso is starting as a system service then the
 SYSTEM PATH must be altered as opposed to the USER PATH.  The USER PATH
 is appropriate to alter if Virtuoso is being started as that user, usually when
 in debug/foreground mode.  This is applicable to any required environment
 variables, not just PATH.</para></note>

 <para>Hosted environments that require SQL access back to the database can
 make use of the in-process client mechanism.  Hosted Runtimes such as PHP
 and ASP .Net would ordinarily use an RPC based (ODBC) connection.  To improve
 the efficiency of the system, keeping it all in-process, a special connection
 can be made with no alteration to the API used in the code for communication.</para>

 <tip><title>See Also:</title>
   <para>The <link linkend="inprocess">In-Process Client</link> keeps connections
   within Virtuoso avoiding unnecessary RPCs.</para></tip>
 </sect1>

<sect1 id="rthclr"><title>CLR, .Net &amp; ASPX Host</title>
 <para>The Common Language Runtime (CLR) is the foundation upon which the
 Microsoft® .NET strategy is built.  The CLR provides an execution environment
 that manages running code and provides services that make software development
 easier.  These services include automatic memory management, cross-language
 integration, interoperability with existing code and systems, simplified
 deployment, and a fine grained security system.  The .NET platform also
 brings with it a new programming language called C#.  It is very similar to Java
 and allows developers to make full use of all features available on the .NET runtime.</para>

 <para>The CLR can run a variety of different types of applications, such as:
 console applications, Web server scripts, traditional Win32-based applications,
  and more.</para>

<para>The CLR provides a language specification for compilers to generate classes
 and code that can interoperate with other programming languages (The
 Common Language Specification: CLS) .  Any API that is written using a
 CLS provider language can be used by any language that is a CLS consumer.
 Compilers generate code in a format called Common Intermediate Language
 (CIL) which is an intermediate representation of a compiled program and is
 easy to compile to native code or be compiled using Just-in-Time (JIT)
 engines.  The restrictions placed by the runtime on the CIL byte codes
 ensures good potential for code optimization by the JIT compiler.  The runtime
 environment provides garbage collection, threading and a comprehensive class
 library.  All these things make code development easier and more appealing
 by allowing a mixture of languages to be collaborating to produce results, all
 contained within a managed sandbox to prevent bugs from breaking other running
 programs.</para>

 <para>Windows has compilers that target the virtual machine from a number
 of languages: Managed C++, JavaScript, Eiffel, Component Pascal, APL, Cobol,
 Perl, Python, Ruby, Scheme, Smalltalk, Standard ML, Haskell, Mercury and Oberon. </para>

 <para>Virtuoso is a CLR host.  It is responsible for initializing the runtime,
 defining the application domain (its runtime boundaries, security settings, etc),
 and executing user code within such domains.  Windows can be used
 as the development platform, a very developer friendly environment with
 a rich set of tools, but you  will not be restricted to Windows, .NET
 and IIS to run the assemblies produced.  Where .NET is not readily available
 or desired Virtuoso contains Mono, an open source re-implementation of
 Microsoft .NET, a vehicle making .NET cross-platform.  </para>

 <para>The CLR run time is a part of the Virtuoso process.  The Mono run time may be
run either as in-process or as out-of-process.  Hosted applications can make use of
the regular Virtuoso .net data provider to access Virtuoso SQL data and procedures.
 Microsoft ASPX files can also be run directly from Virtuoso either from
 the filesystem or WebDAV.  Each of these capabilities releases you from
 the Microsoft platforms without compromising your development platform.</para>


<!-- You can create single-file or multifile assemblies using an IDE, such as Visual
Studio .NET, or the compilers and tools provided by the .NET Framework
SDK.  The simplest assembly is a single file that has a simple name and is
loaded into a single application domain. This assembly cannot be
referenced by other assemblies outside the application directory and
does not undergo version checking. To uninstall the application made up of
the assembly, you simply delete the directory where it resides. For many developers,
an assembly with these features is all that is needed to deploy an application.
-->


 <sect2 id="rthclrenvsetdotnet"><title>Environment Setup</title>
 <para>Follow the steps below to configure the CLR runtime environment
 with Virtuoso:</para>

 <orderedlist>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Install .Net Framework SDK</title>
  <para>The .Net Framework can be downloaded from the Microsoft web site.</para>
  </formalpara>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Install virtclr.dll into the GAC</title>
  <para>The <computeroutput>virtclr.dll</computeroutput> library supplied with
  Virtuoso must be installed into the .Net 'Global Assembly Cache (GAC)'.</para>
  </formalpara>
  <para>.Net library components can be installed into the GAC using the command:
  <computeroutput>gacutil /i &lt;DLL&gt;</computeroutput>.  The gacutil utility is supplied
  with the .Net framework.  In this case we would use the command:</para>
  <programlisting>gacutil /i virtclr.dll</programlisting>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Register virtclr with COM</title>
  <para>The virtclr.dll library must be registered as COM object  using the
  'regasm' utility as follows:</para></formalpara>
  <programlisting>regasm virtclr.dll</programlisting>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Install virt_http.dll into the GAC</title>
  <para>The <computeroutput>virt_http.dll</computeroutput> library supplied with
  Virtuoso must be installed into the .Net 'Global Assembly Cache (GAC)'.</para>
  </formalpara>
  <programlisting>gacutil /i virt_http.dll</programlisting>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>

 <note><title>Note:</title>
 <para>The utilities gacutil and regasm are typically found in
 <computeroutput>%WINDIR%\Microsoft.NET\Framework\&lt;version&gt;</computeroutput>
 e.g. <computeroutput>C:\WINDOWS\Microsoft.NET\Framework\v1.0.3705.288</computeroutput>.</para>
 </note>

 <para>Failure to register the components successfully as described will generate
 "Virtuoso failed to initialize" messages.  The Virtuoso installer, however, should
 automatically register the components for you.</para>

 <para>Private assemblies must be deployed within the directory of the
 containing application and are found during runtime through a process called
 probing - a mapping from an assembly's identity to a file on disk that contains
 the manifest. </para>

 <para>By default, probing for private assemblies is done from the root directory
 (application base) of the calling application (Virtuoso in this case) and the subdirectories that
 follow naming conventions based on assembly name and culture.  You can
 customize this behavior by specifying a privatePath in your application's
 configuration file. The privatePath is a semi-colon delimited list of directories
 that the common language runtime will search for private assemblies.  These
 directory names are relative to the application base - they cannot point outside
 the application base. The directories in the privatePath will be searched after
 the application base itself.  The following configuration file adds a bin
 directory to the assembly search path: </para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
<configuration>
    <runtime>
        <assemblyBinding xmlns="urn:schemas-microsoft-com:asm.v1">
            <probing privatePath="bin"/>
        </assemblyBinding>
    </runtime>
</configuration>
]]></programlisting>

 <para>Configuration files are called:
 <computeroutput>&lt;application name&gt;.config</computeroutput>.  </para>
</sect2>

 <sect2 id="rthclrdotnettest"><title>Testing the Virtuoso .NET Runtime Environment</title>
 <para>To test that you have successfully started the Virtuoso server with
 .NET CLR runtime support make a simple library, import the contained class
 into Virtuoso and call it.</para>

 <para>Using an text editor create a C# source file in the server
 root directory called sanity.cs, with the following contents:</para>

 <programlisting><![CDATA[
using System;

public class sanity
{
    public static string test(string  name) {
       return "Hello "+ name + ", from Virtuoso";
    }
}
]]></programlisting>
 <para>This sample needs to be compiled into bytecode assembly before it can
 be used.  Use a command prompt that is suitable set up to find .NET
 utilities in its path, the .NET Framework SDK installation provides a
 shortcut in the Start menu to a command prompt that is preconfigured.
 From the command prompt change directory to the Virtuoso server root
 containing the C# source file.</para>

 <programlisting><![CDATA[
C:\Program Files\OpenLink\Virtuoso 3.0\bin>csc /target:library sanity.cs
Microsoft (R) Visual C# .NET Compiler version 7.00.9466
for Microsoft (R) .NET Framework version 1.0.3705
Copyright (C) Microsoft Corporation 2001. All rights reserved.
]]></programlisting>

 <para>Now this library must be introduce to the Virtuoso Server.  Using ISQL
 use the following commands to test the CLR:</para>

 <programlisting><![CDATA[
C:\Program Files\OpenLink\Virtuoso 3.0\bin>isql 1112
Connected to OpenLink Virtuoso
Driver: 03.00.2315 OpenLink Virtuoso ODBC Driver
OpenLink Interactive SQL (Virtuoso), version 0.9849b.
Type HELP; for help and EXIT; to exit.
SQL> DB..import_clr (vector ('sanity'), vector ('sanity'));

Done. -- 300 msec.
SQL> select sanity::test('Rob');
callret
VARCHAR
______________________________________________

Hello Rob, from Virtuoso

1 Rows. -- 60 msec.
]]></programlisting>

 <para>Congratulations, you have proven that your Virtuoso server
 can run .NET classes.</para>

 <tip><title>See Also:</title>
 <para>The Virtuoso Tutorials, which are installed with the Demo Virtuoso
 Server (port 1112), contains numerous samples further demonstrating the use
 of the CLR, .NET and Virtuoso.</para></tip>

  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
    <para>The <link linkend="createassembly">Create Assembly</link> Syntax</para>
    <para>The External Hosted <link linkend="createassembly">Create PROCEDURE</link> Syntax</para></tip>

 </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="rthclrmono"><title>CLR &amp; Mono</title>

 <para>The Mono Project is an open development initiative sponsored by Ximian
 that is working to develop an open source, Unix version of the Microsoft .NET
 development and run time platform.  Its objective is to enable Unix developers to build
 and deploy cross-platform .NET Applications.  Likewise, this expands the
 capabilities of Windows programmers, this project opens .NET to non
 Windows platforms.  Mono will implement various Microsoft technologies that
 have now been submitted to the ECMA for standardization.</para>

 <para>The Goal is similar to that of Java, implementing a common virtual machine
 on multiple operating systems, however you are not restricted to one
 language.</para>

 <para>Like .NET, Mono contains a Common Language Infrastructure (CLI) virtual,
 machine that contains a class loader, Just-in-time compiler, and a garbage
 collecting runtime; a class library that can work with any language which
 works on the CLR; a compiler for the C# language.</para>

 <para>Windows has compilers that target the virtual machine from a number
 of languages: Managed C++, JavaScript, Eiffel, Component Pascal, APL, Cobol,
 Perl, Python, Ruby, Scheme, Smalltalk, Standard ML, Haskell, Mercury and Oberon.
 A single object system, threading system, class libraries, and garbage
 collection system can be shared across all these languages, the CLR.</para>

 <para>The CLR and the Common Type System (CTS) enables applications and
 libraries to be written in a collection of different languages that target
 the CLR byte code.  This means that you could define a class to do algebraic
 manipulation written in C#, that class can be reused from any other
 language that supports the CLI.  You could create a class in C#, subclass
 it in C++ and instantiate it in an Eiffel program.</para>

  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
    <para>The <link linkend="createassembly">Create Assembly</link> Syntax</para>
    <para>The External Hosted <link linkend="createassembly">Create PROCEDURE</link> Syntax</para></tip>

 <sect2 id="rthclrenvsetmono"><title>Environment Setup</title>
 <para>Ximian announced the launch of the Mono project, an effort to create
 an open source implementation of the .NET Development Framework.</para>
 <para>Follow the steps below to configure the CLR runtime environment
 with Virtuoso:</para>

 <orderedlist>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Install Mono</title>
  <para>The Mono package is available from the
  <ulink url="http://www.go-mono.com/">Mono project home page</ulink> in the
  form of an RPM for Linux.  The source is also available.</para>
  </formalpara>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Make mscorlib.dll available to /usr/local/lib</title>
  <para>The mscorlib.dll is installed by Mono and needs to be symlinked from
  its default location to <computeroutput>/usr/local/lib</computeroutput>.</para>
  </formalpara>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>

</sect2>

 <sect2 id="rthclrmonotest"><title>Testing the Virtuoso Mono Runtime Environment</title>
 <para>To test that you have successfully started the Virtuoso server with
 Mono CLR runtime support make a simple library, import the contained class
 into Virtuoso and call it.</para>

 <para>Using an text editor create a C# source file in the server
 root directory called sanity.cs, with the following contents:</para>

 <programlisting><![CDATA[
using System;

public class sanity
{
    public static string test(string  name) {
       return "Hello "+ name + ", from Virtuoso";
    }
}
]]></programlisting>
 <para>This sample needs to be compiled into bytecode assembly before it can
 be used.  Make sure you environment is configured to use Mono,
 change directory to the Virtuoso server root containing the C# source file.  Run:</para>

 <programlisting><![CDATA[
bash$ mcs /target:library sanity.cs
Compilation succeeded
]]></programlisting>

 <para>Now this library must be introduce to the Virtuoso Server.  Using ISQL
 use the following commands to test the CLR:</para>

 <programlisting><![CDATA[
C:\Program Files\OpenLink\Virtuoso 3.0\bin>isql 1112
Connected to OpenLink Virtuoso
Driver: 03.00.2315 OpenLink Virtuoso ODBC Driver
OpenLink Interactive SQL (Virtuoso), version 0.9849b.
Type HELP; for help and EXIT; to exit.
SQL> DB..import_clr (vector ('sanity'), vector ('sanity'));

Done. -- 300 msec.
SQL> select sanity::test('Rob');
callret
VARCHAR
______________________________________________

Hello Rob, from Virtuoso

1 Rows. -- 60 msec.
]]></programlisting>

 <para>Congratulations, you have proven that your Virtuoso server
 can run .NET classes via Mono Runtime.</para>

 <tip><title>See Also:</title>
 <para>The Virtuoso Tutorials, which are installed with the Demo Virtuoso
 Server (port 1112), contains numerous samples further demonstrating the use
 of the CLR, .NET, Mono and Virtuoso.</para></tip>

  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
    <para>The <link linkend="createassembly">Create Assembly</link> Syntax</para>
    <para>The External Hosted <link linkend="createassembly">Create PROCEDURE</link> Syntax</para></tip>

 </sect2>
</sect1>

&jvmapi;
&cinterface;
&plugins;

<!--

For Java :
0) JDK or JRE needs to be installed
1) jvm.dll needs to be in %PATH% , *copy* will not work !
2) JavaClasspath (INI setting) needs to contain path to all .class .jar files which are used


There's a [Mono] INI section.
In there there are :
MONO_PATH - where your assemblies (non-system ones) are
MONO_ROOT - where the Mono is installed.
MONO_CFG_DIR - where the mono configuration files are
virtclr.dll - the full path to the above.


The three upcase values you can set also as env variables.

To start ASPX demos on Linux (demo machine) needed:

copy virt_aspx.dll and virtclr.dll in demo directory.
copy machine.config to demo/mono directory
export MONO_ROOT=/dbs/virtuoso/3.0/mono/lib

all necessary file can be found in =/dbs/virtuoso/3.0/mono

The virtclr.dll can be put on ever dir described in settings MONO_PATH (Global assembly cache in Windows).

But virt_aspx.dll need for now in db (application root dir)

For now we link static libmono.a and we need dll (classes) from some distribution.

The static link has two good sides:

We not depend from mono cvs tree status
We can fast put ours patchs.
Also will add necessary dll in distrib.

-->
</chapter>

