<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2013 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->

<sect2 id="secureodbcx509"><title>Using X509 Certificates With ODBC Connection</title>

<para>Virtuoso can be configured to authenticate ODBC logins with a single
X.509 certificate.  The certificate must be registered server side for this purpose
and may contain an additional custom attribute for the users SQL account name.
In this way all login information is held in the possibly password protected
certificate.  The user specifies the certificate path in the place of the user name
and the certificate encryption password as the password.  This works with the
login dialog of the ODBC driver or within a SQLDriverConnect login string.</para>

<!-- is any indication on the client dialog that you can supply a key file instead.  either a browse button or a checkbox to specify key and a browse button. -->
<!-- ser admin page for uploading keys to the server? -->

<para>It is also possible to set up the ODBC client to check for the server's
X.509 certificate by specifying a client side CA (Certificate Authority) list.</para>

<para>The X509 certificate can be used for authentication with the
Virtuoso server via SSL.  In this  case the ODBC client will use an X.509
certificate which contains a SQL username as an extension.
This extension is added when the certificate is issued.  Since an object
ID (OID) of the username attribute can be used any valid object identifier that
does not conflict with existing OIDs (for example 2.16.840.1.NNNNNN).
It will be best to have one's own registered OID for that purpose.</para>

  <sect3 id="secureodbcx509foafsll"><title>WebID Protocol ODBC Login</title>
    <para>Virtuoso supports WebID Protocol ODBC Login. Thus, the INI parameter X509ClientVerify can accept the following values:</para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>0 - do not require</listitem>
      <listitem>1 - ask for trusted certificates</listitem>
      <listitem>2 - optionally ask, if certificate is given will be verified</listitem>
      <listitem>3 - accept optionally any certificate even self-signed</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>If certificate contains WebID, the odbc login will use it. The WebID can be setup to particular account via Conductor's
users interface. </para>
    <para>A typical [Parameters] INI section should contain:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
SSLServerPort         = 1113
SSLCertificate          = keys/server.crt
SSLPrivateKey         =  keys/server.key
X509ClientVerify      = 3
]]></programlisting>
    <para>The client could connect in following way:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
isql 1113 "" -X client.p12 -T server.crt
]]></programlisting>
    <para>Note: The client certificate client.p12 contains WebID which is registered to some sql user account via Conductor.</para>
  </sect3>

<sect3 id="secureodbccertgen"><title>ODBC Client Certificate Generation Using "openssl" Tool</title>

  <para>To generate X509 certificates one can use the "openssl" tool obtained
  freely from <ulink url="http://www.openssl.org/">www.openssl.org</ulink>.
  The <computeroutput>openssl.cnf</computeroutput> configuration file
  must be edited to include the new extension for sqlUserName, but first we
  have to find the hexadecimal representation of the SQL Username.  Then
  you can proceed the use the openssl to create and confirm the
  certificate.  Follow the steps below:</para>

 <orderedlist>
  <listitem><para><emphasis>Find the HEX representation of the SQL Username</emphasis></para>
  <para>You can either work this out from ASCII codes or use a hexdump utility
  found on most Unix platforms.  The following command would be sufficient,
  replacing &lt;user_name&gt; with the actual username:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
$ echo -n "<user_name>" | hexdump -e '":" 1/1 "%02X"'
]]></programlisting>

  <para>For example, the username <computeroutput>'dba'</computeroutput>
  would be <computeroutput>:64:62:61</computeroutput>.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis>Edit the OpenSSL config file: openssl.cnf</emphasis></para>
  <para>Open the file in a text editor of your choosing and add the following:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
[ new_oids ]
sqlUserName=2.16.840.1.NNNNNN.1

...
[ usr_cert ]
...
sqlUserName = DER:NN:NN:NN:NN:NN.....
]]></programlisting>

   <para>replacing <computeroutput>:NN:NN.....</computeroutput> with the
   hexadecimal representation of the username we discovered in the
   previous step.</para>
   </listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis>Make New Certificate Request</emphasis></para>

  <para>Make new certificate request using the command:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
$ openssl req -new
]]></programlisting>

  <para>The tool will ask for certain details.  Once completed it will
  generate a private key also.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis>Generate Certificate</emphasis></para>
  <para>Assuming the role of CA, generate a certificate using the request
  from the previous step, using the following command:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
$ openssl ca -in <req_file>
]]></programlisting>

  <para>The tool will print the details of request and will ask you to sign and
  commit the certificate into the CA repository.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis>Verify New Certificate</emphasis></para>
  <para>Check that the certificate contains the right SQL account name; use
  the following command to obtain a text dump of the certificate:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
openssl x509 -in <certfile> -text -noout
]]></programlisting>

<para>Now we can scan the contents of the output for the extension entries
we added earlier:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
>>>>>
X509v3 extensions:
....
2.16.840.1.NNNNNNN.1:
<SqlAccountName>
^^^^^^ this should match the new OID ^^^^^
>>>>>
]]></programlisting>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="secureodbcclisrvsetup"><title>Virtuoso Server Configuration</title>
  <para>The Virtuoso server can work in two modes based on an
  SSL connection:</para>

  <simplelist>
   <member><emphasis>basic</emphasis> - this is when only connection is
   secured, no certificate verification.  The client is not required to have its own
   trusted certificate.</member>
   <member><emphasis>trusted</emphasis> - additional mechanisms are
   enabled to check client's certificate.  in this case the client is required to have
   a trusted certificate.</member>
  </simplelist>

  <para>To allow Virtuoso to check the client's certificates, the virtuoso.ini
  file must contain the following entries in [Parameters] section:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
; Basic session encryption only parameters
SSLServerPort           = 1113
SSLCertificate          = ./srv.cert.pem ; server's certificate
SSLPrivateKey           = ./srv.key.pem  ; server's private key, must match the certificate
; Trusted operation parameters
X509ClientVerify        = 1
X509ClientVerifyCAFile  = ./ca.pem	   ; CA list; file containing certificates of acceptable CA
X509ClientVerifyDepth   = 1 		   ; dependent of type of certificate checking can be &gt;1
X509ExtensionOID	  = 2.16.840.1.NNNNNNN.1 ; the OID value, same as that used to make client's certificates
]]></programlisting>

  <para>All certificate/key files need to be in PEM format.</para>

  <para>The server needs an "SSLCertificate" and "SSLPrivateKey" to begin
  listening on the "SSLServerPort".  These are essential for the secure
  operations.  Furthermore the certificate must match the private key;
  non-matching certificate and private keys will prevent server startup and
  an error will be logged.
  The private key is required to guarantee that the certificate's claim is true.
  The server certificate is used by the client to identify the server.  The
  client can retrieve and verify this key and choose whether the server
  an be trusted depending on circumstances. </para>

  <note><title>Note:</title>
  <para>basic operation (SSL/TLS) encryption only cannot be used to
  identify a client with certificate. </para></note>

  <para>The "X509ClientVerifyCAFile" is a file containing a CA's (Certificate
  Authority) certificates that the server can use to verify client certificates.
  The client certificate verification in general depends on the "X509ClientVerify" flag,
  which enables or disable this feature.  The 'X509ClientVerifyDepth"
  parameter is used to verify to what degree server will trust the  client's
  certificate. The lower the value, the higher the restriction levels, with a
  minimum value of 1.  This  means that the server will look in CA's certificates
  to find who has issued the client certificate.  If there is no matching CA
  entry the connection will be rejected;  If there is a matching entry then
  verify the issuer chain; If issuer chain is greater than "X509ClientVerifyDepth",
  the connection will be rejected.</para>

  <para>All file paths above must be either absolute or relative to the server working directory. </para>

  <note><title>Note:</title>
  <para>If primary key file is encrypted then the server must be started
  in foreground mode so that a password can be supplied in order to open the file.
  </para></note>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="secureodbcclisetup"><title>Virtuoso Client Configuration</title>

  <para>The following connection options control the client's behavior regarding SSL:</para>

  <simplelist>
   <member><emphasis>Encrypt</emphasis> - specifies type of secure
   connection to be used. </member>
   <member><emphasis>ServerCert</emphasis> - (optional) to specify which
   certificate(s) are to be used to verify server certificates.</member>
  </simplelist>

  <para>The <emphasis>Encrypt</emphasis> option can be set to '1' to specify
  a basic secure connection; no server identity verification will be performed.
  Note that this is only possible when the server is also set to make
  basic SSL connections.</para>

  <para>To ensure server's identity the <emphasis>Encrypt</emphasis> option
  must be set to full or relative (to application working directory) path to the file
  containing client's certificate and private key.  This file can be encoded in
  PKCS#12 or PEM format.  The certificate and private key contained may be
  generated using the steps outlined above.</para>

  <para>When the Encrypt option is set to point to a certificate file, the
  <emphasis>ServerCert</emphasis> option must be set to the full or
  relative path to file containing list of CA certificates in PEM format.  The content
  of this file will be used to verify server's certificate.</para>

  <para>When using these options the UID connection-option must be set to
  an empty string to enable certificate authorization.  The PWD option will be
  used to open the private key.</para>

  <para>Here is an example of an ODBC connect-string:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
...
connectString =
"HOST=localhost:1113;UID=;PWD=keysecret;ENCRYPT=c:\certs\mycertwithkey.p12;SERVERCERT=c:\certs\ca.pem"
...
]]></programlisting>

  <para>If client's certificate does not contains user name for SQL login then
  the server will try matching the certificate fingerprint against registered
  certificates. If any SQL account has such a certificate registered it
  will be used for login.  Otherwise login will be rejected.</para>

  </sect3>

  <sect3 id="secureodbcregkeys"><title>Registering Keys with Virtuoso</title>

  <para>To enable a client certificate to be used for authorization,
  the DBA must register it's MD5 fingerprint (checksum) in the database.
  Registered certificates can be removed from system.  Two functions
  exist for the purposes: <function>USER_CERT_REGISTER()</function>,
  and <function>USER_CERT_UNREGISTER()</function>.  Both functions
  rely on the MD5 checksum of the certificates being registered or un-registered,
  therefor you have the option of supplying these functions with the certificate
  file or the MD5 checksum directly.</para>

  <para>The functions are:</para>

<para><function>USER_CERT_REGISTER (<param>user_name</param>, <param>certificate</param>, <param>password</param>, <param>type</param>);</function></para>
<para><function>USER_CERT_UNREGISTER (<param>user_name</param>, <param>certificate</param>, <param>password</param>, <param>type</param>);</function></para>

 <para>The registered certificate's fingerprints are kept in the DB.DBA.SYS_USERS table as
 vectors of strings under the 'LOGIN_CERTIFICATES' user option value (U_OPTS column).
 The data stored there can be retrieved using a third function: </para>

 <para><function>USER_GET_OPTION()</function></para>

  <para>For example, one might invoke:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
USER_CERT_REGISTER ('DBA', 'file:/dba.pem', '', 'PEM');
]]></programlisting>

  <para>Note that 'file:' URL is needed to designate
  certificate is in a file on file system. </para>

  <para>The above action can be performed also without certificate supplied
  if the MD5 fingerprint is known:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
USER_CERT_REGISTER ('DBA', 'D9:6D:47:D7:67:47:D7:3C:2C:E0:89:91:F3:BC:E7:59');
]]></programlisting>

  <para>and</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
USER_CERT_UNREGISTER ('DBA', 'D9:6D:47:D7:67:47:D7:3C:2C:E0:89:91:F3:BC:E7:59');
]]></programlisting>

 </sect3>

</sect2>
