<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2013 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<chapter label="sqlprocedures.xml" id="sqlprocedures">
	<title>SQL Procedure Language Guide</title>
	<abstract>
<para>Stored procedures are a key component of database performance.  The fewer
messages are sent between the client and the server for a given transaction,
the faster it will complete.</para>

<para>Virtuoso/PL is a simple and straightforward language for writing stored
procedures and triggers in Virtuoso.  Its syntax is a combination of SQL and
C, making learning it as easy as possible. It offers the features commonly
found in database procedure languages in a simple, efficient and concise
package. This document presents the primary concepts of the language and
ends with a reference section.</para>
</abstract>
	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<sect1 id="GENERALPRINCIPLES">
		<title>General Principles</title>
		<para>
A stored procedure is a named piece of Virtuoso/PL code stored in the
SYS_PROCEDURES table. Stored procedures are created with the create
procedure statement and are used by executing a procedure call statement
through the regular SQL API.
</para>
		<para>
A procedure takes zero or more arguments and optionally returns a value.
Procedure arguments may be input, output or input and output.
In this manner a procedure may modify a variable passed to it by its
caller. If the procedure is called from a call statement executed by
a client process, the client process gets back the procedure&apos;s return
value and the values of output parameters.
</para>
<para>
Procedures can be called with positional or keyword parameters.  A call with positional
parameters will bind the first argument in the call to the first parameter in the
procedure parameter list and so on.  A keyword parameter call allows specifying
named parameters, where the argument of a given name is bound to the parameter of
the same name in the procedure's parameter list.  Procedure parameters may be
required or optional.  The combination of optional parameters and the keyword call
notation make it convenient to have procedures with large numbers of parameters of
which only part are used at any one time.
</para>
		<para>
Procedures have local variables and cursors that are not visible to
other procedures. Procedures can call each other without limitations,
including recursively.
</para>
		<para>
In addition to returning a value and changing values of output parameters
a procedure may yield one or more result sets. The client can receive
rows in result sets just like rows returned by a select statement.
A procedure calling another procedure cannot receive a result set
produced by the called procedure, however. While parameters and return
values work equally well between procedures as between procedure and
client application, a result set always goes to the client, even if the
procedure has been called by another procedure.  A procedure view is a
separate construct which allows a procedure to iterate over another procedure's
result set.  See the Procedure Views section.
</para>
		<para>
A procedure consists of statements and expressions similar to those of any
procedural language. In addition, procedures may contain SQL statements
operating on the procedure&apos;s arguments and local variables. Writing a
stored procedure is thus much like using embedded SQL in C, except that
a stored procedure is typically much faster.
</para>
		<para>
The elements of the procedure are:
</para>
		<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>Procedure Declaration</title>
					<para>
This is a create procedure statement that names the procedure and its
arguments.
</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>Variable Declaration</title>
					<para>
This declares a local variable for the procedure.
</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>Cursor Declaration</title>
					<para>
This declares a cursor, A cursor allows a procedure to iterate over the
rows produced by a select statement.
</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>Manipulative SQL statement</title>
					<para>
This can be a delete or update statement, either searched or positioned,
a cursor manipulation or other so called routine statement.
</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>Control statement</title>
					<para>
This is any control structure, loop, assignment or procedure call.
</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<formalpara>
					<title>Handler declaration</title>
					<para>
This specifies what to do in a specific exception situation. Exceptions
are error conditions produced by SQL statements (e.g. deadlock) or
&apos;not found&apos; situations.
</para>
				</formalpara>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<sect1 id="SCOPEOFDECLARATION">
		<title>Scope of Declarations</title>
		<para>A declaration can appear anywhere inside a compound statement. It affects
all statements in the compound statement following the declaration
statement.
</para>

	</sect1>
	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<sect1 id="sqlplDATATYPES">
		<title>Data Types</title>
		<para>
Virtuoso/PL supports the regular SQL scalar data types as well as user-defined-types
(UDTs).   UDTs and structures can be composed of data types or classes made from
any hosted language such C# or Java.
Local temporary tables are not supported by the present
Virtuoso but may be added in the future.
</para>
		<para>
Memory management is automatic. Parameters, cursors and intermediate
results are automatically allocated and freed.
</para>
		<para>
A parameter or variable can be of any data type a column can. Variables
are however typed at run time, so that the declared type is mostly for
documentation. The declared types also affect how interactive SQL
shows certain values.
</para>
<para>There is a special <parameter>vector</parameter> construct, declared
as type <parameter>ANY</parameter>, that can be used as an array.
Vectors must be instantiated using the <function>vector()</function> function,
optionally containing initial elements as a comma-separated list, and can
be increased in size using the <function>vector_concat()</function>.
Elements of a vector are read and changed using the
<link linkend="fn_aref"><function>aref()</function></link> and
<link linkend="fn_aset"><function>aset()</function></link> functions
respectively.  A special notation can be used as a short-hand for accessing the
elements of a vector one-level deep only.  The notation is by using the variable
with the index in square brackets.  Hence, <function>aref(vec, 1)</function> is
the same as <function>vec[1]</function>.

The following example reveal more:</para>

<example id="ex_vectorcontrol"><title>Using Vectors</title>
<para>Simple excerpt showing how to instantiate a vector.</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
declare vec1, vec2, vec3 any;

vec1 := vector();  -- simple empty vector
vec2 := vector('a', 'b', 1, 2);  -- vector of mixed types
vec3 := vector(vector('a', 'b'), vector(1, 2));  -- vector of vectors
]]></programlisting>

<para>Second-level elements of vec3 cannot be referenced as vec3[1][1].</para>

<para>Here is the code for a simple VSP page that shows how vectors
can be used.</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
<html>
 <body>
<?vsp
declare vec1 any;
declare i integer;

vec1 := vector();

http('loading up the vector using vector_concat...<br>');
i := 0;
while ( i <= 5 ) {
  vec1 := vector_concat(vec1, vector(i * 5));
  i := i + 1;
}

http('displaying the contents using aref<br>');
i := 0;
while ( i <= 5 ) {
  http_value(aref(vec1, i)); http('<br>');
  i := i + 1;
}

http('changing the values using aset<br>');
i := 0;
while ( i <= 5 ) {
  aset(vec1, i, i * 10);
  i := i + 1;
}

http('displaying the contents using [] notation<br>');
i := 0;
while ( i <= 5 ) {
  http_value(vec1[i]); http('<br>');
  i := i + 1;
}

http('changing the values using [] notation<br>');
i := 0;
while ( i <= 5 ) {
  vec1[i] := i * 15;
  i := i + 1;
}

http('displaying the contents using [] notation again<br>');
i := 0;
while ( i <= 5 ) {
  http_value(vec1[i]); http('<br>');
  i := i + 1;
}
?>
 </body>
</html>
]]></programlisting>

<para>Which produces the following output:</para>

<screen><![CDATA[
loading up the vector using vector_concat...
displaying the contents using aref
0
5
10
15
20
25
changing the values using aset
displaying the contents using [] notation
0
10
20
30
40
50
changing the values using [] notation
displaying the contents using [] notation again
0
15
30
45
60
75
]]></screen>
</example>

<tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para><link linkend="fn_aref"><function>aref()</function></link></para>
  <para><link linkend="fn_aset"><function>aset()</function></link></para>
  <para><link linkend="fn_vector_concat"><function>vector_concat()</function></link></para>
  </tip>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<sect1 id="RESULTSETS">
		<title>Handling Result Sets</title>
		<para>A single Virtuoso procedure may produce multiple result sets, each
with different result columns. A normal procedure produces one empty
result set, only returning a possible return value and values of output
parameters to the application.
</para>
    <para>The <function>result_names()</function>
predefines variables to be used in a result set to follow.  The variables must
be previously declared, from which the column data types are ascertained.
This assigns the meta data but does not send any results.  The
<function>result()</function> function sends its parameters as a single row
of results.  These parameters should be compatible with those in the previous
<function>result_names()</function>.  The <function>end_results()</function>
function can be used to separate multiple result sets.  The
<function>result_names()</function> can then be used to alter
the structure of the next result set.</para>
<para>The <function>result_names()</function> call can be omitted if
the application already knows what columns and their types are to be returned.</para>

<tip><title>See Also:</title>
    <para><link linkend="fn_result"><function>result()</function></link>,
    <link linkend="fn_result_names"><function>result_names()</function></link>,
    <link linkend="fn_end_result"><function>end_result()</function></link></para>
</tip>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<sect1 id="ARRAYS">
		<title>Result Sets and Array Parameters</title>
		<para>
A procedure may be called with array parameters,
c.f. SQLParamOptions. Each call can yield multiple result sets.
</para>
		<para>
The SQLMoreResults function is used to get from one result set to the
next and from one procedure call to the next. One may have to call this
function an indeterminate number of times before all results from a
procedure with array parameters have been received.
</para>
		<para>
Each procedure return is marked with SQL_SUCCESS_WITH_INFO with SQL state
&apos;PMORE&apos;. The next SQLFetch will retrieve the first row of the first
result set of the next procedure invocation.
</para>


	</sect1>
	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<sect1 id="EXCEPTIONS">
		<title>Exception Semantics</title>
		<para>
Exceptions are of two types: Not Found and SQLSTATE. A not found
exception occurs when a select - into or open statement finds no row or
when a fetch statement reads past the last row of a cursor. A SQLSTATE
exception may result from any operation, typically a manipulative
SQL statement. The SQLSTATE &apos;4001&apos;, deadlock is an example of this.
A user-written procedure may signal a user defined exception with the
signal function.
</para>
		<para>
Virtuoso/PL supports PSM 96 style exception handlers.  These allow catching specific SQL states or ranges of SQL states, invoking a specific block of code when the state is signalled from within the scope of the handler.  The handler may propagate the exception to an outer handler or transfer control to any appropriate point in the containing procedure.
</para>
		<para>
An unhandled exception will cause the procedure where it is detected to
return the exception to its caller. If the caller is another procedure
that has a handler for the specified exception that procedure invokes the handler. If the caller is a call statement issued
by a client, the client gets the SQLSTATE and the SQLExecute function
called by the client returns SQL_ERROR and the client application may
retrieve the SQLSTATE and message with the SQLError function.
</para>
		<para>
A SQLSTATE is any short string used to identify an error or exception
condition. The system itself generates certain predefined SQLSTATE&apos;s
for error conditions. Applications may add other states.
</para>
		<para>
See the DECLARE HANDLER, whenever statement and signal function for an example of
exception handling.
</para>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<sect1 id="PLREF">
		<title>Virtuoso/PL Syntax</title>
		<!-- ~ # ==== ~ ==== # ~ -->
		<sect2 id="createprocstmt">
			<title>Create Procedure Statement</title>
			<programlisting>
CREATE PROCEDURE NAME (parameter , parameter...) [RETURNS data_type]
{ statement ... }

parameter: parameter_type name data_type opt_default

parameter_type: IN | OUT | INOUT

opt_default: | DEFAULT literal | := literal
</programlisting>
  <para>The create procedure statement actually performs a "create or
  replace" type operation.  The create procedure statement compiles and stores a
  Virtuoso/PL procedure. The procedure text is first parsed and compiled into
  Virtuoso virtual machine code and if the compilation is successful the text
  is stored into the SYS_PROCEDURES table. This table is read at startup.
  Stored procedures are thus always available for use and need be defined
  only once.  New procedures created with the same name as existing procedures
  automatically replace their predecessor.</para>
  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
      <para><link linkend="createexthostproc">CREATE PROCEDURE Syntax - External hosted procedures</link></para></tip>
			<screen>
CREATE PROCEDURE FIBO (IN X INTEGER)
{
    IF (X &lt; 2)
	RETURN X;
    ELSE
	RETURN (FIBO (X - 1) + FIBO (X - 2));
}

CREATE PROCEDURE CFIBO (IN X INTEGER)
{
    DECLARE RES INTEGER;

    RES := FIBO (X);

    RESULT_NAMES (RES);

    RESULT (RES);
}
</screen>
</sect2>
		<sect2 id="grantprocstmt">
			<title>Grand Execute Statement</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
GRANT EXECUTE ON procedure_name TO "{USER | ROLE}" ;
]]></programlisting>
<para>The identifier quote character (double quotes) is important usage information since it indicates that 
the USER or ROLE has a literal identifier. Just as a reference (e.g., URL or URI) has the identifier quote 
characters "&lt;" and "&gt;" . </para>
<para>The grantee should have SQL rights in order execution of procedure to be granted to this user.
The rights can be set from Conductor->System Admin->User Accounts->Account->Edit->User Type:</para>
     <figure id="usrt" float="1">
       <title>User Type</title>
       <graphic fileref="ui/usrt.png"/>
     </figure>
<para><emphasis>Example</emphasis></para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
SQL>create procedure DB.DBA.SimplePrint (in txt varchar)
{
 return sprintf('Output is %s', txt);
}
;

Done. -- 0 msec.

SQL>grant execute on DB.DBA.SimplePrint to "demo";

Done. -- 0 msec.

SQL>use demo;

Done. -- 0 msec.

SQL>select DB.DBA.SimplePrint('Virtuoso');

callret
VARCHAR
_______________________________________________________________________________

Output is Virtuoso

1 Rows. -- 0 msec.

]]></programlisting>
</sect2>
	<sect2 id="spasviewsandtablespl">
		<title>Stored Procedures as Views &amp; Derived Tables</title>
		<para>
Virtuoso allows using a stored procedure result set in place of a table. A view may also be
defined as a stored procedure. This provides smooth integration to external
procedural logic in queries.
</para>
		<para>
When a procedure appears as a table, the procedure is called and its result set is inserted
into a temporary space. Processing continues from that point on as if the data came from a table.
</para>

<tip><title>See Also:</title>
<para>For more information about Store Procedures as Views &amp; Derived Tables go to the
<link linkend="spasviewsandtables">SQL Reference Chapter</link></para></tip>
		</sect2>

		<sect2 id="kwds">
			<title>Keyword and Optional Procedure Arguments</title>
<para>
Normally arguments in a procedure call are bound to formal parameters from left to right, as is
the default behavior in any programming language.  If a default value is specified for a parameter
in the procedure definition this parameter is optional and the default value will
be assigned to it if the caller does not specify a value.
A call may consist of zero or more positional arguments followed by zero or more keyword
arguments.  A positional argument is any scalar expression.
A keyword argument is marked with the syntax:
</para>
<programlisting>
NAME =&gt; scalar_exp
</programlisting>
<para>
This notation specifies that the expression is to be bound to the parameter NAME in the
procedure declaration.  The names are matched case-insensitively in all case modes.
After all leading positional arguments have been bound to the matching formal parameters
in the procedure definition, each keyword argument is bound to the parameter of the same name.
After this all unbound formal parameters are assigned to their default values.
If a parameter with no default remains unbound an error is signalled.  OUT and INOUT
parameters are always required, regardless of the mode of calling.
</para>
<para>
An expression can be passed as INOUT or OUT, but in that case the output
value assigned by the procedure is not accessible in the caller.  The output value
is only accessible if the actual parameter is a variable or parameter.
</para>
<para>
Arguments of procedures are always evaluated left to right.
</para>

<programlisting>
create procedure kwd (in k1 int := 111, inout k2 int, in k3 int := 333)
{
  result_names (k1, k2, k3);
  result (k1, k2, k3);
}

kwd (1,1+1,3);
-- results 1,2,3

kwd ();
-- error because inout parameters are always required

kwd (k2=&gt;1);
-- error because a constant is not a suitable value for an inout parameter.

kwd (k2=&gt;1+2);
-- result 111, 2, 333

kwd (k3=&gt;3, k1=&gt;1,k2=&gt;1+1);
-- result 1, 2, 3

kwd (1, k2=&gt;1+1);
-- result 1, 2, 333
kwd (1);
-- error, k2 is required
kwd (badkey=&gt;2, k2=&gt;2+1);
-- error, badkey not a parameter of the function

create procedure kwd2 (in k1 int , in k2 int, in k3 int)
{
  result_names (k1, k2, k3);
  result (k1, k2, k3);
}

kwd2 (k1=&gt;1, k2=&gt;2, k3=&gt;3);
-- result 1, 2, 3
kwd2 (1,2,3);
-- result 1, 2, 3
</programlisting>
</sect2>

		<!-- ~ # ==== ~ ==== # ~ -->
		<sect2 id="whilestmt">
			<title>if, while, for, foreach statements</title>
			<programlisting>
if_statement
	: IF &apos;(&apos; search_condition &apos;)&apos; statement opt_else

opt_else
	: /* empty */
	| ELSE statement

while_statement
	: WHILE &apos;(&apos; search_condition &apos;)&apos; statement

for_statement
  :	FOR &apos;(&apos; for_init_statement_list &apos;;&apos; for_opt_search_cond &apos;;&apos; for_inc_statement_list &apos;)&apos; statement
  | FOREACH &apos;(&apos; data_type_ref identifier IN_L scalar_exp &apos;)&apos; DO statement
</programlisting>
			<para>
The IF statement executes the immediately following statement if the
condition is true. If there is an else clause and the condition is false
the statement immediately following the else keyword will be executed.
</para>
			<para>
The while statement evaluates the search condition and executes the
following statement if the condition is true. It does this as long as
the condition is true. To exit from a loop, use goto. C-like break and
continue statements are not available.
</para>
			<para>
The for statement initiates the for_init_statement_list and executes
the following statement until the search condition is true. After
every execution of the statement it executes for_inc_statement_list.
You can exit the loop with using goto syntax also.
</para>
			<para>
The foreach statement executes the statement for each element from
an array and sets a variable to the corresponding element of that array.
</para>
			<screen><![CDATA[
IF (A > B)
    A := A + 1;
ELSE
    B := B + 1;

WHILE (1 = 1) {
    A := A + 1;
}

FOR (declare X any, X := 1; X <= 2 ; X := X + 1){
    S := S + X;
}

FOR (declare X any, X := 1; X <= 2 ; ){
    S := S + X;
    X := X + 1;
}

FOR (declare X any, X := 1; ; X := X + 1){
    if (X > 2)
    goto exit_loop;
    S := S + X;
}
exit_loop:

declare X integer;
X := 1;
FOR (; X <= 2 ; X := X + 1){
    S := S + X;
}

ARR := vector (1,2);
FOREACH (int X in ARR) do {
    S := S + X;
}
]]></screen>
		</sect2>
		<!-- ~ # ==== ~ ==== # ~ -->
		<sect2 id="compoundstmts">
			<title>compound statement</title>
			<programlisting>
compound_statement
	: &apos;{&apos; statement_list &apos;}&apos;
	;

statement_list
   	: statement_in_cs
	| statement_list statement_in_cs
	;

statement_in_cs
	: local_declaration &apos;;&apos;
	| compound_statement
	| routine_statement &apos;;&apos;
	| control_statement
	| label &apos;:&apos; statement
	;

statement
	: routine_statement &apos;;&apos;
	| control_statement
	| compound_statement
	;

local_declaration
	: cursor_def
	| variable_declaration
	| handler_declaration
	;

variable_declaration
	: DECLARE variable_list data_type
	;


variable_list
	: NAME
	| variable_list &apos;,&apos; NAME
	;
</programlisting>
			<para>The compound statement is the main building block of
procedures. Statements in a compound statement are executed left to right,
unless the flow of control is changed with a goto statement. The compound
statement allows declaring local variables and exception handlers.
See &apos;Scope Rules&apos; above for a description of the scope of declarations.
</para>
			<para>
Labeled statements (goto targets) and declarations can only occur within
a compound statement.
</para>
			<tip>
				<title>See:</title>
				<para><link linkend="createprocstmt">Create Procedure statement</link></para>
			</tip>
		</sect2>
		<!-- ~ # ==== ~ ==== # ~ -->
		<sect2 id="gotortnstmts">
			<title>goto, return statements</title>
			<programlisting>
goto_statement
	: GOTO label
	;

label	: NAME

return_statement
	: RETURN scalar_exp
	| RETURN
	;
</programlisting>
			<para>The goto statement unconditionally transfers control to the label
following it. The label can be anywhere within the same procedure. It is
in principle possible to jump into a block (e.g. loop body) from outside.
</para>
			<para>
The return statement causes the executing procedure to return. If a
return value is specified the expression is evaluated and returned as
the return value of the procedure. If no return value is specified the
procedure returns an undefined value.
</para>
			<para>
Returning from a procedure automatically frees any resources associated
with the procedure. This includes values in local variables or call by
value (IN) parameters and any cursors that may be open.
</para>
			<tip>
				<title>See:</title>
				<para><link linkend="createprocstmt">Create Procedure statement</link></para>
			</tip>
		</sect2>
		<!-- ~ # ==== ~ ==== # ~ -->
		<sect2 id="wheneverstmt">
			<title>whenever statement</title>
			<programlisting>
condition
	: NOT FOUND
	| SQLSTATE STRING
	;

handler_declaration
	: WHENEVER condition GOTO NAME
	;
</programlisting>
			<para>This declares that control should be transferred to a particular label
in the procedure whenever a condition occurs within the lexical scope
of the WHENEVER declaration. This is similar to the statement of the
same name found in most embedded SQL implementations.
</para>
			<para>
The scope of the declaration is all the lines lexically following the
declaration. A previous declaration is replaced by a new declaration
for the same &lt;condition&gt;.
</para>
			<screen>
CREATE PROCEDURE COUNT_CUSTOMERS (IN C_NAME VARCHAR)
{
    DECLARE COUNT INTEGER;

    COUNT := 0;

    DECLARE C CURSOR FOR SELECT C_ID FROM CUSTOMER WHERE C_NAME = C_NAME;

    WHENEVER SQLSTATE &apos;4001&apos; GOTO DEADLOCK;

    WHENEVER NOT FOUND GOTO DONE;

    OPEN C;
    WHILE (1=1)
    {
	FETCH C INTO N;
	COUNT := COUNT + 1;
    }

DONE:
    RETURN COUNT;

DEADLOCK:
    RETURN -1;
}
</screen>
			<note>
				<title>Note:</title>
				<para>This is about the same as select count (*) from CUSTOMER where C_NAME = ?; </para>
			</note>
		</sect2>
		<!-- ~ # ==== ~ ==== # ~ -->
		<sect2 id="callassignstmt">
			<title>call, assignment statements</title>
			<programlisting>
function_call
	: NAME &apos;(&apos; opt_scalar_exp_commalist &apos;)&apos;
	| call &apos;(&apos; scalar_exp &apos;)&apos; &apos;(&apos;opt_scalar_exp_commalist &apos;)&apos;
	;

call_statement
	: CALL NAME &apos;(&apos; opt_scalar_exp_commalist &apos;)&apos;
	| function_call
	;

assignment_statement
	: lvalue EQUALS scalar_exp
	| lvalue &apos;=&apos; scalar_exp
	;

lvalue	:  NAME
</programlisting>
			<para>The call statement calls a specified procedure with the given arguments.
The procedure to call is resolved at run time, i.e. the latest definition
prevails, even if it has been made after the calling procedure was
defined. The CALL reserved word is optional and is supported for
compatibility.
</para>
			<para>
If the called procedure has reference parameters (OUT or INOUT) the
matching actual parameter must be a variable or parameter.
</para>
			<para>
There is a computed function call form of function_call. In this,
the scalar expression in parentheses following the call keyword should
evaluate to a string which then identifies the function to be called.
</para>
			<para>
The assignment statement sets a value to a variable. The variable must
be either a local variable declared with declare or a procedure argument
declared in the procedure argument list. If the variable in question is
a reference parameter the assignment takes effect in the actual parameter
as will, i.e. the value of the argument variable in the caller is set.
</para>
			<screen>
CREATE PROCEDURE COMPUTED_CALL (IN Q INTEGER)
{
    DECLARE FN VARCHAR;

    FN := &apos;F&apos;;

    --- CALL FUNCTION FF WITH ARGUMENT 11.
    R := CALL (CONCATENATE (FN, &apos;F&apos;)) (11);
}
</screen>
		</sect2>
		<!-- ~ # ==== ~ ==== # ~ -->
		<sect2 id="openfetchetcintostmts">
			<title>open, fetch, close, select ... into statements</title>
			<programlisting>
SELECT opt_all_distinct selection
    INTO target_commalist
    table_exp
    with_opt_cursor_options_list
    ;

opt_all_distinct
	: /* empty */
	| ALL
	| DISTINCT
	;

with_opt_cursor_options_list
	: /* empty */
	| WITH opt_cursor_options_list
	;

cursor_option
	: EXCLUSIVE
	;

cursor_options_commalist
	: cursor_option
	| cursor_options_commalist &apos;,&apos; cursor_option
	;

opt_cursor_options_list
	: /* empty */
	| &apos;(&apos; cursor_options_commalist &apos;)&apos;
	;

cursor_def : DECLARE NAME CURSOR FOR query_exp
           | DECLARE NAME (DYNAMIC|KEYSET|STATIC) CURSOR FOR query_exp

open_statement
	: OPEN cursor opt_cursor_options_list
	;

fetch_statement : FETCH cursor INTO target_commalist
                | FETCH cursor (FIRST|NEXT|PREVIOUS|LAST) INTO target_commalist
                | FETCH cursor BOOKMARK scalar_exp INTO target_commalist

target_commalist
	: variable
	| target_commalist &apos;,&apos; variable
	;

close_statement
	: CLOSE cursor
	;
</programlisting>
			<para>The open, fetch and close statements manipulate cursors in Virtuoso/PL
statements. Cursors are declared with the declare cursor statement.
The select into statement is a shorthand for a cursor declaration, open,
fetch and close.
</para>
			<para>
A forward-only cursor declaration is a declaration only and executing one does not
take time. The open statement effectively starts the search associated
with the forward-only cursor.
</para>
			<para>
The forward-only cursor options used with open and select into allow controlling how
the cursor sets locks on selected rows and how many rows it fetches at
a time.  The EXCLUSIVE option should be
used if intending to update or delete a row in the cursor&apos;s evaluation.
This causes selected rows to be locked with exclusive (write) locks.
</para>
			<screen>
The statements:

{
    DECLARE CR CURSOR FOR SELECT C_NAME FROM CUSTOMER WHERE C_ID = ID;
    OPEN CR;
    FETCH CR INTO NAME;
    CLOSE CR;
}

and

SELECT C_NAME INTO NAME FROM CUSTOMER WHERE C_ID = ID;

have the same effect.
</screen>
			<tip>
				<title>See:</title>
				<para>the <link linkend="tpccintro">TPC C Bench Marking</link> chapter for more examples.</para>
			</tip>
		</sect2>
		<!-- XXX: NO INFORMATION
<sect2>
<title>result, result_names, end_result functions</title>

<para>
-->
<!-- function signal -->
		<!-- ~ # ==== ~ ==== # ~ -->
		<sect2 id="forstmt">
			<title>FOR Select Statement</title>
			<programlisting>
&lt;for statement&gt; ::=
     FOR &lt;query exp&gt; DO statement
</programlisting>
			<para>
The FOR statement provides a compact notation for iterating over the result
set of a cursor.  The body is executed once for each row in the query expression&apos;s result set.
The result columns produced by the query expression are accessible as variables of the same
name inside the body.  All result columns do therefore have to be named with the AS declaration
if they are not simple columns, in which case the name defaults to the column&apos;s name.
</para>
			<para>
The body can be exited in mid loop with a goto. The cursor of the FOR does not
have to be specifically closed or opened.  FOR statements can be freely nested.
If a WHENEVER NOT FOUND declaration is in effect before the FOR it will be canceled
by it, so that it is not in effect after the loop&apos;s body.
</para>
			<example>
				<title>Examples</title>
				<programlisting>
for select C_NAME, sum (O_VALUE) as value  from CUSTOMER, ORDER group by C_NAME DO
  {
    result (C_NAME, value);
  })
</programlisting>
				<para>
The equivalent code is
</para>
				<programlisting>
declare C_NAME, value any;
whenever not found goto done;
declare cr cursor for select ....;
open cr;
while (1) {
  fetch cr into C_NAME, value;
  whenever not found default;
  ...
}
done: ;
</programlisting>
			</example>
			<para>
The cursor and end label names are generated to be unique by the FOR expansion.
</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="setstmt">
			<title>SET statement</title>
			<programlisting>
Set_statement:
	SET option &apos;=&apos; scalar_exp
	| SET option OFF
	| SET option ON
	;

option:
	ISOLATION
	| LOCK_ESCALATION_PCT
	| TRIGGERS
	| PARAM_BATCH
	;
</programlisting>
			<para>The SET statement sets an option to a value. Options may control trigger
invocation, transaction isolation and other settable parameters of
the engine. A SET inside a procedure takes effect inside the procedure
and invoked procedures, counting from time of execution.  Control must
pass through the SET statement for it to take effect, i.e. SET is not
a declaration. The effect of a SET does typically not persist across
procedure return.
</para>
			<para>
A SET given at top level, i.e. directly executed and by a client as the
statement of a SQLExecute sets an option at the connection level. This
may only be reversed by another SET.
</para>
			<para>
The option may be:
</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="settriggers">
			<title>SET Triggers</title>
			<para>
A value of OFF or 0 causes triggers not to be invoked even if there may
be applicable triggers.  This is mostly useful for controlling recursion
of triggers or for debugging triggers.
</para>
			<para>The value of TRIGGERS is passed into called procedures but other options are not.
</para>
			<tip>
				<title>See Also:</title>
				<para><link linkend="SETstmt">SET statement.</link></para>
			</tip>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
<sect1 id="EXECSQLPROCSELECT">
		<title>Execute Stored Procedures via SELECT statement</title>
<para>Stored SQL Procedures can be executed via SELECT statement:</para>
<programlisting>
SELECT PROCEDURE_NAME (parameter , parameter...);
</programlisting>
<para>For ex.:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure mytest ( in ss varchar)
{
  return concat('My simple test with ', ss);
}
;


SQL> select mytest('Virtuoso');
callret
VARCHAR
_______________________________________________________________________________

My simple test with Virtuoso

1 Rows. -- 0 msec.
]]></programlisting>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="EXECSQLPROCFORK">
		<title>Execute Stored Procedures In Background</title>
<para>You can start procedure in background using the [name of the procedure][params]&amp; syntax.
This feature forks another ISQL process and leaves the other on background so there will be
two separate clients running separate client connections:</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
SQL>create procedure test()
{
return 'my simple test';
}
;
Done. -- 0 msec.
SQL>test()&
SQL> Connected to OpenLink Virtuoso
Driver: 05.07.3033 OpenLink Virtuoso ODBC Driver
OpenLink Interactive SQL (Virtuoso), version 0.9849b.
Type HELP; for help and EXIT; to exit.

Done. -- 10 msec.
]]></programlisting>
<para>See <link linkend="ASYNCEXECMULTITHREAD">Asynchronous Execution and Multithreading in Virtuoso/PL</link> for background jobs execution details.</para>
</sect1>

	&createassembly;
	&createexthostproc;

	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<sect1 id="ASYNCEXECMULTITHREAD">
          <title>Asynchronous Execution and Multithreading in Virtuoso/PL</title>
          <para>
Many application tasks benefit from parallel execution. This is specially true of I/O intensive workloads
where each thread spends a large amount of time waiting for the network or disks. Typical tasks include
crawling the web and importing large data sets. The whole process must not stop just because there is a
file cache miss or because there is round trip latency or a name resolution delay on the net.
          </para>
          <para>
To this effect, Virtuoso/PL provides the async_queue object. A stored procedure may create an async_queue
that will be served by a pool of worker threads. The size of this pool can be set when creating the queue.
          </para>
          <para>
The thread which made the queue can use the queue to pass procedure/parameter list pairs to the threads.
If a thread is available, the thread will execute the request, if not, the next thread of the pool to
become free will take the oldest queued item and execute it. Thus the queue is served in a FIFO fashion multiplexed over n threads.
          </para>
          <para>
The owner of the queue can check on the results of execution either collectively or individually. Each worker thread
has its own transaction and worker threads may end up waiting for each other own database locks and can deadlock.
The worker thread code is responsible for committing its own transaction and handling any deadlock retries or such.
          </para>
          <para>
When the thread owning the queue makes a request, a request number is returned. This number can be used to later
request the return value and error status of the request. A queue cannot be persisted in a database table and cannot
be passed between threads. A queue can be passed between procedures and kept in data structures such as arrays.
Queue are internally reference counted and when the last reference drops the queue is freed. If a queue is freed
while there is still activity on behalf of the queue, the activities that are ongoing are finished, all requests
that are not started are discarded and all values and error states are discarded. The queue and associated
resources are thereafter freed.
          </para>
          <para>
There is a pool of 20 threads that are shared among all async_queues on the system. Thus, the count of threads given for
the queue is a maximum and does not guarantee that this quantity of threads be used in reality. If no thread is available
in the pool, i.e. other async queues have exhausted the entire pool, the thread making the request ends up executing the
item synchronously. One should take this possibility into account when deciding transaction boundaries, otherwise this is
transparent and the calling thread still gets a request handle and can later check for its completion.
          </para>
          <para>
Queues take procedures and argument lists instead of texts of SQL statements in order to save the time of compiling the text.
It is desirable for best performance to supply the name of the procedure in its full form, with full qualification and matching case.
          </para>
          <para>
Consider the following code samples:
          </para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
create table aqi (n int);

-- The worker procedure. Insert one row and commit.

create procedure INS1 (in n int)
{
  --dbg_obj_print ('ins1 ', n);
  insert into AQI (N) values (n);
  commit work;
  return '22';
}

create procedure taq1 (in x int, in thrs int := 1)
{
  declare aq, res, err any;
  declare n int;
  aq := async_queue (thrs);
  for (n:= 0; n < x; n:=n+1)
    {
      res := aq_request (aq, 'DB.DBA.INS1', vector (n));
    }
  return (aq_wait (aq, res, 1, err));
}


-- This procedure makes a queue with a given number of worker threads, then makes a set of requests and waits for the result
of the last one. Note that this is not necessarily the last to complete if there are multiple threads serving the queue.
]]></programlisting>
                <sect2 id="synchronization">
                        <title>Synchronization</title>
                        <para>
It is possible to add requests to a queue at all times. It is also possible to check for the result of any request made so far,
by either blocking to wait for it or just checking its status.
                        </para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
aq_wait (in aq any, in req_no int, in block int, out err any) returns any
]]></programlisting>
                        <para>
The aq_wait function takes the queue, a request number returned by aq_request, a blocking flag and an output parameter for
the error state.
                        </para>
                        <para>
If there was no error, the error state is set to 0. If the procedure was undefined, the error state is set to 2.
If there was a SQL state signalled from the procedure called on the worker thread, the error state is set to an array
of three elements: The integer 3, the SQL state string and the text of the message. If aq_wait is terminated by an external event,
then an error indicating this is signalled and the state waited for is lost. This can only happen when all transactions are
killed by shutdown or going to a single user state.
                        </para>
                        <para>
If the blocking flag was zero and the request was not complete, then the error output parameter is set to 1 and 1 is returned.
                        </para>
                        <para>
Once aq_wait has retrieved a state, the state is no longer retained in the queue.
                        </para>
                        <para>
The aq_wait_all function allows waiting for all activity to complete but discards individual return states. If some of running activities is terminated by sql error, this error will be raised in the thread executing aq_wait_all function call. 
                        </para>
                        <para>
Note that it is possible to get a deadlock between the requesting thread and a worker thread and that this deadlock
cannot be detected by the database engine since this does not involve a cycle in database locks themselves. Thus,
aq_wait signals an error if the thread calling it holds database locks. Manually committing or rolling back before
calling aq_wait is necessary if the thread can belong to a transaction that holds locks.
                        </para>
                        <para>
Thus, it is most practical to explicitly commit all work on the requesting thread before calling aq_wait or aq_wait_all.
                        </para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure taq_all (in x int, in thrs int := 1)
{
  declare aq, res, err any;
  declare n int;
  aq := async_queue (thrs);
  for (n:= 0; n < x; n:=n+1)
    {
      res := aq_request (aq, 'DB.DBA.INS1', vector (n));
    }
  aq_wait_all (aq);
}


-- This procedure is guaranteed to wait for all requests to be completed but will discard individual error states.
]]></programlisting>
                </sect2>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<sect1 id="PERFTIPS">
		<title>Performance Tips</title>
		<sect2 id="remember">
			<title>Remember the following:</title>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Reference parameters (inout and out) are faster then value parameters (in).</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Use cursors and positioned delete/update (where current of) for read-modify transactions instead of a select .. into and searched update.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Make an EXCLUSIVE read in read-modify transactions.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>When using ORDER BY and wishing to use a particular index, specify ALL
key parts of the index, including those that have a &apos;=&apos; condition. If you
want to have descending order using an index, specify DESC on ALL key parts.
</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<sect1 id="PROCEDURES_TRANSACTIONS">
		<title>Procedures and Transactions</title>
		<para>
A procedure call executed by a client is just like any other SQL
statement. It executes in the context of the client&apos;s active transaction.
If the connection is in autocommit mode the transaction is automatically
committed if the procedure returns successfully and rolled back if
the procedure returns with an error. If the connection is in manual
commit mode, a possible procedure error has no effect on the client&apos;s
transaction, unless the error is a transaction error, e.g. timeout
or deadlock.
</para>

		<para>
For best performance, we recommend using procedures in autocommit
mode. In this way, a single client-server exchange will suffice to carry
out the whole transaction. This will also conveniently roll back the
transaction if the procedure exited as a result of an unhandled SQLSTATE
or a &apos;not found&apos; condition.
</para>
		<para>
Procedures can commit or rollback transactions using commit work and rollback work statements.
</para>
	</sect1>
	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<!-- ======================================== -->

  &twopc;

	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<!-- ======================================== -->
	<sect1 id="TRIGGERS">
		<title>Triggers</title>

  <para>A trigger is a procedure body associated with a table and an event.
  A trigger can take effect before, after or instead of the event on the subject
  table.   Several before, after or instead of triggers may exist for a given event
  on a given table, which can be fired in a specified order. </para>
			<para>Triggers are useful for enforcing integrity rules, maintaining the
validity of data computed from other data, accumulating history data etc.
</para>
			<para>
A trigger body has no arguments in the sense a procedure does. A trigger
body implicitly sees the columns of the subject table as read-only
parameters. An update trigger may see both the new and old values of
the row of the subject table. These are differentiated by correlation
names in the REFERENCING clause.
</para>
			<para>
Triggers are capable of cascading; the code of a trigger may cause
another trigger to be activated. This may lead to non-terminating
recursion in some cases. Triggers may be turned off either inside a
compound statement or inside a connection with the SET TRIGGERS OFF
statement.</para>
			<para>
An update trigger may have a set of sensitive columns whose update will
cause the trigger code to be run. Update of non-sensitive columns will
not invoke the trigger. If no column list is specified any update will
invoke the trigger.
</para>
		<sect2 id="createtrigger"><title>The CREATE TRIGGER statement</title>

  <para>Triggers can be defined to act upon a table or column and fire upon:</para>

  <simplelist>
    <member>UPDATE</member>
    <member>INSERT</member>
    <member>DELETE</member>
  </simplelist>

  <para>at the following times during the operation on a table or column:</para>

  <simplelist>
    <member>BEFORE</member>
    <member>AFTER</member>
    <member>INSTEAD OF</member>
  </simplelist>

  <para>Triggers have a unique name which is qualified by the current catalog
  and owner.  The trigger name is only really relevant for the
  purposes of dropping triggers.  Triggers operate on a table or column which
  must be adequately qualified.</para>

  <para>The trigger body has read-only access to the values of the data
  manipulation operation that triggered the trigger.  In the case of an update
  statement it has access to both old and new values for each effected column.
  These values cannot be changed directly.  If the trigger is to influence any
  data in a table, even from the current operation, it must be achieved by
  another SQL statement.   The REFERENCING clause allows specifying a
  correlation name for new and old values of columns.  By default, the new
  values are seen under the column names without a correlation name.  If old
  values of updated columns are needed, the REFERENCING OLD AS &lt;alias&gt;
  will make &lt;alias&gt;.&lt;column&gt; refer to the old value.</para>

  <para>Triggers defined to make further operations within the same or other
  table may fire further triggers, or even the same trigger again.  Care must be
  taken to understand the implications of this and when triggers cane be
  allowed to continue firing after the current trigger.  For example, an after update
  trigger that makes a further update to the same table will fire the same trigger
  again and may continue looping in this way endlessly.
  The <computeroutput>SET TRIGGER</computeroutput>  statement can be
  issued to control this:</para>

  <simplelist>
    <member>SET TRIGGERS on; -- (default state) further triggers within this transaction are allowed to fire.</member>
    <member>SET TRIGGERS off; -- further triggers within this transaction are disabled.</member>
  </simplelist>

  <para>A table may have more than one trigger.  Their execution order can be
  specified  using the ORDER clause.  Each trigger gets an order number, triggers
  are called starting at the lowest order number in ascending order.</para>

  <para>Syntax:</para>

			<programlisting>
CREATE TRIGGER NAME action_time event ON q_table_name
  opt_order opt_old_ref trig_action

action_time
	: BEFORE
	| AFTER

event
	: INSERT
	| UPDATE opt_column_commalist
	| DELETE

opt_order
	| ORDER INTNUM

opt_old_ref
	| REFERENCING old_commalist

trig_action
	: compound_statement

old_commalist
	: old_alias
	| old_commalist &apos;,&apos; old_alias

old_alias
	: OLD AS NAME
	| NEW AS NAME
</programlisting>

<example id="ex_createtrigger"><title>Creating a simple trigger</title>

<para>This trigger is a simple example of one that would cause an
endless loop if further triggering were not disabled.</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
create trigger update_mydate after
   update on mytable referencing old as O, new as N
{
  set triggers off;
  update mytable
    set
      previousdate = O.mydate,
      mydate=now()
    where id=N.id;
}
;
]]></programlisting>
<para>The trigger makes aliases for the values of the column that are part of
the SQL manipulation transaction that will be in progress, hence the values of the
columns can be accessed as "O.column" and "N.column" for old and new values respectively.</para>
<para>The set statement is scope  to the procedure or trigger body where it occurs, plus procedures called from there  , thus when the trigger
finishes no other triggers are effected by it.</para>
</example>

<example id="ex_createtriggerinsteadof"><title>Creating a simple trigger using INSTEAD OF</title>

<para>This trigger example will show how INSTEAD OF can be used to intercept
the values of an insert statement and re-write it.  In this case the purpose is
to deliberately truncate VARCHAR inserts to prevent an error if the
data type bounds are exceeded:</para>

<para>First we create a test table with a 30 character limitation in one of the columns:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
SQL>create table test_trunc (
      id integer not null primary key,
      txt varchar (30)
      )
    ;

Done. -- 10 msec.
]]></programlisting>

<para>Then we attempt to insert 33 characters into it with the following results:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
SQL>insert into test_trunc (id, txt)
      values (1, 'aaaaaaaaaabbbbbbbbbbccccccccccxxx');

*** Error 22026: [Virtuoso ODBC Driver][Virtuoso Server]SR319: Max column length (30) of column [txt] exceeded
]]></programlisting>

<para>Now we make a trigger to fire instead of insert statements that can
perform some custom error correction, in this case we simply want to chop-off
any extra characters that will cause an insert to fail.</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
SQL>create trigger test_trunc_it
      instead of insert on test_trunc
        referencing new as N
    {
      set triggers off; -- we do not want this looping...
      insert into test_trunc (id, txt) values (N.id, left(N.txt, 30));
    }
    ;

Done. -- 10 msec.
]]></programlisting>

<para>We perform the same test insert, now without errors:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
SQL>insert into test_trunc (id, txt)
  values (1, 'aaaaaaaaaabbbbbbbbbbccccccccccxxx');

Done. -- 10 msec.
]]></programlisting>

<para>And to see what we have in the database, a quick select:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
SQL> select * from test_trunc;
id                txt
INTEGER NOT NULL  VARCHAR
______________________________________________________

1                 aaaaaaaaaabbbbbbbbbbcccccccccc

1 Rows. -- 20 msec.
]]></programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>

		<!-- ~ # ==== ~ ==== # ~ -->
	<sect2 id="triggers_on_views">
		<title>Triggers on Views</title>
		<para>In virtuoso you can create a trigger on a view. To accomplish this there is only one condition: The first trigger for a given type of event (INSERT/DELETE/UPDATE)
		must be an INSTEAD OF trigger. After such a trigger  is defined then any type of triggers (AFTER/BEFORE) can be added.</para>
  <example id="ex_createtriggeronview"><title>Creating a trigger on view</title>

  <para>We will make two tables and an union view for them. Then we will create a trigger which inserts a new record in one of the tables according to values.</para>

  <para>First lets create the tables and the view.</para>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[
create table first_table(
  id integer not null primary key,
  txt varchar
);

create table second_table(
  id integer not null primary key,
  txt varchar
);

create view all_tables (id,from_table,txt)
as select id,'first',txt from first_table
union all
select id,'second',txt from second_table;]]></programlisting>

  <para>Now lets create a trigger instead of insert for the view and insert some data.</para>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[
create trigger insert_all_tables
  instead of insert on all_tables referencing new as N{
    if(N.from_table = 'first' or N.from_table = 'all')
      insert into first_table (id,txt) values(N.id,N.txt);

    if(N.from_table = 'second' or N.from_table = 'all')
      insert into second_table (id,txt) values(N.id,N.txt);
  };

  insert into all_tables (id,from_table,txt) values (1,'first','into first');
  insert into all_tables (id,from_table,txt) values (2,'second','into second');
  insert into all_tables (id,from_table,txt) values (3,'all','into all');

  select * from all_tables;

  id       from_table  txt
  INTEGER  VARCHAR  VARCHAR
  _______________________________________________________________________________

  1        first    into first
  3        first    into all
  2        second   into second
  3        second   into all
]]></programlisting>
  </example>
  <para>You can see that the trigger inserted the data in the two tables according the value of from_table.</para>

	</sect2>
		<!-- ~ # ==== ~ ==== # ~ -->
		<sect2 id="droptrigger">
			<title>The DROP TRIGGER statement</title>
			<programlisting>
DROP TRIGGER qualified_name
</programlisting>
			<para>This drops a trigger of the given name. The name may optionally have
a qualifier and owner, in which case these should be the qualifier and
owner of the subject table of the trigger.  Identical trigger
names may exist for identically named tables in different namespaces.
</para>
		</sect2>
		<!-- ~ # ==== ~ ==== # ~ -->
	<sect2 id="triggers_vdb">
		<title>Triggers and Virtual Database</title>
		<para>
Triggers may be defined on tables residing on remote databases. The
semantic of triggers is identical but will of course only take place when
the manipulation takes place through the Virtuoso defining the triggers.
Trigger bodies may reference remote tables just as any other procedure
bodies can. Note that triggers can be used for replication, i.e. one may
define a local change to be mirrored to a remote table using a trigger.
</para>
		<para>
Consider an application with a warehouse supplying orders. There is a
total value of all orders kept at the warehouse level and there is the
total value of all order lines kept at the order level. When an order
line is added, both the order value and consequently the total order
value are updates. These values are maintained for insert, update and
delete of order line. On the other have, when an order is deleted,
all corresponding order lines must be deleted.
</para>
		<para>
These rules are maintained with the below set of triggers.
</para>
		<screen>
drop table T_WAREHOUSE;

drop table T_ORDER;

drop table T_ORDER_LINE;

create table T_WAREHOUSE (W_ID integer default 1,
			  W_ORDER_VALUE float default 0,
			  W_DATA varchar,
			  primary key (W_ID));

create table T_ORDER (O_ID integer not null primary key, O_C_ID integer,
		      O_W_ID integer default 1,
		      O_VALUE numeric default 0,
		      O_MODIFIED datetime);

create table T_ORDER_LINE (OL_O_ID integer,
			   OL_I_ID integer,
			   OL_QTY integer,
			   OL_MODIFIED timestamp,
			   OL_I_PRICE float default 1,
			   primary key (OL_O_ID, OL_I_ID));

create index OL_I_ID on T_ORDER_LINE (OL_I_ID);

create trigger AMT_INS after insert on T_ORDER_LINE
{
  update T_ORDER
    set O_VALUE = O_VALUE + OL_QTY * OL_I_PRICE
    where O_ID = OL_O_ID;
}

create trigger AMT_DEL after delete on T_ORDER_LINE
{
  update T_ORDER
    set O_VALUE = O_VALUE - OL_QTY * OL_I_PRICE
    where O_ID = OL_O_ID;
}

create trigger AMT before update on T_ORDER_LINE referencing old as O
{
  update T_ORDER
    set O_VALUE = O_VALUE - O.OL_QTY * O.OL_I_PRICE + OL_QTY * OL_I_PRICE
    where O_ID = OL_O_ID;
}

create trigger W_VALUE before update (O_VALUE) on T_ORDER
     referencing old as O, new as N
{
  update T_WAREHOUSE
    set W_ORDER_VALUE = W_ORDER_VALUE - O.O_VALUE + N.O_VALUE
    where W_ID = O.O_W_ID;
}

create trigger O_DEL_OL after delete on T_ORDER order 2
{
  set triggers off;
  delete from T_ORDER_LINE where OL_O_ID = O_ID;
}

create trigger O_DEL_W  after delete on T_ORDER order 1
{
  update T_WAREHOUSE
    set W_ORDER_VALUE = W_ORDER_VALUE - O_VALUE
    where W_ID = O_W_ID;
}

create procedure ol_reprice_1 (in i_id integer, in i_price float)
{
  declare id integer;
  declare cr cursor for
    select OL_I_ID from T_ORDER_LINE;
  whenever not found goto done;
  open cr;
  while (1) {
    fetch cr into id;
    if (id = i_id)
      update T_ORDER_LINE set OL_I_PRICE = i_price where current of cr;
  }
 done:
  return;
}

create procedure ol_reprice_2 (in i_id integer, in i_price float)
{
  declare id integer;
  declare cr cursor for
    select OL_I_ID from T_ORDER_LINE order by OL_I_ID;
  whenever not found goto done;
  open cr;
  while (1) {
    fetch cr into id;
    if (id = i_id)
      update T_ORDER_LINE set OL_I_PRICE = i_price where current of cr;
  }
 done:
  return;
}

create procedure ol_del_i_id_2 (in i_id integer)
{
  declare id integer;
  declare cr cursor for
    select OL_I_ID from T_ORDER_LINE order by OL_I_ID;
  whenever not found goto done;
  open cr;
  while (1) {
    fetch cr into id;
    if (id = i_id)
      delete from T_ORDER_LINE where current of cr;
  }
 done:
  return;
}
</screen>
		<note>
			<title>Compatibility:</title>
			<para>Virtuoso triggers are modeled after SQL 3.  Omitted are the FOR EACH
STATEMENT and related OLD  TABLE AS phrases as well as the WHEN in the
trigger body.  The implementation is otherwise complete.
</para>
		</note>
</sect2>
</sect1>
		<!-- ~ # ==== ~ ==== # ~ -->
<sect1 id="charescaping">
<title>Character Escaping</title>

<para>
The C style escape character can be used to include  special characters inside literals.  The backslash character, '\', followed by an octal character code  or
a special character  provides a notation for  characters that are normally not typable in a string literal such as tab or crlf.
Backslash support can be turned on or off at the statement level, the connection level or server default level.
</para>

<sect2 id="backslashstmt">
<title>Statement Level</title>
	<para>
If you want to activate or deactivate the backslash support in a
stored procedure you can use the following two special comments (on a separate line) :
</para>
<programlisting>--no_c_escapes+</programlisting>

<para>
turns the backslash escaping support off (insert into x values ('c:\test') will result in 'c:\test' in the column
</para>

<programlisting>--no_c_escapes-</programlisting>
<para>
turns the backslash escaping support on. (same as above will insert 'c:test' in the column.)
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="backslashconlevel">
<title>Connection Level</title>

<para>The switch SET SQL_NO_CHAR_C_ESCAPE can be set to 'on' or 'off' to respectively turn backslash support on or off
for the current connection</para>
<para>There is an ODBC connection attribute that can be set for the same effect in an ODBC connection.
SQLGetConnectAttr/SQLSetConnectAttr with option ID of 5002 takes values 0 or 1 to facilitate this
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="backslashserver">
<title>Server Default</title>

<para>SQL_NO_CHAR_C_ESCAPE=0/1 can be set in the &quot;Client&quot;
section of the virtuoso.ini file to set the connection default backslash handling behavior.  The default value is 0.
</para>
</sect2>

<note><title>Note</title>
<para>When a 'create procedure' is executed and that mode is &quot;ON&quot; the
procedure is stored in such a way that it will preserve the setting for
it's text no matter what the current default is.
</para></note>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="PLSCROLLCRSRS">
<title>Virtuoso/PL Scrollable Cursors</title>

<para>
Virtuoso/PL supports scrollable cursors, providing functionality similar to the ODBC scrollable cursor support.
Scrollable Cursor support extends the basic (forward-only) syntax of DECLARE CURSOR and FETCH to support
the various fetch directions &amp; cursor modes.  The Virtuoso/PL scrollable cursors always operate with a
rowset size equal to 1.  The keyset size (where applicable) is as per the default.
</para>
<note><title>Note:</title>
<para>If a Virtuoso/PL cursor is declared forward only it supports only FETCH .. NEXT scroll direction.
The FETCH defaults its direction to NEXT (if omitted) so this is how the syntax
extensions to DECLARE CURSOR &amp; FETCH interoperate with the forward-only cursors syntax.
</para>
</note>

<sect2 id="PLSCROLLDECLARE">
<title>Declaring a Scrollable Cursor</title>
<para>
Virtuoso/PL cursor types are specified at declaration time.  Unlike the forward-only cursor declaration
the scrollable cursor DECLARE CURSOR causes some actions (cursor statement preparation &amp; cursor variable
assignment).  The cursor variable&apos;s value can not be copied,
it should be passed only by reference in procedure calls.
Scrollable cursors have an appropriate destructor, which will close the cursor when the cursor variable goes out of scope.
Variables in the surrounding context are referenced similarly to the forward-only cursor.
</para>
<note><title>Note:</title>
<para>Some types of statements do not allow other cursor types than static.
For example SELECT DISTINCT will always result in a static cursor, ignoring the cursor declared type.
</para>
</note>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="PLSCROLLOPEN">
<title>Opening a Scrollable Cursor</title>
<para>
The OPEN on a scrollable cursor opens the cursor and sets it&apos;s position right before the first resultset row.
So before taking the bookmark value at least one FETCH should be issued.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="PLSCROLLFETCH">
<title>Fetching Data From a Scrollable Cursor</title>
<para>
The FETCH on a scrollable cursor allows specification of a direction.  If there is no more data
in the specified fetch direction this causes the NOT FOUND exception to be raised, as with the
forward-only cursors.  In addition to that if the row on which the cursor is about to position has been
deleted and the isolation level &amp; cursor type allows detecting that, then the exception
SQLSTATE &apos;HY109&apos; (Row deleted) is raised.
</para>
<para>
Positioning on a bookmark is done the following way:
</para>
<para>
A bookmark value should be retrieved using the <link linkend="fn_bookmark">bookmark() function</link>.
The value returned by that function can be stored, copied and retrieved.
This value can also survive a cursor close and reopen, even between transactions.
How the cursor will behave if a bookmark from a cursor with different select statement or scroll
type is used for positioning is undefined and should be avoided.  On some
occasions it may signal an error, on others it will position on a wrong or non-existing row.
As a general rule bookmark values should be used only on the cursor from which  they are generated.
</para>
<para>
The cursor should be in opened state.  Now a FETCH .. BOOKMARK bm_value INTO ... can be issued with
the bookmark variable.
</para>
<para>
Bookmarks can serve for persisting the cursor position in an VSP context.  One can imagine a VSP page
which on it&apos;s first go will execute a cursor and will show the first so-many rows.
Then it can retrieve the bookmark value of the last displayed row, persist it somehow
(for example as an HTTP session variable), then close the cursor and exit.
On each subsequent hit it will open again the same cursor, position on the bookmark
persisted and return the next, previous, first or last so-many rows.
</para>
<!-- &bookmark; -->
</sect2>
<sect2 id="PLSCROLLEXAMPLES">
<title>Virtuoso/PL Scrollable Cursor Examples</title>
<example>
<title>Procedure using scrollable cursor to read the keys in batches of 20</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure READ_KEYS_NEXT_20 (in mask varchar, inout bm any) returns integer
{
  --- This procedure reads the next 20 table names based on a bookmark value.
  declare cr static cursor for
      select distinct KEY_TABLE
        from DB.DBA.SYS_KEYS
	where
	  KEY_IS_MAIN = 1 and
	  KEY_MIGRATE_TO is NULL and
	  KEY_TABLE like mask;
  declare table_name varchar;
  declare inx integer;

  inx := 1;

  -- no 'Row Deleted' (HY109) handling as the static cursors doesn't show the deleted rows.
  whenever not found goto done;
  open cr;

  -- positions on the bookmark or on the first if it is null
  -- and fetches the value into table_name
  if (bm is not null)
    {
      fetch cr bookmark bm into table_name;
      -- note that the value from fetch bookmark is omitted
      fetch cr next into table_name;
    }
  else
    fetch cr first into table_name;

  -- fetches the next 20 rows (or less)
  while (inx < 20)
    {
      result (table_name);
      inx := inx + 1;
      fetch cr next into table_name;
    }

  -- 20 rows were fetched - get the bookmark of the last row fetched
  bm := bookmark (cr);
  close cr;
  return;

done:

  -- no more rows - set the bookmark to NULL
  close cr;
  bm := NULL;
};


create procedure READ_KEYS (in mask varchar)
{
  -- the main function (mask is a mask to be applied over the select

  declare table_name varchar;
  declare bm any;

  -- it'll return a resultset with a single column
  result_names (table_name);

  -- sets the bookmark to empty
  bm := NULL;

  while (1)
    {
       READ_KEYS_NEXT_20 (mask, bm);

       -- that's the flag for no more rows
       if (bm is NULL)
         return;
    }
};

READ_KEYS ('%');
]]></programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="PLFORWARDONLYCR">
<title>FORWARD-ONLY (traditional cursor statement) Example</title>
<example>
<title>Procedure using forward only cursor</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure TEST_FW()
{
  declare cr cursor for select KEY_ID from DB.DBA.SYS_KEYS;
  declare inx, data integer;
  inx := 0;

  whenever not found goto done;
  open cr;
  while (1)
    {
      fetch cr into data;
      inx := inx + 1;
    }
done:
  close cr;
  result_names (data);
  result (inx);
};
TEST_FW();
]]></programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="PLDYNAMICCR">
<title>DYNAMIC (traditional cursor statement) Example</title>
<example>
<title>Procedure using dynamic cursor</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure TEST_DYNAMIC ()
{
  declare cr dynamic cursor for select KEY_ID from DB.DBA.SYS_KEYS;
  declare inx, data integer;
  inx := 0;

  whenever not found goto done;
  open cr;
  while (1)
    {
      fetch cr into data;
      inx := inx + 1;
    }
done:
  close cr;
  result_names (data);
  result (inx);
};
TEST_DYNAMIC ();
]]></programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="PLKEYSETCR">
<title>KEYSET (traditional cursor statement) Example</title>
<example>
<title>Procedure using keyset cursor</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure TEST_KEYSET ()
{
  declare cr keyset cursor for select KEY_ID from DB.DBA.SYS_KEYS;
  declare inx, data integer;
  inx := 0;

  whenever not found goto done;
  open cr;
  while (1)
    {
      fetch cr into data;
      inx := inx + 1;
    }
done:
  close cr;
  result_names (data);
  result (inx);
};
TEST_KEYSET ();
]]></programlisting>
</example>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="plmodules"><title>Virtuoso PL Modules</title>

<para>
Modules are packages of procedures which compile together.  Procedure names in
module definitions are not fully qualified names, but consist only of a single
identifier that it is appended to the name of the module (which is a 3-part
name) to make the 4-part module procedure name.
</para>
<para>
Module procedures do not appear in SQLProcedures output.  Module names are in
the same domain as the procedure names, so it is not possible to have
a procedure with the same name as an existing module.
</para>

<sect2 id="plmodsyntax"><title>Syntax</title>
<programlisting>
CREATE MODULE
  m_name
{
  [PROCEDURE|FUNCTION] p_name1 (...) { ...};
  [PROCEDURE|FUNCTION] p_name2 (...) { ...};
  ...
  [PROCEDURE|FUNCTION] p_nameN (...) { ...};
}
</programlisting>
<programlisting>
DROP MODULE m_name;
</programlisting>
</sect2>

<example id="ex_plmod2"><title>Procedure Modules</title>
<programlisting>
create module
  DB.DBA.MOD
{
  function MOD1 () returns varchar {
    return ('MOD1');
  };

  procedure MOD2 () {
    return concat (MOD1(), 'MOD2');
  };
};
</programlisting>
<para>
This example creates a module, MOD, with 2 procedures: MOD1 &amp; MOD2.
Their fully-qualified names are DB.DBA.MOD.MOD1 and DB.DBA.MOD.MOD2.
</para>
<para>
Note the call to MOD1 in MOD2 - it is not fully qualified, but it resolves to
the module procedure MOD1, instead of any procedure external to the module.
</para>
</example>
<para>
A single part procedure name in a call inside a module is first matched against procedures defined in the module. 
If the above example were  executed by DBA (in the DB qualifier),
then the  below  statements are equivalent:
</para>

<programlisting>
select DB.DBA.MOD.MOD1()
select DB..MOD.MOD1()
</programlisting>
<para>
The statement:
</para>
<programlisting>
select MOD.MOD1()
</programlisting>
<para>
will result in calling the DB.DBA.MOD.MOD1() only if a function DB.MOD.MOD1
does not exist.  If it exists, it will be preferred over DB.DBA.MOD.MOD1
when using this notation.
</para>

<sect2 id="plmodsecurity"><title>Security</title>
<para>
Module procedures can be granted to users.  Modules can also be granted to
users.  Granting execute to a module is equivalent to granting execute for
all of the module's procedures.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="handlingplcondit"><title>Handling Conditions In Virtuoso/PL Procedures</title>

  <para>
Condition handlers determine the behavior of a Virtuoso/PL procedure when a
condition occurs.  You can declare one or more condition handlers in your Virtuoso/PL
procedure for general SQL conditions or specific SQLSTATE values.
</para>
  <para>
If a statement in your procedure raises an SQLEXCEPTION condition and you declared
a handler for the specific SQLSTATE or SQLEXCEPTION condition the server passes control
to that handler.
</para>
  <para>
If a statement in your Virtuoso/PL procedure raises an SQLEXCEPTION condition,
and you have not declared a handler for the specific SQLSTATE or the
SQLEXCEPTION condition, the server passes the exception to the calling procedure (if any).
If the procedure call is at the top-level, then the exception is signalled to the calling
client.
</para>
  <para>
Handlers are active only for the duration of the enclosing compound statement.  When an exception
is thrown outside the handler's scope then this handler is never called.
</para>

<sect2 id="declarecondit"><title>Declaring Condition Handlers</title>

  <para>
The general form of handler declaration is:
</para>
<programlisting>
DECLARE &lt;handler_type&gt; HANDLER FOR
	&lt;condition&gt; [, &lt;condition [...]]
	&lt;sql_procedure_statement&gt;;
</programlisting>
  <para>
For compatibility handlers can be declared also as :
</para>
  <programlisting>
WHENEVER &lt;condition&gt; [GOTO &lt;label&gt;|DEFAULT];
</programlisting>
  <para>
When Virtuoso raises a condition that matches the &lt;condition&gt;, the &lt;sql_procedure_statement&gt;
gets executed and when (and if) it finishes the execution continues according to the &lt;handler_type&gt;.
</para>

<programlisting>
&lt;handler_type&gt;
</programlisting>

  <para>
<emphasis>CONTINUE</emphasis> - Specifies that after &lt;sql_procedure_statement&gt; completes,
execution continues with the statement after the statement which caused the error.
</para>

  <para>
<emphasis>EXIT</emphasis> - Specifies that after &lt;sql_procedure_statement&gt; completes,
execution continues after the end of the compound statement that contains the declaration of the handler. 
</para>

  <programlisting>
&lt;condition&gt;
</programlisting>

  <para>
<emphasis>NOT FOUND</emphasis> - Identifies any condition that results in SQL STATE = SQL_NO_DATA_FOUND (+100)
</para>
  <para>
<emphasis>SQLEXCEPTION</emphasis> - Identifies all character SQL STATEs excluding ones starting with '01', '02' and '00'
</para>
  <para>
<emphasis>SQLWARNING</emphasis> - Identifies character SQL STATEs starting with '01'.
This is a shortcut for SQLSTATE '01*'
</para>
  <para>
<emphasis>SQLSTATE [VALUE] '&lt;sql_state_mask&gt;'</emphasis> - Identifies character SQL STATEs.
The &lt;sql_state_mask&gt; can be a full 5 character value or 0-4 characters  followed by an '*'.
When a '*' is present then any SQL STATE signal led which starts with the same characters as
the &lt;sql_state_mask&gt; before the '*' will cause that handler to execute.
For example the exception with SQL state '42S22' will match all the following
</para>

<programlisting>
SQLSTATE &lt;conditions&gt; :
SQLSTATE '*' SQLSTATE '42*'
SQLSTATE '42S22'
</programlisting>

<note><title>Note:</title>
<para>Handler's call priority is determined by the number of matching characters in this mask.</para>
</note>

<programlisting>
&lt;sql_procedure_statement&gt;
</programlisting>

  <para>
This can be any allowed Virtuoso/PL statement as well as an compound statement.  This statement is
executed in the same procedure context  as the procedure body itself, so any labels and variables in the
procedure body can be used and RETURN causes the procedure to end.  No handler is active while the
&lt;sql_procedure_statement&gt; is executed.  So any exception raised is passed directly to the procedure
caller.  The &lt;sql_procedure_statement&gt; can be empty resulting in the &lt;handler_type&gt; action being
taken right after setting the __SQL_STATE &amp; __SQL_MESSAGE variables.
</para>
  <para>
When multiple active handlers &lt;condition&gt;s match the exception being raised Virtuoso chooses the closest to the
statement raised the exception that has a largest call priority.
This means that if an exception is there are two handlers with condition SQLSTATE '4*' and SQLSTATE '42*'
and an exception with SQL STATE '42S22' is raised the handler with &lt;condition&gt; '42*' will be called.
</para>

<programlisting>
WHENEVER &lt;condition&gt; GOTO &lt;label&gt;
</programlisting>
<para>is an equivalent of:</para>
<programlisting>
DECLARE EXIT HANDLER FOR &lt;condition&gt; GOTO label.
</programlisting>
<programlisting>
WHENEVER &lt;condition&gt; DEFAULT
</programlisting>
<para>is equivalent of:</para>
<programlisting>
DECLARE EXIT HANDLER FOR &lt;condition&gt; RESIGNAL;
</programlisting>

  <para>
The following examples demonstrate simple common handlers:
</para>

  <para>
<emphasis>CONTINUE handler:</emphasis> The handler assigns a value of 1 to a local variable at_end when a NOT FOUND condition
is raised.  The execution then continues with the statement after the signal.
</para>

  <programlisting>
create procedure test1 ()
{
  declare at_end integer;

  at_end := 0;
  declare continue handler for NOT FOUND at_end := 1;

  result_names (at_end);

  result (at_end);
  signal (100);
  result (at_end);
}
</programlisting>

  <para>
When this procedure gets executed it returns the following result set :
</para>

  <screen>
0
1
</screen>

  <para>
<emphasis>EXIT handler:</emphasis> The handler assigns a value of 2 to a local variable at_end when a NOT_FOUND condition is raised.
The execution then continues with the statement after the compound statement containing the signal.
</para>

  <programlisting>
create procedure test2 ()
{
  declare at_end integer;

  result_names (at_end);

  at_end := 0;
  declare exit handler for NOT FOUND at_end := 1;

    {
      result (at_end);
      signal (100);
      result (3);
    }
  result (at_end);
}
</programlisting>

  <para>
When this procedure gets executed it returns the following result set :
</para>
  <screen>
0
1
</screen>

  <programlisting>
__SQL_STATE and __SQL_MESSAGE variables.
</programlisting>

<para>
All Virtuoso/PL procedure have  two variables implicitly declared :
</para>

<programlisting>
declare __SQL_STATE any;
declare __SQL_MESSAGE varchar;
</programlisting>

  <para>
Initially they are set to 0.
</para>

  <para>
When an exception is raised these variables are set as follows :
</para>

  <programlisting>
__SQL_STATE gets the SQL STATE (character string or integer 100 for NOT FOUND)
__SQL_MESSAGE gets the SQL MESSAGE (character) or NULL if no message.
</programlisting>

  <para>
Their values are preserved until the next exception overwrites them.
</para>

  <programlisting>
RESIGNAL statement

Syntax :
RESIGNAL [ '&lt;new_sql_state&gt;' ]

RESIGNAL  is a shortcut for    signal (__SQL_STATE, __SQL_MESSAGE)
RESIGNAL '&lt;new_sql_state&gt;' is a shortcut for     signal ('&lt;new_sql_state&gt;', __SQL_MESSAGE);
</programlisting>

  <para>
This statement resignals the current exception to the caller of the procedure.
</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="stacktracesql"><title>Stack Trace Reporting On Sql Error Generation</title>
  <para>
When an exception occurs the Virtuoso server has the ability to provide information
about the procedure call stack.  It appends the call stack information to the
error message text.  There are also line numbers besides each level of the call stack
which are a Virtuoso/PL procedure.  The line numbers mark the beginning of the
innermost compound statement.
</para>
  <para>
The call stack reporting mode is controlled by the "CallstackOnException" option
in the <link linkend="parameters"><emphasis>Parameters</emphasis> section of the Virtuoso INI file</link>.
</para>
  <para>
This parameter takes the following values:
</para>
  <simplelist>
    <member>0 (default) - Call stack reporting disabled.</member>
    <member>1 - Call stack is reported but does not include values of arguments.</member>
    <member>2 - Call stack is reported and contains all available information.</member>
  </simplelist>
<para>
Call stack reporting can be a security hole because it can demonstrate internal logic of the system to the end user;
this is especially important for dynamic web pages.
Mode 2 is especially insecure because it may print values of function arguments that may contain confidential information.
</para>
<para>
Some client applications are unable to handle long error messages properly.
Client-side APIs for ODBC and similar protocols assume that client should
allocate a buffer for error message string and then ask the API to save
the message string to the specified buffer of the specified size. Not all
client applications work properly if a message does not fit in the buffer.
If an client application you use reports an empty string instead of error
message or displays a message like 'Error message is too long' then you may
wish to decrease the value of the "CallstackOnException" option to keep
messages shorter.
</para>
</sect2></sect1>

&pldebugger;
&rowlevelsecurity;

</chapter>



