<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2014 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->

<sect1 id="uddi"><title>UDDI</title>

<sect2 id="uddiconcepts"><title>Concepts</title>
  <para>
Universal Description, Discovery and Integration (UDDI) is the name of a
web-based service that exposes information about a business or other entities
and its technical interfaces or APIs.  These services are run by UDDI-enabled
servers,  and can be used by any business that wants to make their information
available, as well as anyone who wants to find that information.  There is no
charge for using the basic services of these sites.
</para>
  <para>
By accessing any of the public sites, anyone can search for
information about web services that are made available by or on behalf
of a business.  This provides a mechanism that allows others to
discover what technical programming interfaces are provided for
interacting with a business for such purposes as electronic commerce.
The benefit to the individual business is increased exposure in an
electronic commerce enabled world.
</para>
  <para>
Businesses can register several kinds of simple data to help others
answer questions of &quot;who, what, where and how.&quot; Simple
information about a business - information such as name, business
identifiers (D&amp;B D-U-N-S Number(R), etc.), and contact information
answers the question &quot;Who.&quot;  &quot;What&quot; involves classification
information including industry codes and product classifications,
as well as descriptive information about the services that are
available for electronic interchange.  Answering the question &quot;Where&quot;
involves registering information about the URL or email address (or
other address) through which each type of service may be accessed.
Finally, the question &quot;How&quot; is answered by registering references to
information about specifications that describe how a particular
software package or technical interface functions.  These references
are called '<parameter>tModels</parameter>' in the documentation.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="uddisoap"><title>Dealing with SOAP</title>
  <para>
UDDI API functions are exposed as SOAP v1.1 messages over the HTTP
protocol.  In version 1, the <literal>SOAPAction</literal> HTTP Header
is required.  The value passed in this HTTP Header must be an empty
string that is surrounded by double quotes.
</para>

<example id="ex_uddisoap"><title>UDDI and Soap</title>
<programlisting>
POST /UDDI/inquiry HTTP/1.1
Host: www.foo.com
Content-Type: text/xml
Content-Length: nnnn
SOAPAction: ""

.... body follows ....
</programlisting>
</example>

  <para>
SOAP is used in conjunction with HTTP to provide a simple mechanism for
passing XML messages to UDDI-enabled servers using a standard HTTP-POST
protocol.  Unless specified, all responses will be returned in the normal HTTP
response document.
</para>

<tip><title>See Also:</title>
  <para>
For more information about Virtuoso's SOAP Implementation see the
<link linkend="soap">SOAP Services</link> section.</para></tip>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="uddiapisupport"><title>Supported API Calls</title>
  <para>
The UDDI APIs always return a SOAP entity body which contains messages
as described in UDDI v1 XML Schema  (uddi_1.xsd).
</para>

<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para><emphasis>Authorization API</emphasis> - Used to establish
authentication mechanism (tokens), dropping already established connections.</para>

  <itemizedlist mark="dash">
    <listitem><emphasis>discard_authToken:</emphasis> Used to inform a UDDI
enabled server that a previously provided authentication token is no longer valid.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>get_authToken:</emphasis> Used to request an authentication
token from a UDDI-enabled server.  Authentication tokens are required to use all
other APIs defined in the publishers API.  This function serves as the
program's equivalent of a login request.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>get_registeredInfo:</emphasis> Used to request an
abbreviated synopsis of all information currently managed by a given individual.
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Searching API</emphasis> The publicly accessible queries are:</para>

  <itemizedlist mark="dash">
    <listitem><emphasis>find_binding:</emphasis> Used to locate specific bindings
within a registered <parameter>businessService</parameter>.  Returns a <parameter>bindingDetail</parameter> message.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>find_business:</emphasis> Used to locate information
about one or more businesses .  Returns a <parameter>businessList</parameter> message.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>find_service:</emphasis> Used to locate specific services
within a registered <parameter>businessEntity</parameter>.  Returns a <parameter>serviceList</parameter> message.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>find_tModel:</emphasis> Used to locate one or more <parameter>tModel</parameter>
information structures.  Returns a <parameter>tModelList</parameter> structure.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>get_bindingDetail:</emphasis> Used to get full <parameter>bindingTemplate</parameter>
information suitable for making one or more service requests.  Returns a
<parameter>bindingDetail</parameter> message.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>get_businessDetail:</emphasis> Used to get  full
<parameter>businessEntity</parameter> information for one or more businesses.  Returns a <parameter>businessDetail</parameter>
message.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>get_businessDetailExt:</emphasis> Used to get extended
<parameter>businessEntity</parameter> information.  Returns a <parameter>businessDetailExt</parameter> message.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>get_serviceDetail:</emphasis> Used to get full details
for a given set of registered <parameter>businessService</parameter> data.  Returns a <parameter>serviceDetail</parameter>
message.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>get_tModelDetail:</emphasis> Used to get full details for
a given set of registered <parameter>tModel</parameter> data.  Returns a <parameter>tModelDetail</parameter> message.
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

</listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Repository Manipulation API</emphasis></para>

  <itemizedlist mark="dash">
    <listitem><emphasis>delete_binding:</emphasis> Used to remove an existing <parameter>bindingTemplate</parameter>
from the <parameter>bindingTemplate</parameter>s collection that is part of a specified <parameter>businessService</parameter>
structure.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>delete_business:</emphasis> Used to delete registered <parameter>businessEntity</parameter>
information from the registry.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>delete_service:</emphasis> Used to delete an existing <parameter>businessService</parameter>
from the businessServices collection that is part of a specified <parameter>businessEntity</parameter>.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>delete_tModel:</emphasis> Used to delete registered information about a
<parameter>tModel</parameter>.  If there are any references to a <parameter>tModel</parameter> when this call is made, the <parameter>tModel</parameter>
will be marked deleted instead  of being physically removed.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>save_binding:</emphasis> Used to register new <parameter>bindingTemplate</parameter> information
or update existing <parameter>bindingTemplate</parameter> information.  Use this to control information
about technical capabilities  exposed by a registered business.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>save_business:</emphasis> Used to register new <parameter>businessEntity</parameter> information
or update existing <parameter>businessEntity</parameter> information.  Use this to control the overall
information about the entire  business.  Of all the save APIs this one has the broadest
effect.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>save_service:</emphasis>  Used to register or update complete information
about a <parameter>businessService</parameter> exposed by a specified <parameter>businessEntity</parameter>.
  </listitem>
    <listitem><emphasis>save_tModel:</emphasis>  Used to register or update complete information
about a <parameter>tModel</parameter>.
  </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="uddiauthmech"><title>Authorization Mechanism</title>
  <para>
The Publishers API describes the messages that are used to control the content
contained within  a UDDI-enabled server, and can be used by compliant non-operator
implementations that adhere to the behaviors described in this programmer's reference
specification.
</para>
  <para>
All calls made to UDDI-enabled servers that use the messages defined in the
publisher's API will be transported using SSL encryption.  UDDI-enabled servers
will each provide a service description that exposes a <parameter>bindingTemplate</parameter> that
makes use of HTTPS and SSL to secure the transmission of data.
</para>

<sect3 id="uddiauth"><title>Authentication</title>
  <para>
Each of the calls in the publisher's API that change information at a given
UDDI-enabled server requires the use of an opaque authentication token.  These
tokens are generated by or provided by each UDDI-enabled server independently,
and are passed from the caller to the UDDI-enabled server in the element
named <parameter>authInfo</parameter>.
</para>
  <para>
These tokens are meaningful only to the  UDDI-enabled server that provided
them and are to be used  according to the published policies of a given
UDDI-enabled server.
</para>
  <para>
Each party that has been granted publication access to a given UDDI-enabled
server will be provided a token by the site.  The methods for obtaining this token are
specific to each UDDI-enabled server.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="uddiestcreds"><title>Establishing Credentials</title>
  <para>
Before any party can publish data within a UDDI-enabled server,
credentials and permission to publish must be supplied with the
individual operator.  Generally, you will only need to interact with
one UDDI-enabled server because all data published at any UDDI-enabled
server are replicated automatically to all other such servers.
Establishing publishing credentials involves providing some verifiable
identification information, contact information, and establishing
security credentials with the individual server.  The specifics of
these establishing credentials is server-dependent, and all valid
UDDI-enabled servers provide a Web-based user interface through which
you can establish an identity and secure permission to publish data.
</para>
  <para>
Every registry implementation that adheres to these specifications
establishes its own mechanism for token generation and authentication.
The only requirement placed on token generation for use with the publisher's
API is that the tokens themselves must be valid string text that can be placed
within the <parameter>authInfo</parameter> XML element.  Given that binary-to-string translations are
well-understood and in common use, this requirement will not introduce hardships.
</para>
  <para>
Authentication tokens are not required to be valid except at the UDDI-enabled server
or implementation from which they originated.  These tokens need only have meaning
at a single UDDI-enabled server or implementation, and should not be expected
to work across sites.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="genauthtokens"><title>Generating Authentication Tokens</title>
  <para>
Many implementations are expected to require a login step.  The
<parameter>get_authToken</parameter> message is  provided to accommodate implementations that
desire a login step.  Security schemes  based on
exchanging User ID and password credentials fall into this category.  For
implementations that desire this kind of security, the <parameter>get_authToken</parameter> API is
provided as a means of generating a temporary authentication token.
</para>
  <para>
Certificate-based authentication and similar security mechanisms do not
require this additional step of logging in. Instead, they can pass
compatible authentication token information such as a certificate value
within the <parameter>authInfo</parameter> element provided on each of the
publisher's API messages.  If certificate-based authentication or similar
security is employed the use of the <parameter>get_authToken</parameter>
and <parameter>discard_authToken</parameter> messages is optional.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="uddiapicalls"><title>UDDI API Calls</title>

<para>
This section describes the Virtuoso UDDI-related messages.  These messages
are divided into APIs for authentication, inquiry, and publication.
</para>

<sect3 id="authapis"><title>Authorization API</title>

&uddi_get_authToken;
&uddi_get_registeredInfo;
&uddi_discard_authToken;

</sect3>
<sect3 id="uddisearchapi"><title>Inquiry API Functions</title>
  <para>
The inquiry API messages <parameter>find_binding</parameter>,
<parameter>find_business</parameter>, <parameter>find_service</parameter>,
and <parameter>find_tModel</parameter> all accept an optional element
named <parameter>findQualifiers</parameter>.  This argument provides a
means to allow the caller to override default search behaviors.
</para>
  <para>
The messages in this section represent inquiries that anyone can make of
any UDDI-enabled server at any time.  These messages all behave synchronously
and are required to be exposed via HTTP POST only.  Other synchronous or
asynchronous mechanisms may be provided at the discretion of the individual
UDDI-enabled server or compatible registry.
</para>
  <para>
The publicly accessible queries are:
</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem><emphasis>find_binding:</emphasis> Used to locate specific bindings
within a registered <parameter>businessService</parameter>.  Returns a <parameter>bindingDetail</parameter> message.
</listitem>
  <listitem><emphasis>find_business:</emphasis> Used to locate information
about one or more businesses.  Returns a <parameter>businessList</parameter> message.
</listitem>
  <listitem><emphasis>find_service:</emphasis> Used to locate specific
services within a registered <parameter>businessEntity</parameter>.  Returns a <parameter>serviceList</parameter> message.
</listitem>
  <listitem><emphasis>find_tModel:</emphasis> Used to locate one or more
<parameter>tModel</parameter> information structures.  Returns a <parameter>tModelList</parameter> structure.
</listitem>
  <listitem><emphasis>get_bindingDetail:</emphasis> Used to get full
<parameter>bindingTemplate</parameter> information suitable for making one or more service requests.
Returns a <parameter>bindingDetail</parameter> message.
</listitem>
  <listitem><emphasis>get_businessDetail:</emphasis> Used to get the full
<parameter>businessEntity</parameter> information for a one or more businesses.  Returns a
<parameter>businessDetail</parameter> message.
</listitem>
  <listitem><emphasis>get_businessDetailExt:</emphasis> Used to get extended
<parameter>businessEntity</parameter> information.  Returns a <parameter>businessDetailExt</parameter> message.
</listitem>
  <listitem><emphasis>get_serviceDetail:</emphasis> Used to get full details
for a given set of registered <parameter>businessService</parameter> date.  Returns a <parameter>serviceDetail</parameter>
message.
</listitem>
  <listitem><emphasis>get_tModelDetail:</emphasis> Used to get full details
for a given set of registered <parameter>tModel</parameter> data.  Returns a <parameter>tModelDetail</parameter> message.
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

&uddi_find_binding;

&uddi_find_business;

&uddi_find_service;

&uddi_find_tModel;

&uddi_get_bindingDetail;

&uddi_get_businessDetail;

&uddi_get_businessDetailExt;

&uddi_get_serviceDetail;

&uddi_get_tModelDetail;

</sect3>

<sect3 id="uddipublishingfuncs"><title>Publishing API Functions</title>
  <para>
The messages in this section represent inquiries that require authenticated access
to an operator site.  Each business should initially select one UDDI-enabled server
to host their information.  Once chosen, information can only be updated at the site
originally selected.
</para>
  <para>
The messages defined in this section all behave synchronously and are only
callable via HTTP-POST.  HTTPS is used exclusively for all the calls
defined in this publisher's API.
</para>

<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><emphasis>save_binding:</emphasis> Used to register new <parameter>bindingTemplate</parameter> information
or update existing <parameter>bindingTemplate</parameter> information.  Use this to control information about
technical capabilities exposed by a registered business.
  </listitem>
<listitem><emphasis>save_business:</emphasis> Used to register new <parameter>businessEntity</parameter> information
or update existing <parameter>businessEntity</parameter> information.  Use this to control the overall information
about the entire business.  Of all the save messages, this one has the broadest effect.
  </listitem>
<listitem><emphasis>save_service:</emphasis> Used to register or update complete information
about a <parameter>businessService</parameter> exposed by a specified <parameter>businessEntity</parameter>.
  </listitem>
<listitem><emphasis>save_tModel:</emphasis> Used to register or update complete
information about a <parameter>tModel</parameter>.
  </listitem>
<listitem><emphasis>delete_binding:</emphasis> Used to remove an existing <parameter>bindingTemplate</parameter>
from the bindingTemplates collection that is part of a specified <parameter>businessService</parameter>
structure.
  </listitem>
<listitem><emphasis>delete_business:</emphasis> Used to delete registered <parameter>businessEntity</parameter>
information from the registry.
  </listitem>
<listitem><emphasis>delete_service:</emphasis> Used to delete an existing <parameter>businessService</parameter>
from the businessServices collection that is part of a specified <parameter>businessEntity</parameter>.
  </listitem>
<listitem><emphasis>delete_tModel:</emphasis> Used to delete registered information about
a <parameter>tModel</parameter>.  If there are any references to a <parameter>tModel</parameter> when this call is made, the <parameter>tModel</parameter>
will be marked deleted instead of being physically removed.
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

&uddi_save_binding;

&uddi_save_business;

&uddi_save_service;

&uddi_save_tModel;

&uddi_delete_binding;

&uddi_delete_business;

&uddi_delete_service;

&uddi_delete_tModel;

</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="uddiexamples"><title>Examples</title>

<example id="ex_uddi_genfind"><title>Generic Find</title>
<para>Finds all registry entries for names beginning with 'M':</para>
<programlisting>
select http_get ('http://localhost:6666/SOAP', null, 'POST',
  'Content-Type: text/xml\r\nSOAPAction: ""',
  '&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;Envelope xmlns="http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/soap/envelope/"&gt;
&lt;Body&gt;
&lt;find_business xmlns="urn:uddi-org:api" generic="1.0"&gt;
&lt;name&gt;M&lt;/name&gt;
&lt;/find_business&gt;
&lt;/Body&gt;
&lt;/Envelope&gt;');
</programlisting>
</example>

<example id="ex_uddi_findbyname1"><title>Find By Name 1</title>
<para>Find by name with sort options by name and date, both ascending:</para>

<programlisting>
select http_get ('http://localhost:6666/SOAP', null, 'POST',
  'Content-Type: text/xml\r\nSOAPAction: ""',
  '&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;Envelope xmlns="http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/soap/envelope/"&gt;
&lt;Body&gt;
&lt;find_business xmlns="urn:uddi-org:api" generic="1.0"&gt;
&lt;findQualifiers&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;sortByNameAsc&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;sortByDateAsc&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;/findQualifiers&gt;
&lt;name&gt;&lt;/name&gt;
&lt;/find_business&gt;
&lt;/Body&gt;
&lt;/Envelope&gt;');
</programlisting>
</example>

<example id="ex_uddi_findbyname2"><title>Find By Name 2</title>
<para>Find by name, sorted by name descending and date ascending:</para>
<programlisting>
select http_get ('http://localhost:6666/SOAP', null, 'POST',
  'Content-Type: text/xml\r\nSOAPAction: ""',
  '&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;Envelope xmlns="http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/soap/envelope/"&gt;
&lt;Body&gt;
&lt;find_business xmlns="urn:uddi-org:api" generic="1.0"&gt;
&lt;findQualifiers&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;sortByNameDesc&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;sortByDateAsc&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;/findQualifiers&gt;
&lt;name&gt;&lt;/name&gt;
&lt;/find_business&gt;
&lt;/Body&gt;
&lt;/Envelope&gt;');
</programlisting>
</example>

<example id="ex_uddi_findbynameematch"><title>Find By Name 3</title>
<para>Find by exact name match, case-sensitive, and sorted by name and
date ascending:</para>
<programlisting>
select http_get ('http://localhost:6666/SOAP', null, 'POST',
  'Content-Type: text/xml\r\nSOAPAction: ""',
  '&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;Envelope xmlns="http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/soap/envelope/"&gt;
&lt;Body&gt;
&lt;find_business xmlns="urn:uddi-org:api" generic="1.0"&gt;
&lt;findQualifiers&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;exactNameMatch&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;caseSensitiveMatch&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;sortByNameAsc&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;sortByDateAsc&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;/findQualifiers&gt;
&lt;name&gt;Microsoft Corporation&lt;/name&gt;
&lt;/find_business&gt;
&lt;/Body&gt;
&lt;/Envelope&gt;');
</programlisting>
</example>

<example id="ex_uddi_findbyidbay"><title>Find By <parameter>identifierBag</parameter> Element 'DUNS':</title>
<programlisting>
select http_get ('http://localhost:6666/SOAP', null, 'POST',
  'Content-Type: text/xml\r\nSOAPAction: ""',
  '&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;Envelope xmlns="http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/soap/envelope/"&gt;
&lt;Body&gt;
&lt;find_business xmlns="urn:uddi-org:api" generic="1.0"&gt;
&lt;findQualifiers&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;exactNameMatch&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;caseSensitiveMatch&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;sortByNameAsc&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;sortByDateAsc&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;/findQualifiers&gt;
&lt;identifierBag&gt;
&lt;keyedReference keyName="D-U-N-S" keyValue="08-146-6849"
  tModelKey="UUID:8609C81E-EE1F-4D5A-B202-3EB13AD01823"/&gt;
&lt;/identifierBag&gt;
&lt;/find_business&gt;
&lt;/Body&gt;
&lt;/Envelope&gt;');
</programlisting>
</example>

<example id="ex_uddi_findbytmodel"><title>Find by <parameter>tModel</parameter></title>
<programlisting>
select http_get ('http://localhost:6666/SOAP', null, 'POST',
  'Content-Type: text/xml\r\nSOAPAction: ""',
  '&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;Envelope xmlns="http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/soap/envelope/"&gt;
&lt;Body&gt;
&lt;find_business xmlns="urn:uddi-org:api" generic="1.0"&gt;
&lt;findQualifiers&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;exactNameMatch&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;caseSensitiveMatch&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;sortByNameAsc&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;sortByDateAsc&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;/findQualifiers&gt;
&lt;tModelBag&gt;
&lt;tModelKey&gt;UUID:68DE9E80-AD09-469D-8A37-088422BFBC36&lt;/tModelKey&gt;
&lt;/tModelBag&gt;
&lt;/find_business&gt;
&lt;/Body&gt;
&lt;/Envelope&gt;');
</programlisting>
</example>

<example id="ex_uddi_findbydiscovery"><title>Find by discovery URL</title>
<programlisting>
select http_get ('http://localhost:6666/SOAP', null, 'POST',
  'Content-Type: text/xml\r\nSOAPAction: ""',
  '&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;Envelope xmlns="http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/soap/envelope/"&gt;
&lt;Body&gt;
&lt;find_business xmlns="urn:uddi-org:api" generic="1.0"&gt;
&lt;findQualifiers&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;exactNameMatch&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;caseSensitiveMatch&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;sortByNameAsc&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;findQualifier&gt;sortByDateAsc&lt;/findQualifier&gt;
&lt;/findQualifiers&gt;
&lt;discoveryURLs&gt;
&lt;discoveryURL&gt;
http://uddi.microsoft.com/discovery?businessKey=D94B25A4-BD6D-4426-AEAC-1087DCC21421
&lt;/discoveryURL&gt;
&lt;/discoveryURLs&gt;
&lt;/find_business&gt;
&lt;/Body&gt;
&lt;/Envelope&gt;');
</programlisting>
</example>

<example id="ex_uddi_getauth"><title>Get authentication token</title>
<programlisting>
select http_get ('http://localhost:6666/SOAP', null, 'POST',
  'Content-Type: text/xml\r\nSOAPAction: ""',
  '&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;Envelope xmlns="http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/soap/envelope/"&gt;
&lt;Body&gt;
&lt;get_authToken xmlns="urn:uddi-org:api" generic="1.0"&gt;
&lt;userID&gt;dav&lt;/userID&gt;
&lt;cred&gt;dav&lt;/cred&gt;
&lt;/get_authToken&gt;
&lt;/Body&gt;
&lt;/Envelope&gt;');
</programlisting>
</example>

<example id="ex_uddi_discardauth"><title>Discard Authentication Token</title>
<programlisting>
select http_get ('http://localhost:6666/SOAP', null, 'POST',
  'Content-Type: text/xml\r\nSOAPAction: ""',
  '&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;Envelope xmlns="http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/soap/envelope/"&gt;
&lt;Body&gt;
&lt;discard_authToken xmlns="urn:uddi-org:api" generic="1.0"&gt;
&lt;authInfo&gt;71255ffc5b0a22b4699bfcee74cba97f&lt;/authInfo&gt;
&lt;/discard_authToken&gt;
&lt;/Body&gt;
&lt;/Envelope&gt;');
</programlisting>
</example>

</sect2>

<tip><title>See Also:</title>
<para><link linkend="uddischema">UDDI System Tables</link></para></tip>
</sect1>
