<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2018 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->

<sect2 id="usermodel"><title>Virtuoso User Model</title>

<para>The Virtuoso User Model is designed to support:</para>

<simplelist>
 <member>Use of an external server for password and user account base maintenance 
 for example an LDAP server, another database server etc.  This allows user accounts to be 
 verified against security information stored in some  centralized repository, 
 allowing integration into existing security infrastructure .</member>
 <member>Single namespace for users and groups for SQL and web service access.  
 In this  way the local security info is stored in one place and allows 
   enabling SQL account to work as a web account or a web account as an SQL 
 account. This enforces unique names for users and roles in the database.</member>
 <member>Extensibility of user information retrieval  and checking.</member>
 <member>Extensibility of user account and group attributes.</member>
</simplelist>

<para>There is a set of functions for administering the users and groups 
(roles) of a Virtuoso database.  All the user administration functions are restricted to
members of the dba group only.</para>
 
<note><title>Note:</title>
<para>The terms 'role' and 'group' are identical in their usage in this document.  
The terms security object or grantee refer collectively to users and 
groups.</para></note>

<para>User manipulation functions do not generally return values.  In case of 
error an error condition will be signaled.</para>

<para>Users and roles are in the same namespace and are identified by name.  
One name will not both designate a user and a group.  A user or group may be 
SQL enabled.  A name that identifies a role (group) does not have a password 
and is not a valid login name.</para>

<para>A user may belong to multiple roles.  A role may inherit multiple other 
roles.  One role may be inherited or directly granted to a security object 
multiple times.  The order of granting is not relevant.  The effective 
privileges of a user are those granted to public, those granted to the user 
plus those granted to a direct or indirect role of the user.  The relationship 
between users and roles is many to many.  A role can be granted multiple other 
roles as well as direct permissions.  Cycles in granting roles are not allowed, 
an error will be signaled if an operation would result in a cycle in the
role inheritance graph.</para>

<para>When SQL procedures or queries are executing, the effective privileges 
are those granted to the owner of the procedure or view.  A top level 
dynamic SQL statement executes with the effective privileges of the logged in 
user.  If a SQL statement executes as a result of an HTTP request, the 
applicable virtual directory specifies on behalf of which SQL account the SQL is 
executed.  A role cannot be the owner of procedures, views or other executable 
SQL entities.</para>

<sect3 id="vumsecobjects"><title>Security Objects Management</title>

<para>The following functions allow for creation and deletion of security objects 
and roles, and for assigning or removing roles from security objects:</para>

<simplelist>
  <member><link linkend="fn_USER_CREATE"><function>USER_CREATE()</function></link></member>
  <member><link linkend="fn_USER_ROLE_CREATE"><function>USER_ROLE_CREATE()</function></link></member>
  <member><link linkend="fn_USER_DROP"><function>USER_DROP()</function></link></member>
  <member><link linkend="fn_USER_ROLE_DROP"><function>USER_ROLE_DROP()</function></link></member>
  <member><link linkend="fn_USER_CHANGE_PASSWORD"><function>USER_CHANGE_PASSWORD()</function></link></member>
  <member><link linkend="fn_USER_SET_QUALIFIER"><function>USER_SET_QUALIFIER()</function></link></member>
  <member><link linkend="fn_USER_GRANT_ROLE"><function>USER_GRANT_ROLE()</function></link></member>
  <member><link linkend="fn_USER_REVOKE_ROLE"><function>USER_REVOKE_ROLE()</function></link></member>
  <member><link linkend="fn_USER_SET_OPTION"><function>USER_SET_OPTIONS()</function></link></member>
  <member><link linkend="fn_USER_GET_OPTION"><function>USER_GET_OPTIONS()</function></link></member>
</simplelist>

<para>The security objects and roles data are contained in the system tables 
described in the <link linkend="UserSysTables">User System Tables</link> Section 
of the Appendix</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="vumuseroptions"><title>User Options</title>

<itemizedlist>
 <listitem><formalpara><title>PASSWORD_MODE</title>
  <para>Function for checking a given password on SQL or DAV login.  See below.</para>
  </formalpara></listitem>

 <listitem><formalpara><title>PASSWORD_MODE_DATA</title>
  <para>Application specific data for the Password Mode hook.</para>
  </formalpara></listitem>

 <listitem><formalpara><title>LOGIN_QUALIFIER</title>
  <para>Default qualifier for SQL session.</para>
  </formalpara></listitem>

 <listitem><formalpara><title>SQL_ENABLE</title>
  <para>If set SQL login is granted.</para>
  </formalpara></listitem>

 <listitem><formalpara><title>DAV_ENABLE</title>
  <para>If set the user account can be user for web authentication.</para>
  </formalpara></listitem>
  
 <listitem><formalpara><title>DISABLED</title>
	 <para>If set the user account is locked and cannot be used to 
	     login as SQL or Web user (depends of SQL_ENABLE and DAV_ENABLE flags). 
	     If the account in question is SQL enabled the DBA group can switch 
	     the execution identity to it (see set_user_id () function).
	     This is useful when we need an account to execute Web pages (VSP/VSPX)
	     with some execution permissions but we do not 
	     want to allow it to login via SQL/ODBC. 
	 </para>
  </formalpara></listitem>

 <listitem><formalpara><title>PRIMARY_GROUP</title>
  <para>This is the primary group of the user.  This is no different from 
  other group memberships.</para>
  </formalpara></listitem>

 <listitem><formalpara><title>GET_PASSWORD</title>
  <para>Function that will retrieve the password.  If not defined the password 
  is assumed to be in the SYS_USERS table.  This allows for custom encrypted 
  storage of passwords etc.  This is simpler to use than the check hook.  
  Note that for security configurations where the server never does know the 
  passwords of user accounts, no digest based authentication schemes can be used, 
	including the HTTP digest authentication, since the digests cannot be computed 
  and checked without knowing the password.  Possible users of this feature  
  are  DBEV_LOGIN or HTTP login hooks.</para>
  </formalpara></listitem>

 <listitem><formalpara><title>E-MAIL</title>
  <para>informative: e-mail of that user.</para>
  </formalpara></listitem>

 <listitem><formalpara><title>FULL_NAME</title>
  <para>informative: full name of the user.</para>
  </formalpara></listitem>

 <listitem><formalpara><title>HOME</title>
  <para>WebDAV home directory of the account, it is meaningful  only if the 
  account is web enabled.</para>
  </formalpara></listitem>

 <listitem><formalpara><title>PERMISSIONS</title>
  <para>WebDAV default permissions for new WebDAV objects created by the user.  
  This is only meaningful when web access is enabled.</para>
  </formalpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>The functions for setting/getting these options will accept any 
other named values, the above list only being those reserved for Virtuoso so far.</para>
</sect3>


<sect3 id="vumloginexthook"><title>Login Extension PL Hook</title>
    
<para><function>DB.DBA.USER_FIND
    <paramdef>in <parameter>name</parameter> varchar</paramdef>
    </function></para>

<para>This is a user-defined PL function hook which, if it exists, will be 
executed before doing the SQL/ODBC login.  In this hook the user can find a 
user account from some other server and register it in the local database.  Or, 
this can be used to perform some pre-login actions.  It is similar to the 
DBEV_LOGIN, but it does not change any account validation rule, it is 
purely for pre-processing.</para>

<tip><title>See Also:</title>
<para>The <link linkend="hooks">Database Event Hooks</link> chapter.</para></tip>

<sect4 id="vumplhooksxmpls"><title>PL Hooks Examples</title>

<example id="vumqryldap"><title>Querying an LDAP Server</title>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure DB.DBA.LDAP_SEARCH (inout user_name varchar, in digest varchar)
{
  whenever sqlstate '28000' goto ldap_validation_failure;
  if (lcase(user_name) <> 'dba')) 
    {
      ldap_search('foo.bar.com', 0, 'o=organization', '(cn=a*)',
		sprintf('uid=%s,ou=users,o=organization', user_name), pwd_magic_calc(user_name,digest,1));
      user_name := 'dba';
      return 1; -- force validation as dba
    }
  else 
    {
      -- bypassing ldap authentication for dba, let validation occur normally
      return -1; 
    }

ldap_validation_failure:
  return -1; -- try to validate normally
}]]></programlisting>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure DB.DBA.DBEV_LOGIN (inout user_name varchar, in digest varchar, in session_random varchar) 
{
  declare get_pwd varchar;
  get_pwd := user_get_option (user_name, 'PASSWORD_MODE'); 
  if (get_pwd is not null)
    {
      declare rc integer;
      rc := call (get_pwd) (user_name, digest);
      return rc;	  
    }    
  return -1;
};]]></programlisting>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
user_create ('test_ldap', 'secret', vector ('PASSWORD_MODE', 'DB.DBA.LDAP_SEARCH'));
]]></programlisting>
</example>

<example id="vumuserfindhook"><title>USER_FIND PL Hook Example</title>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
create table 
MY_DBA_USERS (M_NAME varchar primary key, M_PASSWORD varchar);]]></programlisting>

<programlisting><![CDATA[
create procedure 
DB.DBA.USER_FIND (in name varchar)
{
  -- do nothing for existing users
  if (exists (select 1 from SYS_USERS where U_NAME = name))
    return;
  -- if there is in custom table
  if (exists (select 1 from MY_DBA_USERS where M_NAME = name))
    {
      declare pwd varchar;
      -- get password
      select M_PASSWORD into pwd from from MY_DBA_USERS where M_NAME = name;
      -- create a new SQL user based on external data
      USER_CREATE (name, pwd, NULL);
    }
};]]></programlisting>
</example>
</sect4>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="vumrolesemantics"><title>SQL Role Semantics</title>

<para>The terms user group and role are used interchangeably.  Roles can be 
nested.  There is a many to many relationship between users and roles.  There 
is likewise a similar, acyclic many to many relationship between roles.  Each 
role has a component role list of its granted (parent) roles, recursively, 
no cycles allowed.</para>

<para>All role grants are listed in the roles system table whether they be
explicitly granted or only as a result of granting a group with groups
granted to it.  The role grant graph has an explicit edge for each
role membership, direct or otherwise.  The GI_DIRECT flag is true if
the grant is direct.  Only direct role grants can be revoked.</para>

<tip><title>See Also:</title>
<para>The role system table description can be found in the appendix 
under <link linkend="UserSysTables">System Tables</link>.</para></tip>

<para>The following SQL statements deal with roles.  To create a new 
role (group) object the following  statement can be used:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[CREATE ROLE <NAME>]]></programlisting>

<para>The &lt;NAME&gt; is a name of role to be created.  It must be unique 
in space of all security objects.</para>

<example id="vumcreaterole"><title>Creating a security role</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[SQL> create role admins;]]></programlisting>
</example>

<para>Use the following statement to remove an existing role from the 
security schema. </para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[DROP ROLE <NAME>]]></programlisting>

<example id="vumrmrole"><title>Removing a security role</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[SQL> drop role admins;]]></programlisting>
</example>

<para>The GRANT and REVOKE statements are used for controlling role membership as follows:
To assign a new 
group, or list of groups (&lt;ROLE&gt;,...) to user &lt;USER&gt; use:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[GRANT <ROLE> [, <ROLE>] TO <USER> [WITH ADMIN OPTION];]]></programlisting>

<para>If the admin option is specified, the grantee can grant this same 
privilege further to other grantees.</para>

<para>Roles can be revoked using:</para>

<programlisting><![CDATA[REVOKE <ROLE> [, <ROLE>] FROM <USER>;]]></programlisting>

<example id="vumgranting"><title>Granting &amp; revoking security roles</title>
<programlisting><![CDATA[SQL> grant admins, users to demo;]]></programlisting>
<programlisting><![CDATA[SQL> revoke admins from demo;]]></programlisting>
</example>

<para>Only the dba group accounts may administer roles.</para>

<para>The dba group is not physically a role.  When an empty database is created, it will have the dba account with full privileges.  To grant these same full privileges to another user, the dba uses the grant all privileges to &lt;grantee&gt;. statement.  This 
will give the grantee full dba privileges, or in other words, add to the dba group.  This may be reversed with the revoke all privileges from &lt;grantee&gt; statement.
</para>

<para>The GRANT statement accepts any valid SQL security object in the TO clause. 
One cannot log in or perform any operations as a role.  Roles are exclusively 
shorthand for specific sets of permissions which are changed together and
are needed for multiple users. </para>
</sect3>

</sect2>




