<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- 
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2012 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->

<sect1 id="vsmx"><title>Testing Web Published Web Services</title>
  <para>Virtuoso provides a mechanism for testing SOAP messages instantly.  This 
  mechanism is the Virtuoso Service Module for XML (VSMX) - an automatically 
  generated test page for published web services.  The VSMX file is generated 
  at the same time  the WSDL file is generated.  A VSMX file is a SOAP 
  operations test page generated based on the descriptions of a WSDL file.  
  The VSMX file  has the extension .vsmx, as opposed to the .wsdl 
  extension of the WSDL file, and can be accessed similarly.</para>

  <para>VSMX pages give instant access to published  SOAP services for 
  testing.  Any newly created service will need testing which normally means 
  writing more code to call the service, supply parameters, retrieve the result, 
  display the results in some manor, etc.  The VSMX feature of Virtuoso 
  eliminates this otherwise  repetitive process by automatically 
  maintaining a test page for SOAP messages: the VSMX file.  This greatly 
  speeds up the development and testing cycle.  The 
  beauty of this is that this is automated, even Microsoft's ASMX file 
  requires that you code the services descriptions before seeing the results.</para>

  <para>Web Service developers would use VSMX to forego the test bed creation step 
  in light of automatic test page generation.  Project managers can easily keep 
  track of their developers progress by checking the test page periodically.</para>

  <para>Since WSDL descriptions by themselves are not very pleasing to the human 
  eye, the VSMX test page can be used to preview services available on a Virtuoso 
  server, or from a remote source using <link linkend="importwsdl">SOAP/WSDL Proxying</link>. 
  Even experienced developers will find these easier to read than WSDL files.</para>

  <para>Each SOAP enabled virtual directory will have a WSDL and VSMX file available.  
  The VSMX file is a test page for the SOAP operations.  This test page can be 
  found as simply as the WSDL can be found.  From the WSDL chapter we have seen that 
  for every SOAP enabled virtual directory you automatically get the file:</para>
  <programlisting>http://[host:port]/[SOAP Virtual Directory]/services.wsdl</programlisting>
  <para>likewise you also get:</para>
  <programlisting>http://[host:port]/[SOAP Virtual Directory]/services.vsmx</programlisting>

  <para>You simply point your web browser to this file for the test page.  The 
  demo database contains samples that can be found as:</para>
  
  <programlisting>http://[host:port]/SOAP/services.vsmx</programlisting>

    <figure float="0"><title>VSMX Test Page</title>
      <graphic fileref="ui/vsmx001.png"/></figure>

  <para>The page shows all the operations that are available.  Click on 
  the link that corresponds to the operation to test and the services details and test 
  facilities will also appear, allowing you to supply input parameters making the SOAP call.</para>

  <para>Once executed the result of SOAP call will be rendered using the Virtuoso 
  XSLT processor and built-in style sheet, and appended to bottom of the 
  services details.  </para>

  <para>In addition to the simple types: numbers and strings, more complex 
  types such as arrays and structures can be specified as input parameters.  
  For an array, each value must be specified on a separate row in the input text 
  field.  For structures the names of structure members will be displayed, 
  following by the equals sign, the values of the structures members can then 
  be input after the equals sign.  Arrays of arrays or structures of arrays 
  cannot be used on the test page.</para>

  <para>The first comment line of a stored procedure in the format:</para>
  <programlisting>--## [comment]</programlisting>
  <para>will be included in the WSDL description of the SOAP message 
  for that procedure when generating the WSDL file.</para>

</sect1>



