<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2017 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<chapter label="webappdevelopment.xml" id="webappdevelopment"><title>Web Application Development</title>

<abstract>
 <para>This chapter deals with the Virtuoso HTTP Server, its Dynamic Page 
 generation and components used to configure it.  The HTTP Servers features 
 include:</para>

 <simplelist>
  <member>Web server configuration and access control.</member>
  <member>Multihosting, Virtual Hosting and Virtual Directories - A single Virtuoso 
  server can map requests into multiple spaces of web pages based on the 
  interface to which the requests come (multihosting) or on the Host 
  HTTP/1.1 header (virtual hosting).</member>
  <member>HTTP/1.0 and HTTP/1.1 support, keep alive connections and pipelining.</member>
  <member>Proxying - Virtuoso can automatically redirect requests to certain 
  resources or directories to another web server.</member>
  <member>Authentication and security - Specific directories can be made to 
  require authentication (basic or digest) or may be restricted to SSL only.  
  Authentication can also be totally user defined.</member>
  <member>SOAP - given directories can be defined as containing SOAP services, 
  which can be accessed by SOAP clients, invoking Virtuoso stored procedures.</member>
  <member>Dynamic content - Given paths can be executable, allowing 
  defining VSP, and VSPX pages that generate HTML or XML using embedded 
  Virtuoso/PL.</member>
  <member>WebDAV - Paths can be mapped into DAV collections maintained inside  
  the database.  Virtuoso WebDav is a Unix file system-like mechanism allows 
  specifying access rights and ownership of DAV resources.</member>
  <member>WebDAV resources may optionally be indexed in a free text index.</member>
  <member>A web robot allows copying external web resources into Virtuoso WebDAV.</member>
 </simplelist>

</abstract>

  <para>Virtuoso provides a full function web server with dynamic web page
  generation capability using SQL procedures embedded in HTML or XML via VSP or 
  VSPX.  Runtime hosting allows Virtuoso to generate dynamic web pages from 
  other sources also, such as ASP.Net, PHP or JSP.  </para>

  <para>Out-of-the-box Virtuoso listens for HTTP requests on the port defined 
  in the HTTP Server section of the Virtuoso INI file.  The Visual Server 
  Administration Interface is available at this port and can be used to further 
  configure the web server.</para>

  <para>Web resources can be based on the file system, reside in the database or 
  in WebDAV or any combination of all of them.  WebDAV space can be specified 
  at the path level, by default, paths beginning with /DAV are mapped to the 
  WebDAV root collection (directory) and all other paths are assumed to be file 
  system based.  By default / is mapped to the directory specified as ServerRoot in 
  the HTTP Server section of the virtuoso.ini file.</para>

  <para>Virtual Directories provide a way to make mappings from paths to other 
  resources such as specific file system or WebDAV locations, other HTTP Servers 
  acting as a proxy or to alter specific processing or authentication rules for a 
  directory.</para>

&webserver;

&web_acl;

&vsp;

&vspx;

&rth.aspx;

<sect1 id="asmxhosting"><title>ASMX Web Service Hosting</title>

  <para>Microsoft ASMX Web Services can be hosted in exactly the same way as 
  ASPX Applications can be.  A ASMX Web Services Project created in Visual Studio
  can be copied to either the file system (under the VSPROOT directory) or the 
  Virtuoso WebDAV repository.  You must copy the project directory to the 
  required location and then make a Virtual Directory pointing to it.  If the 
  location is in WebDAV then ensure that execute permissions are set for 
  any .asmx files.</para>

  <tip><title>See Also:</title>
    <para><link linkend="rthwritaspxapps">ASP.Net Web Application Hosting</link></para></tip>

</sect1>

&blogger;

&php; 

&jsphosting;

&perl;

&python;

&ruby;

</chapter>
