<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2019 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<chapter label="webservices.xml" id="webservices">
  <title>Web Services</title>
  <abstract>
    <para>The term Web Services describes an application of XML for exposing
    application functionality to disparate clients via the Web. This paradigm
    provides access to entire applications, modules, objects, functions,
    and methods via HTTP and other transport protocols. Web Services are
    inherently platform- and programming-language independent. Services can be
    developed in one language and consumed in another; this holds true
    irrespective of client or server host operating system combinations.</para>
    <para>A collection of core XML-based specifications and standards work in
    concert to fulfill the Web services value proposition. These standards
    include:</para>
  <simplelist>
    <member> SOAP - XML notation that describes how messages are assembled and
    transmitted over HTTP between services and service consumers.</member>
    <member> WSDL - XML notation for describing SOAP services. </member>
    <member> UDDI - Application of the SOAP protocol for registering and
    publishing information about organizations, contacts within organizations,
    and Web Services that these organizations have chosen to expose to the
    public.</member>
  </simplelist>
  <para>
  Virtuoso enables stored procedures to be exposed as Web services that
  are consumable by any Web services-aware development tool,
  application, or environment. The stored procedures exposed by Virtuoso
  may be native stored procedures, or may be hosted in any third-party
  database that supports stored procedures, and is accessible via an
  ODBC or JDBC driver.  In Virtuoso, exposing stored procedures as Web
  services does not require any programming effort.  You simply identify
  the stored procedures to be exposed using the Virtuoso Administrative
  Interface.
  </para>
  <para>
  This feature is immensely valuable in situations where organizations
  are seeking to transform time-tested stored procedures into Web
  Services without having to upgrade or change databases or host
  operating systems.  In modern enterprises, such stored procedures
  drive mission-critical solutions; Virtuoso's approach to Web services
  enables you to maximize current investment while minimizing the need
  for rework.
  </para>
  </abstract>

	<!-- ################### ~~~~~~~~~~ ################### -->

&soap;

&wsdl;

&vfoafssl;

&voauth;

&ws-security;

&ws-routing;

&ws-rm;

&ws-trust;

&xmla;

&xmlrpc;

&syncml;

&uddi;

&exposingws;

&vsmx;

&bpel;

&xsql;

</chapter>
