<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2013 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<refentry id="fn_tidy_html">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>tidy_html</refentrytitle>
    <refmiscinfo>xml</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>tidy_html</refname>
    <refpurpose>Invoke built-in version of HTML Tidy utility to fix typical errors in  HTML text</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <funcsynopsis id="fsyn_tidy_html">
      <funcprototype id="fproto_tidy_html">
        <funcdef><function>tidy_html</function></funcdef>
	<paramdef>in <parameter>raw_html</parameter> varchar</paramdef>
	<paramdef>in <parameter>tidy_config</parameter> varchar</paramdef>
      </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
  <refsect1 id="desc_tidy_html"><title>Description</title><para>
This function improves the given source HTML text, by invoking a
custom version of HTML Tidy utility.
To learn more about Tidy see http://www.w3.org/People/Raggett/tidy/ .
Some particular combinations of errors in source HTML may cause Tidy to
misinterpret the source so the output may be incomplete or corrupted.
This is an  unavoidable problem, due to heuristic nature of the procedure.
 On the other hand, Tidy will process almost any HTML suitable for some
&quot;popular&quot; browser, e.g. Internet Explorer or Netscape Navigator.
</para></refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="params"><title>Parameters</title>
    <refsect2><title>raw_html</title>
      <para>
Source HTML text to process.
Note that the encoding of this text must be specified in
<parameter>tidy_config</parameter> string,
and default encoding of session will not be mentioned by Tidy.
</para>
</refsect2>
    <refsect2><title>tidy_config</title>
<!--
      <para>
Configuration string, space-delimited list of options, exactly as
in original Tidy's command-line or in Tidy's configuration file.
Not all options of original Tidy will work, due to obvious reasons,
unsupported options will be silently ignored, so you may read your
favorite Tidy's configuration file by file_to_string function and
pass it to tidy_html.
</para>
    <table><title>Tidy options</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
       <thead><row><entry>Option</entry><entry>Effect</entry></row></thead>
	<tbody>
<row><entry>-indent or -i</entry><entry>indent element content</entry></row>
<row><entry>-omit   or -o</entry><entry>omit optional endtags</entry></row>
<row><entry>-wrap 72</entry><entry>wrap text at column 72 (default is 68)</entry></row>
<row><entry>-upper  or -u</entry><entry>force tags to upper case (default is lower)</entry></row>
<row><entry>-clean  or -c</entry><entry>replace font, nobr &amp; center tags by CSS</entry></row>
<row><entry>-numeric or -n</entry><entry>output numeric rather than named entities</entry></row>
<row><entry>-errors or -e</entry><entry>only show errors</entry></row>
<row><entry>-quiet or -q</entry><entry>suppress nonessential output</entry></row>
<row><entry>-xml</entry><entry>use this when input is wellformed xml</entry></row>
<row><entry>-asxml</entry><entry>to convert html to wellformed xml</entry></row>
<row><entry>-slides</entry><entry>(DISABLED) to burst into slides on h2 elements</entry></row>
<row><entry>-raw</entry><entry>leave chars > 128 unchanged upon output</entry></row>
<row><entry>-ascii</entry><entry>use ASCII for output, Latin-1 for input</entry></row>
<row><entry>-latin1</entry><entry>use Latin-1 for both input and output</entry></row>
<row><entry>-iso2022</entry><entry>use ISO2022 for both input and output</entry></row>
<row><entry>-utf8</entry><entry>use UTF-8 for both input and output</entry></row>
<row><entry>-mac</entry><entry>use the Apple MacRoman character set</entry></row>
<row><entry>-config &lt;file&gt;</entry><entry>(DISABLED) set options from config &lt;file&gt;</entry></row>
<row><entry>-f &lt;file&gt;</entry><entry>(DISABLED) write errors to named &lt;file&gt;</entry></row>
<row><entry>-modify or -m</entry><entry>(DISABLED) to modify original files</entry></row>
<row><entry>-version or -v</entry><entry>(DISABLED) show version</entry></row>
<row><entry>-help or -h</entry><entry>(DISABLED) list command line / configuration options</entry></row>
	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
-->
      <para>
Configuration string is a list of options, delimited by newlines,
with exactly the same syntax as original Tidy's configuration file.
Not all options of original Tidy will work, due to obvious reasons,
unsupported options will be silently ignored, so you may read your
favorite Tidy's configuration file by file_to_string function and
pass it to tidy_html.
</para>

<formalpara><title>tidy-mark: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis> (the default) Tidy will add a meta
element to the document head to indicate that the document has
been tidied. To suppress this, set tidy-mark to <emphasis>no</emphasis>. Tidy
won't add a meta element if one is already present.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>markup: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>Determines whether Tidy generates a pretty printed version of
the markup. Bool values are either <emphasis>yes</emphasis> or <emphasis>no</emphasis>.
Note that Tidy won't generate a pretty printed version if it
finds unknown tags, or missing trailing quotes on attribute
values, or missing trailing '&gt;' on tags. The default is
<emphasis>yes</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>wrap: <emphasis>number</emphasis></title>

<para>Sets the right margin for line wrapping. Tidy tries to wrap
lines so that they do not exceed this length. The default is 66.
Set wrap to zero if you want to disable line wrapping.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>wrap-attributes: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, attribute values may be wrapped
across lines for easier editing. The default is no. This option
can be set independently of wrap-scriptlets</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>wrap-script-literals: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, this allows lines to be wrapped
within string literals that appear in script attributes. The
default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>. The example shows how Tidy wraps a really
really long script string literal inserting a backslash character
before the linebreak:
<screen>
&lt;a href="somewhere.html" onmouseover="document.status = '...some \
really, really, really, really, really, really, really, really, \
really, really long string..';"&gt;test&lt;/a&gt;
</screen>
</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>wrap-asp: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>no</emphasis>, this prevents lines from being wrapped
within ASP pseudo elements, which look like:
&lt;%&#160;...&#160;%&gt;. The default is <emphasis>yes</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>wrap-jste: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>no</emphasis>, this prevents lines from being wrapped
within JSTE pseudo elements, which look like:
&lt;#&#160;...&#160;#&gt;. The default is <emphasis>yes</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>wrap-php: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>no</emphasis>, this prevents lines from being wrapped
within PHP pseudo elements. The default is <emphasis>yes</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>literal-attributes: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, this ensures that whitespace
characters within attribute values are passed through unchanged.
The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>tab-size: <emphasis>number</emphasis></title>

<para>Sets the number of columns between successive tab stops. The
default is 4. It is used to map tabs to spaces when reading
files. Tidy never outputs files with tabs.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>indent: <emphasis>no, yes</emphasis> or <emphasis>auto</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, Tidy will indent block-level tags.
The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>. If set to <emphasis>auto</emphasis> Tidy will
decide whether or not to indent the content of tags such as
title, h1-h6, li, td, th, or p depending on whether or not the
content includes a block-level element. You are advised to avoid
setting indent to yes as this can expose layout bugs in some
browsers.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>indent-spaces: <emphasis>number</emphasis></title>

<para>Sets the number of spaces to indent content when indentation
is enabled. The default is 2 spaces.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>indent-attributes: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, each attribute will begin on a new
line. The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>hide-endtags: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, optional end-tags will be omitted
when generating the pretty printed markup. This option is ignored
if you are outputting to XML. The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>input-xml: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, Tidy will use the XML parser rather
than the error correcting HTML parser. The default is
<emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>output-xml: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, Tidy will use generate the pretty
printed output writing it as well-formed XML. Any entities not
defined in XML 1.0 will be written as numeric entities to allow
them to be parsed by an XML parser. The tags and attributes will
be in the case used in the input document, regardless of other
options. The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>add-xml-pi: <emphasis>bool</emphasis>, add-xml-decl: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, Tidy will add the XML declaration
when outputting XML or XHTML. The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>. Note
that if the input document includes an &lt;?xml?&gt; declaration
then it will appear in the output independent of the value of
this option.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>output-xhtml: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, Tidy will generate the pretty printed
output writing it as extensible HTML. The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.
This option causes Tidy to set the doctype and default namespace
as appropriate to XHTML. If a doctype or namespace is given they
will checked for consistency with the content of the document. In
the case of an inconsistency, the corrected values will appear in
the output. For XHTML, entities can be written as named or
numeric entities according to the value of the "numeric-entities"
property. The tags and attributes will be output in the case used
in the input document, regardless of other options.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>doctype: <emphasis>omit, auto, strict, loose</emphasis> or
&lt;<emphasis>fpi</emphasis>&gt;</title>

<para>This property controls the doctype declaration generated by
Tidy. If set to <emphasis>omit</emphasis> the output file won't contain a
doctype declaration. If set to <emphasis>auto</emphasis> (the default) Tidy
will use an educated guess based upon the contents of the
document. If set to <emphasis>strict</emphasis>, Tidy will set the doctype to
the strict DTD. If set to <emphasis>loose</emphasis>, the doctype is set to
the loose (transitional) DTD. Alternatively, you can supply a
string for the formal public identifier (fpi) for example:
<screen>
doctype: "-//ACME//DTD HTML 3.14159//EN"
</screen>
If you specify the fpi for an XHTML document, Tidy will set
the system identifier to the empty string. Tidy leaves the
document type for generic XML documents unchanged.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>char-encoding: <emphasis>raw, ascii, latin1, utf8</emphasis> or
<emphasis>iso2022</emphasis></title>

<para>Determines how Tidy interprets character streams. For
<emphasis>ascii</emphasis>, Tidy will accept Latin-1 character values, but
will use entities for all characters whose value &gt; 127. For
<emphasis>raw</emphasis>, Tidy will output values above 127 without
translating them into entities. For <emphasis>latin1</emphasis> characters
above 255 will be written as entities. For <emphasis>utf8</emphasis>, Tidy
assumes that both input and output is encoded as UTF-8. You can
use <emphasis>iso2022</emphasis> for files encoded using the ISO2022 family
of encodings e.g. ISO 2022-JP. The default is
<emphasis>ascii</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>numeric-entities: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>Causes entities other than the basic XML 1.0 named entities
to be written in the numeric rather than the named entity form.
The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis></para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>quote-marks: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, this causes " characters to be
written out as &amp;quot; as is preferred by some editing
environments. The apostrophe character ' is written out as
&amp;#39; since many web browsers don't yet support &amp;apos;.
The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>quote-nbsp: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, this causes non-breaking space
characters to be written out as entities, rather than as the
Unicode character value 160 (decimal). The default is
<emphasis>yes</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>quote-ampersand: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, this causes unadorned &amp;
characters to be written out as &amp;amp;. The default is
<emphasis>yes</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>assume-xml-procins: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, this changes the parsing of
processing instructions to require ?&gt; as the terminator rather
than &gt;. The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>. This option is
automatically set if the input is in XML.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>fix-backslash: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, this causes backslash characters "\"
in URLs to be replaced by forward slashes "/". The default is
<emphasis>yes</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>break-before-br: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, Tidy will output a line break before
each &lt;br&gt; element. The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>uppercase-tags: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>Causes tag names to be output in upper case. The default is
<emphasis>no</emphasis> resulting in lowercase, except for XML input where
the original case is preserved.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>uppercase-attributes: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis> attribute names are output in upper
case. The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis> resulting in lowercase, except
for XML where the original case is preserved.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>word-2000: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, Tidy will go to great pains to strip
out all the surplus stuff Microsoft Word 2000 inserts when you
save Word documents as "Web pages". The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.
Note that Tidy doesn't yet know what to do with VML markup from
Word, but in future I hope to be able to map VML to SVG.</para>
<para>
 Microsoft has developed its own optional filter for exporting to
HTML, and the 2.0 version is much improved. You can download the
filter free from the <ulink url="http://officeupdate.microsoft.com/2000/downloadDetails/Msohtmf2.htm">
Microsoft Office Update site</ulink>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>clean: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, causes Tidy to strip out surplus
presentational tags and attributes replacing them by style rules
and structural markup as appropriate. It works well on the html
saved from Microsoft Office'97. The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>logical-emphasis: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, causes Tidy to replace any occurrence
of i by em and any occurrence of b by strong. In both cases, the
attributes are preserved unchanged. The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.
This option can now be set independently of the clean and
drop-font-tags options.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>drop-empty-paras: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, empty paragraphs will be discarded.
If set to no, empty paragraphs are replaced by a pair of
&lt;br&gt; elements as HTML4 precludes empty paragraphs. The
default is <emphasis>yes</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>drop-font-tags: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis> together with the clean option (see
above), Tidy will discard font and center tags rather than
creating the corresponding style rules. The default is
<emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>enclose-text: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, this causes Tidy to enclose any text
it finds in the body element within a p element. This is useful
when you want to take an existing html file and use it with a
style sheet. Any text at the body level will screw up the
margins, but wrap the text within a p element and all is well!
The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>enclose-block-text: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, this causes Tidy to insert a p
element to enclose any text it finds in any element that allows
mixed content for HTML transitional but not HTML strict. The
default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>fix-bad-comments: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, this causes Tidy to replace
unexpected hyphens with "=" characters when it comes across
adjacent hyphens. The default is <emphasis>yes</emphasis>. This option is
provided for users of Cold Fusion which uses the comment syntax:
&lt;!---&#160;---&gt;</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>add-xml-space: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, this causes Tidy to add
xml:space="preserve" to elements such as pre, style and script
when generating XML. This is needed if the whitespace in such
elements is to be parsed appropriately without having access to
the DTD. The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>alt-text: <emphasis>string</emphasis></title>

<para>This allows you to set the default alt text for img
attributes. This feature is dangerous as it suppresses further
accessibility warnings. <emphasis>YOU ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR MAKING YOUR
DOCUMENTS ACCESSIBLE TO PEOPLE WHO CAN'T SEE THE
IMAGES!!!</emphasis></para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>write-back: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, Tidy will write back the tidied
markup to the same file it read from. The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.
You are advised to keep copies of important files before tidying
them as on rare occasions the result may not always be what you
expect.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>keep-time: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, Tidy won't alter the last modified
time for files it writes back to. The default is <emphasis>yes</emphasis>.
This allows you to tidy files without effecting which ones will
be uploaded to the Web server when using a tool such as
'SiteCopy'. Note that this feature may not work on some
platforms.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>error-file: <emphasis>filename</emphasis></title>

<para>Writes errors and warnings to the named file rather than to
stderr.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>show-warnings: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>no</emphasis>, warnings are suppressed. This can be
useful when a few errors are hidden in a flurry of warnings. The
default is <emphasis>yes</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>quiet: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, Tidy won't output the welcome message
or the summary of the numbers of errors and warnings. The default
is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>gnu-emacs: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, Tidy changes the format for reporting
errors and warnings to a format that is more easily parsed by GNU
Emacs. The default is <emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>split: <emphasis>bool</emphasis></title>

<para>If set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis> Tidy will use the input file to create
a sequence of slides, splitting the markup prior to each
successive &lt;h2&gt;. You can see an example of the results in a
<ulink url="http://www.w3.org/Talks/1999/03/24-stockholm-xhtml/">
recent talk on XHTML</ulink>. The slides are written to
"slide1.html", "slide2.html" etc. The default is
<emphasis>no</emphasis>.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>new-empty-tags: <emphasis>tag1, tag2, tag3</emphasis></title>

<para>Use this to declare new empty inline tags. The option takes a
space or comma separated list of tag names. Unless you declare
new tags, Tidy will refuse to generate a tidied file if the input
includes previously unknown tags. Remember to also declare empty
tags as either inline or blocklevel, see below.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>new-inline-tags: <emphasis>tag1, tag2, tag3</emphasis></title>

<para>Use this to declare new non-empty inline tags. The option
takes a space or comma separated list of tag names. Unless you
declare new tags, Tidy will refuse to generate a tidied file if
the input includes previously unknown tags.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>new-blocklevel-tags: <emphasis>tag1, tag2, tag3</emphasis></title>

<para>Use this to declare new block-level tags. The option takes a
space or comma separated list of tag names. Unless you declare
new tags, Tidy will refuse to generate a tidied file if the input
includes previously unknown tags. Note you can't change the
content model for elements such as table, ul, ol and dl. This is
explained in more detail in the original release notes.</para></formalpara>

<formalpara><title>new-pre-tags: <emphasis>tag1, tag2, tag3</emphasis></title>

<para>Use this to declare new tags that are to be processed in
exactly the same way as HTML's pre element. The option takes a
space or comma separated list of tag names. Unless you declare
new tags, Tidy will refuse to generate a tidied file if the input
includes previously unknown tags. Note you can't as yet add new
CDATA elements (similar to script).</para></formalpara>


</refsect2>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="ret"><title>Return Types</title>
<para></para></refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="errors_tidy_html"><title>Errors</title>
    <table><title>Errors signalled by tidy_html</title>
      <tgroup cols="4">
       <thead><row><entry>SQLState</entry><entry>Error Code</entry><entry>Error Text</entry><entry>Description</entry></row></thead>
	<tbody>
	  <row>
	    <entry><errorcode>XTID2</errorcode></entry>
	    <entry><errorcode></errorcode></entry>
	    <entry><errorname>HTML Tidy failed</errorname></entry>
	    <entry>The given HTML text contains serious errors. To get detailed list of them, call tidy_list_errors with same parameters as tidy_html.</entry>
	  </row>
	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="examples"><title>Examples</title>
    <example id="ex_tidy_html"><title></title>
      <para></para>
      <screen>
fine_html := tidy_html (ugly_html, '
indent: auto
indent-spaces: 2
wrap: 72
markup: yes
output-xml: no
input-xml: no
show-warnings: yes
numeric-entities: yes
quote-marks: yes
quote-nbsp: yes
quote-ampersand: no
break-before-br: no
uppercase-tags: no
uppercase-attributes: no
char-encoding: latin1
new-inline-tags: cfif, cfelse, math, mroot,
  mrow, mi, mn, mo, msqrt, mfrac, msubsup, munderover,
  munder, mover, mmultiscripts, msup, msub, mtext,
  mprescripts, mtable, mtr, mtd, mth
new-blocklevel-tags: cfoutput, cfquery
new-empty-tags: cfelse');
</screen>
    </example>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="seealso"><title>See Also</title>
    <para><link linkend="fn_tidy_list_errors"></link></para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>

