<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2017 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<refentry id="VX-S-4">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>Advanced VSPX programming</refentrytitle>
    <refmiscinfo>tutorial</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>VSPX tree control</refname>
    <refpurpose>Directory tree browser</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsect1 id="VS-S-4a">
    <title>Vertical oriented tree</title>
    <para>
    To display any data which can be represented as tree hierarchy,
    the vspx:tree control can be used.  In it's forms it may be represented as 
    vertical or horizontal one. The following example show directory structure of the 
    VSPX tutorials on local file system.  
    </para>
    <para>
    The vspx:tree control have three important attributes:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>root - This is a name of PL procedure which must return nodes under root of tree</listitem>
      <listitem>child-function - This evaluated on a node must return children nodes or empty if it's a leaf</listitem>
      <listitem>start-path - This expression or constant is passed to the root function</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>In our example the root and child functions returns a array of strings per directory or file, the '.' and '..' are omitted. In interest also are two special containers and one place-holder:</para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>leaf-template - the content of this template will be instantiated and rendered when current position in the tree is a leaf.</listitem>
      <listitem>node-template - this will be instantiated and rendered on nodes, per each node. The place of next node is designated with "node" placeholder.</listitem>
      <listitem>node - place-holder to mark-up place where child content must be instantiated.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>In that control like as in data-set may have special button suffixed with '[name of tree control]_toggle'. This will be rendered as other submit buttons (in our case it have image appearance), but it will have special function to expand or collapse the branch.</para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
