<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2012 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<HelpTopic>
<sect1 id="account_create">
    <title>Creating and editing user accounts</title>
            <para>Required fields are marked with a red asterisk (*).</para>
	    <simplelist>
              <member>Account name: <para>Used to store real name or description of the account</para></member>
              <member>User login: <para>Used to identify user when logging in</para></member>
              <member>Default Qual/Catalog: <para>Default qualifier and catalog for the user</para></member>
              <member>Password: <para>User password. Same string must be entered in both Password and
              Confirm password fields to detect typing errors.</para></member>
              <member>User enabled: <para>This is a master enable/disable switch. If unchecked, the user will not be able to log into the system in any capacity</para></member>
              <member>Allow SQL/ODBC logins: <para>Controls whether the user is allowed to login using a database client, such as a standalone interactive SQL CLI or an ODBC client.</para></member>
              <member>Primary role: <para>User primary role (group) in the system. Controls role-based grants to DB objects. WebDAV resources and collections created by the user will have their group owner set as this group by default.</para></member>
              <member>Account roles: <para>Additional roles (groups) the user is a member of.</para></member>
              <member>Email: <para>User email for administrative and other purposes</para></member>
              <member>DAV home path: <para>User home in WebDAV file server</para></member>
              <member>Default permissions: <para>Default permissions flags for resources uploaded by the user into WebDAV file server. The permission flags are as in UNIX&trade;-like systems - read-write-execute by user, group and others. The additional t flag controls free-text indexing.</para></member>
              <member>Quota: <para>User quota (bytes) in WebDAV file server. Has no effect if quotas are not enabled. To enable DAV quotas, you need to set the DAVQuotaEnabled parameter in virtuoso ini file to a non-zero value.</para></member>
            </simplelist>
  </sect1>
</HelpTopic>
