<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2013 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<HelpTopic>
<sect1 id="xquery">
    <title>XQuery Interface</title>
    <!--
    <para></para>
    <simplelist>
      <member></member>
    </simplelist>
    -->

    <para>
	In general query's context node may either be a single resource or a collection.
    </para>
    <para>
	This page asks which option to be used for query context (the values/selection will be asked on the next screen depending of type selected here):
    </para>
    <simplelist>
      <member>DAV Resource - local WebDAV resource</member>
      <member>DAV Collection - local WebDAV collection containing a resources</member>
      <member>Database Table - document kept in a table</member>
      <member>External URL - external document or external WebDAV collection</member>
      <member>No context - an empty document will be used for context node</member>
    </simplelist>
    <para>	
	The DAV browser allows selecting a resource or collection from the local DAV
	space. If a collection is selected, all XML resources therein are
	concatenated into a forest as by the collection function.  This is placed
	under an element node called "root" and is used as the context of the query.
    </para>

    <para>
	if an external resource is desired as the context node, the URL may be
	entered.  This will be retrieved either with the collection or the doc
	function, as indicated by the check-box.
    </para>

    <para>
	Because many resources are not well formed, the check-box Skip Malformed
	allows skipping resources which are not parseable as XML from the  context
	collection.  The Parse as HTML checkbox will parse HTML, correcting tag
	nesting.
    </para>


  </sect1>
</HelpTopic>
