<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2016 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<refentry id="XP-V-1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>Using XPath queries to XML views</refentrytitle>
    <refmiscinfo>tutorial</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>Genaral</refname>
    <refpurpose>Using XPath queries to XML views. Overview.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

<refsect1 id="XP-V-1a">
<title>XPATH Implementation and SQL</title>
<para>
Virtuoso offers XPATH as a query language for XML views. The statement is there converted into SQL in the context 
of the mapping defined by the __view XPATH option, which is mandatory. An XPATH query string is a valid top 
level SQL statement. This is interpreted as a single select or union of selects with the result columns 
being specified by various XPATH options. 
The basic query string 
</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
XPATH [__view "xmlview_name"] /xpath_query
]]></programlisting>
<para>
The same functionality can be got by the following query:
</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
select * from (XPATH '[__view "xmlview_name"]/xpath_query')n
]]></programlisting>
<para>Xml view can be created by two methods:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem> using CREATE XML VIEW statement </listitem>
  <listitem> using Annotated XSD Schemas</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
  The second method is described in &apos;Using Annotated XSD Schemas for Creating XML View&apos; chapter 
  of this tutorial.
</para>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="XP-V-1b">
<title>CREATE XML VIEW statement</title>
<para>
The XML view declaration establishes a 'virtual document' a context within which XML hierarchy relationships 
can be translated into arbitrary joins. The virtual document can be then materialized into an actual set of persistent 
XML elements or used to generate SQL from XPATH. 
The XML view declaration corresponds to the grammar rules described in XML Support chapter, Virtuoso XML Services section.
</para>
			<para>
Each table in the declaration generates an element into the result
document. SQL views can be used as tables to accommodate for hidden joins, sub-queries, ordering and
aggregates. If a view is used, which by nature has no primary key, the primary key
clause should be used to define a uniquely identifying set of view columns.
	</para>
			<para>
Each level of the hierarchy is declared as a list of child elements. Each such element maps
one table or view into an entity according to a join condition.  The join conditions
can reference columns from the associated table and columns from tables in parent elements.
The join condition can also have scalar filtering conditions. A top element&apos;s join
condition may only specify scalar conditions.  
</para>
			<para>
Each set of sibling child nodes is delimited by braces {}.  The top 
level of the view typically consists of one element in the outermost braces.  This element 
has itself a child list delimited by braces.  Each such list can have more than 
one different element. 
</para>
			<para>
Each element specifies:
</para>
			<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
				<listitem>
					<para>SQL table</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Correlation name for use in subsequent joins for this table</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>XML element name to use for delimiting a row of this table</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>List of columns, with optional XML element or attribute names</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>join condition - will relate rows of this table to rows of the table in the enclosing element.
  If this element is at the top level, this can only consist of scalar conditions</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Optional PRIMARY KEY clause, needed if the table in this element is a view, does not 
  have a primary key or if a non-primary key unique identity is desired</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Optional ELEMENT flag</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Optional list of child elements, delimited by braces</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
The column list can mention a single column or a single column renamed into an
XML attribute of a different name. If a column of a table is referenced in a subsequent join
condition it must appear in the output columns list.  Expressions are not directly allowed
but a view with expression columns can be used.
	</para>
			<para>
The opt_public clause, when present, offers a shorthand for calling xml_view_publish 
at the same time as making the definition.  This makes a DAV resource reflecting the contents 
of the view.  The contents may either be generated on demand or persisted as a DAV accessible XML document.
In the latter case the document may be regenerated at a fixed interval. The interval is 
expressed in minutes.
	</para>
			<para>
The path is expressed as an absolute path from the root collection of the DAV server.
	</para>

</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="XP-V-1c">
				<title>Examples</title>
				<programlisting>
create xml view &quot;cat&quot; as
{
  &quot;Demo&quot;.&quot;demo&quot;.&quot;Categories&quot; &quot;C&quot; as &quot;category&quot;
	(&quot;CategoryID&quot;, &quot;Description&quot; as &quot;description&quot;)
    {
      &quot;Demo&quot;.&quot;demo&quot;.&quot;Products&quot; &quot;P&quot; as &quot;product&quot;  (&quot;ProductName&quot;)
	on (&quot;P&quot;.&quot;CategoryID&quot; = &quot;C&quot;.&quot;CategoryID&quot;)
    }
}
</programlisting>
				<para>
This declares a two level hierarchy with a category node for each category
and a product child node for each product in the category.
</para>
				<programlisting><![CDATA[
create xml view "cats_e" as
  select "category"."CategoryID", "CategoryName", 
    "ProductName", "ProductID"
    from "Demo".."Categories" "category", "Demo".."Products" as "product" 
    where "product"."CategoryID" = "category"."CategoryID" element;
]]></programlisting>
				<para>Here is a similar example, this time using the element option.</para>
<programlisting><![CDATA[
create xml view "product" as
{
  "Demo"."demo"."Products" p as "product" 
      ("ProductID", "ProductName" as "product_name","UnitPrice" as "price", "SupplierID","CategoryID")
    {
      "Demo"."demo"."Suppliers" s as "supplier"  ("CompanyName")
	on (s."SupplierID" = p."SupplierID")
       ,
      "Demo"."demo"."Categories_aux" c as "category"  ("Description")
	on (c."CategoryID" = p."CategoryID")

    }
}
]]></programlisting>
<para>
This declares a two level hierarchy with a product node for each product
and a supplier and category children node for each supplier and category in the product.

</para>
</refsect1>

</refentry>

