<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2016 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<refentry id="SO-S-6">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>SOAP</refentrytitle>
    <refmiscinfo>tutorial</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>WSDL service</refname>
    <refpurpose>Generating HTML based Service interactions from a WSDL file</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

<refsect1 id="SO-S-6a">
<title>Web services architecture</title>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem>Service providers deploy and publish services by registering them with the Service broker.</listitem>
  <listitem>Service requesters find services by searching the Service broker's registry of published services.</listitem>
  <listitem>Service requesters bind to the Service provider and consume the available services.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="SO-S-6b">
<title>Technology Uses</title>
In the world of Web services, each of these three operations involves three complimentary yet distinct technologies:
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem>Publishing services uses the Universal Description, Discovery and Integration (UDDI) API</listitem>
  <listitem>Locating services uses a combination of UDDI and the Web Services Description Language (WSDL)</listitem>
  <listitem>Binding to services leverages WSDL and the Simple Object Access Protocol (SOAP).</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>At the most basic level, the Binding operation is the most important of the three.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="SO-S-6c">
<title>Example</title>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem>The example will create a SOAP based interface and WSDL description for searching an existing Customer Order</listitem>
  <listitem>New orders can be added into the demo database.</listitem>
  <listitem>The first page renders the WSDL as an HTML form for selecting the SOAP method.</listitem>
  <listitem>The second page renders the WSDL again to make a form for input parameters. Note that on this 
      entry form needs to be entered valid _CustomerID (for example ALFKI) and _ProductID (for example is 1).
      Otherwise the servce will generate SOAP Fault message. Also _ShipVia needs to have a correct value 
      to be entered (for example 1,2 or 3).  
  </listitem>
  <listitem>Final page displays the result from the SOAP call.</listitem>
</itemizedlist> 
</refsect1>
</refentry>
