<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- 
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2013 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<refentry id="xpf_filter">
  <refmeta> 
    <refentrytitle>filter</refentrytitle> 
    <refmiscinfo>XPATH</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta> 
  <refnamediv> 
    <refname>filter</refname> 
    <refpurpose>Composes trees of shallow copies of given XML entities.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv> 
  <refsynopsisdiv> 
    <funcsynopsis id="xpf_syn_filter"> 
      <funcprototype id="xpf_proto_filter">
        <funcdef>node-set <function>filter</function></funcdef> 
	<paramdef><parameter>selection</parameter> sequence</paramdef>
      </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
  <refsect1 id="xpf_desc_filter"><title>Description</title>
<para>The function takes a single parameter which can be any expression.
The function evaluates its argument and returns a shallow copy of the nodes that are selected by the argument,
preserving any relationships that exist among these nodes. Duplicate nodes are removed before the processing.
</para>
<para>The structure of the resulting node-set may be explained in the following way.
First of all, all input entities are grouped by their documents, so we have a set of distinct documents and
for every document we have a list of entities that refers to various nodes of the document.
After that, every such document is processed separately, and the result of processing is a node-set;
the union of these node-sets will be returned as the result of the call of filter() function.
A copy of the document is made, and a &quot;color&quot; is assigned to every node of the copy:
it's &quot;black if the original node is listed in the <parameter>selection</parameter> sequence,
otherwise it's &quot;white&quot;. Then &quot;white&quot; nodes are removed from the copy, node after node:
if a &quot;white&quot; node may be found, it is replaced with list of its children. Finally, we have a list of
one or more &quot;black&quot; nodes whose descendants are all &quot;black&quot;, too, and this list is
added into the resulting node-set.
</para>
<para>(The actual algorithm is much faster and much more complicated than the described one, but the result is identical.)
</para>
<para>Note that this function is defined in XQuery standard, not in XPath, but in Virtuoso it may be used freely in expression of any kind.</para>
</refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="xpf_params_filter"><title>Parameters</title>
    <refsect2><title>selection</title>
      <para>The sequence of nodes that should be included into the result</para></refsect2>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="xpf_ret_filter"><title>Return Types</title><para>Node-set</para></refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="xpf_errors_filter"><title>Errors</title>
    <table><title>Errors signalled by filter()</title>
      <tgroup cols="4">
       <thead><row><entry>SQLState</entry><entry>Error Code</entry><entry>Error Text</entry><entry>Description</entry></row></thead>
	<tbody>
	  <row>
	    <entry><errorcode>XP001</errorcode></entry>
	    <entry><errorcode>XPFB0</errorcode></entry>
	    <entry><errorname>The argument of XQUERY function filter() must be a sequence of XML entities</errorname></entry>
	    <entry>According to the XQuery standard, the function should signal an error if input contains values other than XML entity.</entry>
	  </row>
	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="xpf_examples_filter"><title>Examples</title>
    <example id="xpf_ex_filter"><title>Composing table of contents</title>
      <para>The following example is from the XQuery standard and it
illustrates how filter() might be used to compute a table of contents
for a document that contains many levels of nested sections.
The query filters the document, retaining only section elements,
title elements nested directly inside section elements,
and the text of those title elements.
Other elements, such as paragraphs and figure titles, are eliminated, leaving only the "skeleton" of the document.
The example generates a table of contents for a document named &quot;cookbook.xml&quot;.</para>
<screen>
&lt;toc&gt;
   {
   filter(document("cookbook.xml") //
      (section | section/title | section/title/text()))
   }
&lt;/toc&gt;
</screen>
    </example>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1 id="xpf_seealso_filter"><title>See Also</title>
    <para><link linkend="xpf_shallow">shallow()</link></para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>

