<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2019 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<refentry id="RP-S-1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>WS Routing</refentrytitle>
    <refmiscinfo>tutorial</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>Making an SOAP router endpoint</refname>
    <refpurpose>Setting up a SOAP router endpoint</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

<refsect1 id="RP-S-1a">
<title>Example</title>
<para>
This chapter describes general guide lines for using routing capabilities of the Virtuoso SOAP server.
</para>
<para>
In order to have the rest of examples of this section working, the following steps must be performed.
</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
 <listitem>If you are going to try .NET examples the MS WSDK toolkit must be installed on a W2K machine. The .NET examples are tested with 1.0.0.0 version of Microsoft.WSDK.dll, so make sure that version of that assembly is the same.</listitem>
 <listitem>Make sure that WS Routing examples of MS WSDK working before trying any of interoperability examples.</listitem>
 <listitem>From this page run the setup script (set the initial state), this will define the routing and ultimate endpoints. </listitem>
</itemizedlist> 

<para>
The SOAP directory option we are using to setup a WS Routing (SOAP router) is:
</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem> WS-RP - yes/no , this is to enable WS Routing filter</listitem>
</itemizedlist> 

<para>
The VSP page is example how Virtuoso SOAP client can be used to invoke the sample services as AddInt or echoString.Form this page we can invoke these operations via different routers. Note that "Operation to invoke" option must be set properly depending of type of endpoint (see remarks on select page).
</para>

<para>
The .NET client example must be complied before trying it. To do this follow the steps:
</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem>Change in the RoutingClient.cs and referalCache.config files &lt;virtuoso:port&gt; to host and port where your virtuoso HTTP server is listening.</listitem>
<listitem>compile the example issuing nmake command in the tutorial/services/rp_s_1 directory. On that step you may need to have .NET Visual Studio installed and .NET Framework SDK</listitem>
<listitem>if you going to compile the client on an other box, make sure that referralCache.config file is in the same directory where is .exe file.</listitem>
</itemizedlist> 

</refsect1>
</refentry>
