<!--
 -  
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -  
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2016 OpenLink Software
 -  
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -  
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -  
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -  
 -  
-->
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<refentry id="VS-S-1">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>Web Server Setup</refentrytitle>
    <refmiscinfo>tutorial</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>Mapping Requests to Resources</refname>
    <refpurpose>General information about the virtual host/directory mechanism</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

<refsect1 id="VS-S-1a">
<title>Listening Interface Concepts</title>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem>A single Virtuoso server can accept HTTP requests on multiple interfaces.</listitem>
  <listitem>Listening interfaces are defined via a virtual directory mechanism (not based on INI setting).</listitem>
  <listitem>Virtual directory operation can be stopped or started without restarting the server engine.</listitem>
  <listitem>The request accepted on a given interface can be processed in a separate Web space.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="VS-S-1b">
<title>Virtual Host</title>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem>The term Virtual Host refers to the practice of maintaining more than one server on one machine, as differentiated
by their apparent host name. For example, it is often desirable for companies sharing a web server to have their
own domains, with web servers accessible as www.company1.com and www.company2.com, without requiring the user to
know any extra path information. The Virtual host can be IP-based or non-IP.</listitem>
  <listitem>The IP-based (named in this document as multihosting) refers to the practice of making one machine listen on
different interfaces and respond with different pages.</listitem>
  <listitem>The non-IP (named virtual hosting) refers to the practice where one machine is allocated more than one DNS
alias. The web content served can then be based on the alias that the client contacted, as identified by the
'Host' HTTP header field.</listitem>
  <listitem>A single Virtuoso server can map requests into multiple spaces of web pages based on the interface to
  which the requests come (multihosting) or on the Host HTTP/1.1 header (virtual hosting).</listitem>
  <listitem>A single physical interface can map multiple virtual hosts.</listitem>
  <listitem>The virtual host name must be defined also in Domain Name Server as an alias of the official host name.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="VS-S-1c">
<title>Attributes</title>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem>Logical Path - The path part from URL which user-agent wants.</listitem>
  <listitem>Mapped Path - Defacto location of requested Web resource.</listitem>
  <listitem>Is in DAV - The Virtuoso server has space for Distributed Authoring &amp; Versioning (DAV see: rfc2518 for details) under "/DAV" URL. The logical path can me mapped in to this space.</listitem>
  <listitem>Default page - The name of page or resource on Web server to show if a directory/folder is requested. It applies to the entire subdirectory tree.</listitem>
  <listitem>Is browseable - If no default page specified or page does not exist, then show directory content. Warning: This setting can raise security problems, because all directory content will be shown.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="VS-S-1d">
<title>Security</title>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem>The Web server has access to the file system directory (see ServerRoot INI setting) using the privileges
	of the user who is running it.</listitem>
  <listitem>Access to the WebDAV repository can be restricted to only special accounts, as each resource/folder can
   have different permissions applied.</listitem>
  <listitem>Execution in a mapped path can be enabled/disabled.</listitem>
  <listitem>Basic and Digest HTTP authentication schemes can be used.</listitem>
  <listitem>HTTPS listeners can be started.</listitem>
  <listitem>User-agent's certificate can be requested and checked.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="VS-S-1e">
<title>Authentication Function</title>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem>An application dependant PL function for HTTP authentication can be defined for each path mapping.</listitem>
  <listitem>The authentication function can be used to restore session variables.</listitem>
  <listitem>The built-in authentication functions can be used.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="VS-S-1f">
<title>Request Postprocessing Function</title>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem>An application dependant PL function can be defined for each path mapping to store the session variables
  (in session table).</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="VS-S-1g">
<title>Database User Accounts for execution of active content</title>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem>Database User Account for VSP: For each path mapping, a different Database account can be supplied.
  The VSP will be executed on behalf of this account.</listitem>
  <listitem>Database user account for SOAP: For each path mapping, the SOAP calls can be assign to a different Database
  account. The WSDL schema will show only PL procedures granted to this account.</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="VS-S-1h">
<title>Example Listen host &amp; Virtual host mappings</title>
<para>It is possible to have a mapping in the file system /www1/ for  http://www.a.com/ requests.
    In this case we will specify the listen host www.a.com (the port default is 80), logical path / and
	physical location /www1/.</para>
<para>In some cases more than one web server is needed on the same machine. A second DNS alias www.b.com can
	be routed to the www.a.com. A mapping for this alias can then be: listen host is again www.a.com but virtual host is
	www.b.com and physical location can be a /www2/ under HTTP root directory. When a User-Agent requests the
	http://www.b.com/ it will send a 'Host' header field, in this field value will be 'www.b.com'. The web server will
	find a second map and will try to process the pages under /www2/.</para>
</refsect1>

<refsect1 id="VS-S-1i">
<title>Finding the closest applicable mapping</title>
<para>Its possible to define more than one mapping for one virtual/listen host combination. In this case the closest
match to the request is used. For example with the following mappings:</para>
<table border="1">
<tr><th>Logical Path</th><th>Physical Path</th></tr>
<tr><td>www.a.com/</td><td>/www/a</td></tr>
<tr><td>www.a.com/a</td><td>/www/b</td></tr>
</table>
<para>Gets the following mapping:</para>
<table border="1">
<tr><th>Request</th><th>Physical Path</th></tr>
<tr><td>http://www.a.com/a/</td><td>/www/b</td></tr>
<tr><td>http://www.a.com/other</td><td>/www/a/other</td></tr>
</table>
<para>The Web server will find the closest path match when processing the logical to physical mapping.</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>
